breaking news
five time MBA
champion Kobe Bryant
died in helicopter crash
a high profile aviation
accident devastates Los Angeles
NTSB investigators
quickly inspect the wreckage
all the mechanical systems
electronic systems
appeared to be working fine
the data provides a detail
picture of the entire flight
so they get airborne just after 9:00
and then again held up for 12 minutes
November 2 echo x-ray
hold at site
Burbank airspace
okay we'll hold at site
Burbank
certainly this added
to the time of the flight
he's bombing along
here about 140 knots
investigators must
consider the unthinkable
was he trying to make
up for the last time?
a lot of people wonder if
Kobe being Kobe might have
put pressure on this pilot
but there is no evidence
to support that suspicion
so what happened to this guy?
hey rick
I'm gonna go straight
north to Dodger Stadium
around Burbank
and follow the 118 to get up
and around the weather down here
what's visibility
of Burbank?
broken clouds with
5 miles of visibility
we're good to go
Ara Zobayan is a helicopter pilot
with more than 8000 flying hours
they'll be here about 15 minutes
I'll meet them here
and help them get loaded
roger that
he is the chief pilot
for Island Express
helicopter charter company based
in California Los Angeles county
Island Express is a
family owned company
that's been in southern
California for a number of decades
and they're known as a company
that can provide VIP helicopter service
amongst their high
profile regular customers
media star kyle Jenner
LA Clipper's superstar
Kawhi Leonard
and today's client
LA Lakers great Kobe Bryant
Kobe Bryant was one of the
best basketball players of all time
he is an iconic
Los Angeles Laker
he was drafted by the team in
1996 when he was 17 years old
he became a heart and
soul of the team for 20 years
he won five world
championships
he went to the all
star game 18 times
and really
just became a huge star in
his own right apart from the team
and that he was recognized
simply by his first name Kobe
how is everyone doing today?
Ara Zobayan has flown Kobe
and his family dozens of times
let's get going
Kobe and the pilot of this
helicopter really become friends
because he had piloted him so many
times around southern California that
they developed the relationship
Kobe Bryant flies in
luxury Sikorsky S-76B
it's configured to
carry 8 passengers
the Sikorsky S-76B is
sort of like an air limousine
and that is quite
common for VIP travel
I think heads of state
use it in different countries
and it also uses sort of air
ambulance in some situations
spacious and reliable
it really considered
about safe as they come
Kobe
his daughter Gianna
and six others are headed to a
basketball tournament near Camarillo
18 miles away
Kobe is the team's coach
Gianna
the star player
today's 13 minute flight will take
the helicopter north passed Burbank
and then west
towards Camarillo
Zobayan will follow two
highways for guidance
the five
north west
and the 101
west to Camarillo
hey everyone it's about
to get loud back there
copter 72 echo x-ray
I express for island departure
helicopter 72
echo x-ray
clear for departure
from island express
have a good flight
good flight to echo x-ray
just after 9:00AM
the helicopter lifts
off from Santa Ana
the destination is Kobe
Bryant's Mamba Sport Academy
it's a regular
journey for Zobayan
he flew the same group
there a back yesterday
he was a very experienced pilot
he was able to fly the
helicopter at speed at low altitude
in a very dense airspace and
deal with weather at the same time
since his early days as a player, Kobe
Bryant has preferred helicopter travel
to the crowded freeways
of southern California
he routinely uses helicopters for
his personal and professional travel
Kobe loved to fly by helicopter just
because he loved how much time it saved him
Kurt Deetz also flew
for island express
flying in LA is
like no where else
there is a large congestion
of multiple type of airspace
in small area
so you always in
and out of airspace
today's flight
will first need to past through the
control airspace surrounding Burbank
and then Van Nuys
Burbank, helicopter 72
echo x-ray Sikorsky helicopter
approaching the zone for
a 101 westbound transition
Zobayan requests permission to
past through Burbank airspace
it's a very busy airport
and the controllers
they don't know
what they're doing
November 72 echo x-ray
Burbank tower
Burbank class charlie is IFR
say intentions
Burbank is only
accepting IFR flights
or instrument flight rules
which requires pilot to
navigate solely on instruments
Zobayan however is only authorized
to fly using visual flight rules (VFR)
the threshold for the visual
flight is normally 3 miles
the Burbank airport
was 2.5 miles
within sufficient
visibility for VFR
the controller
denies his request
but zobayan has been flying helicopter
in southern California long enough
to know a way
around this restriction
asking for special VFR
transition to the 101 westbound
special VFR allows him to operate
at lower than standard visibilities
down to 1 mile of visibility
and that's an agreement
you have with the tower saying
I'm here
I wanna go there
I'm requesting a special VFR
special VFR allows zobayan to navigate
visually through the area of low visibility
November 2 echo x-ray
hold outside Burbank airspace
I have an aircraft going
around in an inbound citation
the controller authorizes zobayan
to cross into Burbank airspace
but under the
rules of special VFR
he must now wait until the
airspace is clear of traffic
okay we'll hold outside Burbank
2 echo x-ray
hey everyone
we'll have to circle
here for a few minutes
while we wait for a few
planes to get out our way
it shouldn't delay too much
anytime you have a hold
because you mean late
finally after holding
for 12 minutes
the Burbank airspace clears
and zobayan is
allowed to pass through
November 2 echo x-ray
clear to Burbank
maintain special VFR
copy that
we'll maintain special VFR
copter 2 echo x-ray
from Burbank
the helicopter will follow
the I-5 freeway northwest
and the 118 around the
the top of Van Nuys airspace
the south to follow
the 101 to Camarillo
Kobe Bryant and the other passengers
are anticipated to arrive in Camarillo
just a few minutes
behind schedule
Van Nuys
helicopter 2 echo x-ray with you
for the special VFR transition
helicopter 72 echo x-ray
cleared into Van Nuys along
the 118 freeway westbound
the helicopter is clear to pass
through the airspace near Van Nuys
zobayan now dials in the
final controller for this journey
the southern California
radar approach controller
who will handle the flight
until it reaches Camarillo
helicopter 72 echo x-ray
with you at 570 to Camarillo
Southern California approach
roger, are you just gonna stay down
that low all the way to Camarillo?
the helicopter is flying
570 feet above the ground
yes sir, low altitude
2 echo x-ray
zobayan needs to
stay bellow the clouds
which are around 1000
feet above the ground
when he went
was a lowest amount available
because of the weather
roger, I'm gonna use
radar with you surely
but at the low
altitude in hilly terrain
controllers won't be able to
maintain radar contact with the flight
the controllers will not
see him on radar you so low
copy that
2 echo x-ray
less than 10 minutes
from his destination
the visibility gets worse
in the Lose Angeles basin area
it's well known to get
the supreme layer of
colder water,
temperatures, warmer air
where you get these low
clouds and you get lower visibility
zobayan radio is in his intention
to climb above some low clouds
we're gonna go ahead start
our climb to go above the layers
2 echo x-ray
where are you?
just west of Van Nuys
2 echo x-ray
ident
the controller hasn't been
tracking the helicopter
he needs zobayan to
flash his transponder signals
so he can located on his screen
you press the button
of transponder that
flashes on their radar screen
so they know where you are
ident
2 echo x-ray
say intentions
we're climbing to 4000
2 echo x-ray
and what are you gonna
do when you reach altitude?
in the hills near Calabasas
witnesses see a helicopter
emerge from the clouds
and hit the ground
the team tracking
Kobe Bryant's flight
realizes something's going wrong
the helicopter should have
landed at Camarillo by now
it's disappeared
from their flight tracker
we have some breaking news
a helicopter crash in southern
California Lose Angeles county
sheriff's deputies responding
to reports of that crash
just before 10:00
am pacific time
it's located in the
Calabasas area
it doesn't take long before the
media is reporting the tragic news
Kobe Bryant
his 13 year old daughter
along with 7 other people
have been killed in
the helicopter crash
it's just one of those things
where you can read the words and
you kind of process
them but you don't really
it's hard for thinking because
you've got to think about
that he's never coming back
he was the guy, he was
my icon, my role model
who got me into this world
who got me playing
you won't see another
player like him again
this what we missed
there is this tremendous
outpouring of grief in Lose Angeles
people flock the staple center
left all different
kinds of mementos
this is much bigger
than basketball I think
just because
I think Kobe was a real symbol
you know of just hard work, dedication
everybody was really just
heartsick by what happened
love you Kobe, love you
Gigi, and all the family
we're here to conduct
a safety investigation
and our mission is not to
just determine what happened
but why it happened
and how it happened
to prevent a similar accident
from ever happening again
the NTSB begins its
investigation at the crash site
looking for any clues to explain
why a state of the art helicopter
being flown by highly
experienced pilot
crashed 24 miles
short of its destination
the first think you
do with the crash site
is try to see that all the
components make it to the crash site
was there any kind
of mechanical failure
did a rotor blade break
or tail rotor come off
the team uses a drone to scan the accident
site and study the shape of the debris
look at this accident site
is very clear
this was a relatively
high rate of descent
the helicopter pit
and the wreckage then bounced
about 90 feet where came to rest
so there is a lot more
vertical speed here
than you have horizontal speed
and all the parts of helicopter
made it to the accident site
investigator study
flight control surfaces
the engines and rotors
as well as the helicopter's
flight instruments
examinations components found that there
was no evidence of any pre impact failures
that all the mechanical
system, electronic systems
everything at that time
appeared to be working fine
the NTSB's Bill English
has led investigation
into some of the world's most
notorious aviation accidents
we need to cover all
our bases on this one
knowing there is a high
profile person on board
obviously NTSB responded
with a major investigation team
okay
he takes off at 9:07
he flies north west
to better understand
what happened
investigators piece together a
detailed flight path from an ADS B system
that's on board the
Sikorsky helicopter
ADS B data is like
transponder data
controllers can
see these recorded
your airspeed, altitude and
heading, other information
and so you have
this plotting capability
look like there is some
kind of hold here at Burbank
he follows the i5 to Van Nuys
south to the 101 which he
follows until he makes this U turn
straight into a hell site
you'd see this turn to left
where he's coming back
around or doing something
and that question is
now in the investigation
what is exactly the
pilot doing here?
let's take a look at visibility
they study visibility reports from
weather station along the route
he did manage to
avoid the worst of it here
but socked in the
Burbank and Van Nuys
but nothing he can't get through
4 mile of visibility
when he got near the Burbank
air port, it's 2.5 miles of visibility
that still totally flyable for him
in fact by his
operation specifications
he could go down
to 1 mile of visibility
okay
I get it
if the visibility was down to zero
but this wasn't enough bad
so what happened to this guy?
why do we have a high time pilot
in a aircraft capable of flight
and visibility conditions he
should have been able to handle
either lose control or somehow
inadvertently flies
helicopter in the ground
that becomes a key
piece of investigation
we need to figured out
what he get actually see
we have a request for the public
we're looking for photos
of the weather in
the area of the crash
if you could send those photos
to witness@.gov
investigators make a plea
to the public for evidence
regarding the island
express helicopter crash
that took the lives of
Kobe Bryant and 8 others
they're looking for clues to
explain how the pilot, Ara Zobayan
ended up hitting a hillside
on a route he knew well
more than 8300 flying hours
instructor on their 73
chief pilot at island express
apparently Kobe's favorite pilot
bit of a superstar
this pilot was not a rookie
who just got his license
he was one of LA's
top helicopter pilots
working for one of
it's top companies
with some of its most
high profile clients
record show that at 7:00 am
on the morning of the flight
zobayan checked the weather
for his preflight risk assessment
and determine that even
there were low hanging clouds
blanketing the area
the flight was low risk
a risk assessment is
weather, anxiety, sleep
all these factors
are going to a flight
but a low lying cloud layer
surrounding Lose Angeles
known as a marine layer
forced zobayan to alter
his regular more direct route
because of the weather he flew
more inland than he normally does
sort of a back door way
in to where they're going
based on the forecast
this plan was okay
pretty good visibility
all along the way
so what went wrong?
investigators need to understand
the exact conditions zobayan flew into
in the final
moments of the flight
these are three separate cameras
all facing cells towards the 101
couldn't ask for a better view
the NTSB's plea for pictures
of the weather pays off
a nearby baseball facility
had surveillance cameras
pointed a key sections of the
flight path as the helicopter flew past
let's see what this one
shows on a clear day
investigators compare images from
the same camera taking on a clear day
to images recorded at
the time of the accident
yeah, perfect
okay, so
one minute before the accident, the
helicopter would be bombing along here
I can't see it
how close did it
get to the camera?
best view of it would be here
that's 4400 feet
the helicopter is less than
a mile from the camera
but isn't visible
okay so what
about larger objects?
this hills for instance
visible on the clear day
but not at the time of the crash
that hill top is 8000 feet away
so visibility beneath the
clouds was less that 8000 feet
it's mile and half
the video study tells investigators
that around the time of the accident
zobayan would not have been
able to see any further than 1.5 miles
you only allow to fly in
visibilities one mile and greater
mile and a half
pretty low
pretty minimum
investigators know zobayan
would have been able to fly safely
bellow the clouds
with 1.5 mile visibility
so what if he was actually
above the cloud base?
so he was only
415 feet above the ground
the cloud ceiling
the base of the cloud layer was
reported to be 1100 feet near Van Nuys
but zobayan was flying about
450 feet above the ground
which would put him
well bellow the clouds
there are images from the
camera on the 101 facing west
okay
you can just make him out here
actually heading into fairly heavy cloud
same camera
3 seconds later
it's disappeared
we have a witness
who said that she saw the helicopter
disappeared into what she described as
a thick wall of heavy clouds
the NTSB had quite a few very
good witnesses in my opinion
and they also had
cameras in the area
so they can collect data in real time of
what this pilot would have been encountering
the surveillance data shows them
only 450 feet above the ground
so the cloud base was no more
than 450 feet above the ground
not the 1100 feet which was
being reported along its root
the reported an airport five
miles away can be greatly different
than what you're encountering
because of uplifting winds
and that type of
thing around the hills
the area near Calabasas
has its own unique climate
the Malibu Canyon can
channel fog up from pacific ocean
that fog is known to pull precisely where
zobayan was seeing flying into clouds
the fog gathers
here at murrell road
and this is where our witnesses
saw him enter the clouds
investigators have determined that
just over a minute before the accident
zobayan flew into dense cloud that would
have reduce his visibility to near zero
that clinches it
he flew into IMC
IMC
Instrument meteorological conditions
is when visibility is so poor that
pilots need to fly only on instruments
they were only authorized
to fly into visual flight rules
legally he's not allow to enter
he's only allowed to go
in visual conditions only
and yet he did
in aviation there is a term for VFR pilots
who fly into low visibility conditions
it's called an inadvertent
encounter with IMC
it can happen at night
flying into clouds that you didn't see
it can happen that you're
choosing to avoid something
and you inadvertently
go into clouds
unfortunately to accident
happens way too often
inadvertent IMC is a leading cause of
aviation accident over the past ten years
more than 80 percent
of them are fatal
you can't see
where the horizon is
and you can't see the
sky from the ground
you don't know visually
which is our main sense
you have to rely on secondary
senses such as sense of balance
and they are
illusions that come up
an inadvertent encounter with instruments
conditions is so potentially dangerous
that pilots train to do
whatever they can to avoid it
how did he get himself
into the situation?
let's see his speed and altitude
the data from the ADS B gives
investigators a detailed picture
of the helicopter
altitude and speed
as it approach Calabasas
if zobayan try to avoid
the worsening conditions
the data would show it
he's bombing along
here about 140 knots
visibility is getting
worse and worse
but he's not slowing down
he's not turning around
he just keeps going
why?
he could have turn around
landed at Van Nuys
he could have circle for a while
near the airport
wait for the
conditions to improved
for whatever reason
we don't know
he chose none of those options
the team now considers
the widely held belief
that zobayan was pressured to continue
the flight by his high profile passenger
a lot of people wonder
after the crash happened
if Kobe being Kobe might
have put pressure on this pilot
to get to where he wanted to go
because that's the whole reason that he was
taking the helicopter in the first place
is to get from point A to point B
and do it without unnecessary delays
the same passengers take the
same flight a day before the accident
they scheduled
to take off at 9:45
but Kobe changed that to 9:00
they move it up by 45 minutes, so that Kobe
could watch another team or team's play
in preparation for his daughter's
basketball tournament on Sunday
so they get airborne
just after nine
and then this happens
they're held up for 12 minutes
November 2 echo x-ray
hold at site Burbank airspace
I have an aircraft going
around in an inbound citation
investigators know that kobe's helicopter
was held up at Burbank for 12 minutes
while zobayan waited for traffic
to clear the control airspace
okay we'll hold at site Burbank
2 echo x-ray
a little more than
10 minutes later
zobayan flew into thick cloud cover
that speed at speed of 160 miles an hour
as he approach Camarillo
in my opinion 140
knots is probably
twice speed he should have
operating in those visual condition
he should have slow it down
was he trying to make
up for the last time?
the team digs into Kobe Bryant
previous flights with island express
to see if there is any history
of him putting pressure on pilots
he took 26 flights with
island express last year
and not once did he
pressure a pilot to keep going
Kobe would never
put pressure a pilot
I flew him for two years
not once
was there ever any
amount of pressure from him
investigators find no evidence that
Kobe Bryant or any member of his team
put pressure on zobayan
to continue the flight
they had a history
they scrutinize Kobe Bryant
relationship with Ara zobayan
for anything that could have
effected the pilot's behaviour
on the day of the accident
more than history
the director of operation says that
Kobe's relationship with Ara was, quote:
warm and friendly
he trusted Ara with
his girls and his family
that they always wanted Ara
the company's BP says
that their relationship was
more like a friendship
and that Kobe would
call him Mr pilot man
this guy sure were tight
relationship may have
been pressure enough
how's everyone doing today?
investigators conclude that zobayan
close relationship with Kobe Bryant
may have led to self induced
pressure to get him to his destination
part of the concern here is that the
pilot was trying to complete the mission
in part to satisfy the client
investigators soon find
another important factor
that may have influenced
zobyan's decision making
six minutes before the crash he clears
Van Nuys airspace and head south
tells controller that he planned
to stay low all the way to Camarillo
stay bellow clouds
helicopter 72 echo x-ray
are you just going to stay down
that low all the way to Camarillo?
yes sir, low altitude
2 echo x-ray
two minutes later
he starts following the 101 which
should lead them straight to Camarillo
but as along the 101
for 2 more minutes
until he hits this
wall of clouds
24 miles to go
he's almost there
almost
zobayan was less than 10 minutes away from
getting his passenger to their destination
you're close to finishing
you have a tendency to be
willing to tolerate conditions
might have caused you
not to take the trip originally
the team believes Zobayan
was suffering from a conditions
known as plan continuation bias
when he decided to keep going
despite deteriorating weather conditions
plan continuation bias
is an unconscious bias
to continue with the original plan
even when conditions changed
in an aviation environment
it can be deadly
it doesn't take long for
things to start going wrong
as soon as he enter that cloud
instead of turning around
Zobayan decides to
climb above the clouds
we're gonna go ahead and start
our climb to go above the layers
he start banking
further and further left
descends rapidly
hits the hill here
the pilots unusual actions
lead investigators to wonder
about the level of training he received
he was trained to avoid IMC
and what to do if you got into it
they discover that
zobayan was well trained
to escape the precise
conditions he flew into
this pilot trained routinely
for inadvertently IMC situation
more than that
he was the chief
pilot of the company
he set the safety
standards for all the pilots
and he trained them on how to
deal with instrument conditions
this is what he was thought
a review of zobayan's training
shows that he was
thought to reduce his speed
use the auto pilot to
climb above the clouds
and then declare an emergency
his training was good
but did zobayan
follow his training?
here he is entering
an area of low visibility
still flying well
above 100 knots
no evidence of slowing down
investigators know
zobayan did not reduce speed
they now wonder if he
engage the auto pilot
play
we're gonna go ahead start
our climb to go above the layers
look at that rate of climb
1500 feet a minute
can be auto pilot doing that?
that exceeds the authority
the auto pilot system
therefore this climb was
being manually controlled
all right
but at this point he's just trying to
get above the clouds without auto pilot
the higher zobayan
climbs into the dense cloud
the worse the visibility gets
but he never asks for help
well he never
reports an emergency
and never mentions being an IMC
one thing he should
have been saying
many many many
tell you're in emergency
he didn't slow down
he didn't use auto pilot
and never declare an emergency
he ignored all his training
they are basic procedures
that should be followed
and you have to
have the very cautious
on approach to any sort
of instrument conditions
this was not evident in the
way the pilot flew that day
by ignoring his training
zobayan found himself in a
rapid climb with no visibility
and without the
help of the auto pilot
prime conditions for
becoming spatially disoriented
Annmarie landman studies the
effect of spatial disorientation in pilots
if you take away outside
visual reference from a pilots
then he or she will really
have to trust their instruments
because if you don't have
outside visual reference
then any sensation that you
feel can be very misleading
did Ara zobayan suffer
the effects of disorientation
after flying into dense clouds?
2 echo x-ray
say intentions
zobayan's last words show
that's precisely what happened
we're climbing to 4000
2 echo x-ray
did you hear that?
it's like he completely
lost his bearings
the recording tells investigators
that zobayan believed he was climbing
when he was actually descending
rapidly towards the ground
in a steep left turn
it's what aviators
called the graved spiral
so ride that aircraft
no, in the mountains area
you're not
you're absolutely not
the team has pieced
together a picture of a pilot
who flew into prime conditions
for causing disorientation
zobayan's problem starts just
after he flies into the cloud
he decides the best
thing to do is fly above it
but as he climbs
visibility worsens
and his reference to the highway
bellow and the horizon ahead
quickly disappear
it's all but impossible for pilots to
determine a plane's pitch and roll
without a visual reference
to their surroundings
without visual cues
the human body is unable to
maintain its special bearings
the result is disorientation
as the highway bellow veers left
zobayan tries to stay with it
he puts the helicopter
into a gradual left turn
he's not looking at the
instruments at this point
he was perhaps looking down
too search for the highway
that he was following before
2 echo x-ray
ident
zobayan now faces a distraction that
makes the situation significantly worse
ident
he is forced to identify
himself to the controller
it's not only a distraction
it forces him to move his head which
increases the risk of disorientation
we advise pilots to
not move their head around when they're
flying without outside visual reference
this is moving the
fluid in your inner ears
and this actually makes you a
little more susceptible to illusions
the highway now
veers off to the right
but he's lost sight of it
he's banking further
and further to the left
without even realizing it
30 seconds from impact
disorientation sets in
the turn is so gradual
and it is so slow
that the onset
it seems that he's
not feeling that
so for him stills feels
that he's flying left
and he gets to 600
feet and start to descend
without even knowing it
it's clear that prior
to the accident
the pilot really didn't know
what the helicopter was doing
because he was
asked his intentions
and he indicated that he
was climbing to 4000 feet
we're climbing to 4000
2 echo x-ray
at that point the
helicopter was not climbing
it was descending
towards a crash
and the pilot didn't realize it
he's now in a rapid descend and
likely looking for clear skies above
not noticing what his
instruments are showing
without having
outside visual references
and not being focused
on your instruments
it's very easy that happen
and it does happen far too often
he's so far over
it's like he's lost his lift
he's plummeting to the ground
graveyard spiral
classic
about a minute after
entering the cloud
he hits the ground like this
almost on his side
at more than 160 knots
there is no sign he ever figured
out what was really happening
Kobe Bryant and 8 others died as
a result of a all 2 common scenario
a helicopter pilot flying IMC
and becoming disoriented
we need something to
help pilots understand that
just because you feel like your
body is being pushed down on the seat
doesn't mean you're climbing
that device exists
and it's helping train
pilots in the Netherlands
the one of a kind
simulator let's researchers
reproduce the feelings
of spacial disorientation
without pilots having
to leave the ground
okay martin so how
are you feeling now?
feeling pitched up
you feel pitched up
yeah
investigators hoping to
prevent the kind of accident
that caused Ara zobayan
to get so badly disoriented
are looking closely at the work
being done in labs like this one
at the Netherlands organization
for applied scientific research
or TNO
we investigate the effects of spacial
disorientation on pilot performance
zobayan believed he was climbing
when he was actually descending
and was unaware that
he was in a steep left turn
he was suffering from two of the
most common illusions effecting pilots
somatogravic involving
his sense of pitch
and Somatogyral
involving his sense of role
spacial disorientation is a factor in about
30 percent of fatal helicopter crashes
this rotating chair helps pilots
experience the effects of the leans
the inability to recognize
that you're in a steep turn
when a pilot starts a turn
the fluid in the inner ear response
and it's telling that
he or she is in a turn
but after a while
the fluid sort of settles
so it's actually feels as if
they're flying level again
this pilot is using his thumbs to show
the direction he believes he's turning
for the first few
seconds he's right
but as the fluid
in his ear settles
he no longer senses the turn
this is the identical illusion
that Ara zobayan experienced
it's why he never realized that
he had entered the gradual left turn
once he lost sight
of the highway bellow
even though his instruments would
have been telling him precisely that
we trained them here to
really trust their instruments
and to really be focused
on their instruments
specially in situations
of low visibility
but the heart of TNO's
facility is this simulator
called Desdemona
so here is just what's
going to happen
just have to wait for our mark
and then you have
to just level the aircraft
but you have to do it
without the instruments
so only based on
your god feelings
it's a disorientation demonstrator
which safely simulates the effects
of pitch and roll illusions on pilots
it's the only one in the world
okay martin
you just first
you just going to fly a little bit to
get quite a bit on the controls, all right
roger
so you have the
instruments available
okay, let's start simulation
unlike simulators that
are attached to the ground
Desdemona can simulate unlimited
degrees of pitch, yaw and roll
as well as the
forces of acceleration
it's really important to have
simulator that can really create a
constant force or constant
force of feels like acceleration
pilot Martin Kemner
is about to experience the
same sensation that zobayan felt
moments before the crash
the instruments in the
simulator are turned off
so he must rely
only on feel
Martin, how are you feeling now?
feeling straight and level
let's ramp up the acceleration
and see how that feels
now we're starting
the centrifuge
and the cabin of the simulator
is pointing towards the center
so for martin is actually just
feels like he's accelerating forwards
the acceleration causes him to
mistake what's actually happening
okay martin
what are you feeling now?
a bit pitched up
and what do you think that
the aircraft is doing now?
we're climbing now
if you're accelerating forwards
the little hairs
in your inner ear
will actually give
a constant signal
that it's the same as if
you're being pitched up
we're climbing to 4000
2 echo x-ray
it's the exact illusion that caused Ara
Zobayan to believe he was still climbing
when his helicopter
was in a steep descent
okay now
bring the nose back to level
yep
sure
so you can see that he's bring
the nose bellow the horizon
for him this
actually feels level
so can we show
him the instrument?
oh my god
more than 10 degrees down
okay
here we cover
we hope that this helps them to
recognize spacial disorientation
when it occurs
definitely we also hope
to teach them some skills
that help them to manage
spacial disorientation if it occurs
hello
that was it
that was crazy
I believed that as a tribute
to the victims of this accident
the industry needs to realize how
common and sinister these effects can be
and develop better
safety standards
as result of NTSB recommendations
the federal aviation administration
is evaluating tools like Desdemona
that can be used to train
more pilots how to recognize
and cope with the
effects of disorientation
the last thing NTSB
was to do is to back
and investigate this kind
of accident all over again
and through the
death of this person
and people on board
hopefully this would be the
one to help improve safety
time will tell