a business jet shuttling
passengers to Akron, Ohio
no no no
slams into a residential neighborhood
less than 2 miles from the runway
we have a plane ...
heavy fire
there are no survivors
investigators searched the
wreckage but find few clues
the aircraft was burned down
to almost nothing on the hill
but a close examination
of radar data
provides a lead
they're clear to descend
and then they wait
full two minutes
why?
we really wondered what is the
situation in the cockpit at that time?
hey you guys you know
where you are going
it's going to be some weather so
I'd like to have your
update with the flight
well did you hear that?
execuflight Flight 1526
is climbing towards
cruising altitude
over the us Midwest
let's keep climbing
with 150 feet per minute
roger
on board are 7 executives from a
Florida base property management company
sorry
they've charted the
luxury jet from execuflight
a private carrier based
in Fort Lauderdale
Donnie Shackleford is a former
captain who flew with execuflight
execuflight caters to the people of
south Florida for business purposes
also to entrepreneurs,
athletes and even entertainers
17,000 feet
roger
leveling off
execuflight 1526 is flying
a short 35 minute flight
north east from
Dayton to Akron Ohio
first officer Renato Marchese is the
pilot flying the twin engine Hawker 700
he's logged more than 4000
hours flying various private jets
Captain Oscar Chávez
is originally from Colombia
and he's logged over 6000 hours
flying private jets and cargo planes
the captain had flown
with me as the first officer