an emergency above the french
Alps strikes trans air cargo flight 671
there was a enormous bang
and the aircraft almost inverted
mayday mayday mayday mayday
the crew needs to
land but are flying blind
kabo 671
we have no radar contact
they stood a very real
chance of hitting a mountain
then they discover
something even more horrifying
I saw nothing in the
number 4 engine position
the wing is clean
assuming the worse
the first officer leaves
a clue for investigators
I took the photograph
because I wasn't sure
what would happen next
if somebody might
find the camera
they see the truth
trans air flight 671 is preparing
for take off at Luxembourg airport
forecast says we'll get
some weather about an hour
that's crossover the alps
typical
captain Ingemar Berglund is
highly experienced Swedish pilot
who’s has been flying Boeing
707 aircraft for over a decade
the captain had
been a military pilot
and he'd been on air transport
flying for most of his working life
these experience
was pretty vast in Africa
and in Europe
he knew the routes
and he was a very good pilot
kabo 671
you're clear for take off
runway 24
clear for take off
roger
first officer Martin Emery
is an accomplished British pilot
who has work as an instructor
and an air traffic controller
ready to go
the first officer had
about 10,000 hours
about half of which
was on the Boeing 707
so he was very experienced too
rotate
the Boeing 707 is
a long range aircraft
powered by 4 Pratt
& Whitney engines
it was a very basic airplane
very strong
very reliable
and could carry 40
or 50 tons of freight
assisting the pilots is
flight engineer Terry Boone
the Boeing 707 didn't have much
in the way of automated systems
but this meant that
there was a whole panel
side ways in the flight deck
in which the flight engineer had
to operate every system manually
he was probably one the most experienced
Boeing 707 flight engineers in the world
today's flight is 7 hour journey
from Luxembourg to Kano Nigeria
feels a little heavy today
do you see what's
loaded back there?
so oil equipment
yeah
not the light kind
flight 671 is operated by the newly
formed Nigeria company Trans Air Limited
their client
Kabo air cargo
Trans Air had only been formed
a few weeks before this incident
used purely for the
oil industry transport
a lot of equipment down
to Nigeria for the oil works
this was an extra special flight
in that it was carrying equipment that
would have helped Nigeria in modernizing
kabo 671 levels
off at 29,000 feet
the flight ban indicated
with the weight to the aircraft
we should stay at a
slightly low at the normal
flight level for the
first part of the flight
until we burned off fuel
and then we could
gain a higher flight level
how are the guys in the back?
good
made us coffee
also on board are
a cargo supervisor
and the maintenance engineer
like them more everyday
so the five of them were
knowledgeable about the 707
they were knowledgeable about
this sort of ad-hoc air cargo word
although they hadn't met
until a 4:00 night previously
I think they work well
together as a team
over the alps
the weather deteriorates
pretty much ground level
up to about 33000 feet
was in cloud
and the cloud was
rough and turbulent
I'm gonna buckle
up until we're above it
good idea
we engaged our five seat harness
rather than just the 4 point harnesses
that we normally keep on to a top of climb
and then moved
down seats forward
to be really guarding the
control in this turbulent air
it was getting quite rough
ask if we can go to 33
kabo 671
request flight level 330
671 roger
climb to flight level 330
climb 330
the requested climb
was to go up another 4000
one hour into the flight
just as the plane
reaches 33000 feet
there was a enormous bang
followed almost
immediately by another one
and the aircraft
absolutely rolled to the right
the captain uses all his
strength to level the plane
have the captain not
reacted as quickly as he did
the aircraft could
have rolled over
in fact inverted
engine fire
engine 3 and 4
show signs of fire
while the flight engineer
deals with the engine alarm
the first officer
checks on the engines
I saw nothing in the
number 4 engine position
number 4 engine
has left the wing
mayday mayday mayday
kabo 671
with reduced engine power
and an unbalanced configuration
the flight drops out of the
sky in an uncontrolled descent
the descent rate was horrific
I think I saw 8 or 9
thousand feet per minute
it's diving quickly towards the
french alps through heavy cloud
they need to get out
of the mountains and
they can't see outside
because of the thick cloud
they need the air traffic
controller to give them a direction
in which to head for a safe
heaven for a safe airborne
mayday mayday mayday
request descent for radar landing
the ground service can follow
your track over the ground
your heading, height and
speed from a transponder
they can point you to the
nearest available runway
but air traffic
control had bad news
kabo 671
we have no radar contact
say your position please sir
they can no longer see
flight 671 on the radar
with no body able to give
them a direction to steer
they stood a very real
chance of hitting a mountain
the plane's radar
transponder has failed
I was considering which direction
we could go to avoid the mountains
it was very scary
the situation is dire enough that the first
officer records the damage to the wing
I wasn't sure what
would happened next
I believe if anything ended
like the flight before
we were ready
somebody might find the
camera and then they see the truth
flight 671 is on an uncontrolled
descent over the french alps
with thick cloud and no transponder
for the controller to guide them
the crew is flying blind
mayday mayday mayday
request descent for radar landing
the flight engineer attempts to
get the transponder working again
he suspects there
is a power issue
the reason the air traffic
control lost the radar initially
was probably because
the electrics power in the radar
failed when engine
number 4 fell off
the flight engineer redirects
the power to engine 1
he selected the essential
power selector to engine 1
which had an operative
electrical generator
it works
request descent
radar landing
roger
turn left heading
south to Marseille
the controller direct flight
671 to Marseille airport
75 miles away
you turn left 180
okay
there was a immense relief
as they descended out of cloud
and finally could see the
mountains around them
but relief is short lived
after the first officer gives the
right wing a further inspection
we've lost both
engines on the right wing
what?
with the 5 point harness
you're slightly restricted
but I did managed to look
right of my right shoulder
and both the engines
were off the wing
the wing was clean
which was a really big shock
we've lost both engines
both engines
just about the worst thing
that can happen in an airliner
is to have an engine
depart from the aircraft
the only thing worse than that would be to
have two engines depart from your aircraft
with only the two left
engines functioning
control of the plane
is compromised
when you've lost both
engines from the right wing
and still have a lot of thrust
from the engines on the left wing
it'd upsets that balance
and cause the airplane
to turn and to roll very
powerfully to the right
getting the airplane to turn left
is a huge ask under
these circumstances
you turn 180
yeah
I'm trying
flying the disabled plane is
testing the captain strength
the Boeing 707 has all
manual flying controls
it's very heavy to fly
when everything working well
when you've lost two
engines on one side
it's virtually at the limit of
physical capability for the captain
do you wanna dump fuel?
yes
dump fuel
to keep flight 671 in the air
the crew decides
to reduce it's load
this aircraft was carrying
a very heavy fuel load
and it was imperative
to reduce that fuel load
but it requires a
precise calculation
they need to leave themselves enough
fuel to reach Marseille and land safely
112 tons is the maximum
safe way in which they can land
if there any heavier than that
and hit the ground hard, they would
sliding along the runway on their belly
shedding fuel and burning
this is not a position
you wanna be in
the process is time consuming
as flight 671 complete its
left turn toward Marseille
captain Berglund reduces
power in the two left engines
they had to reduce the
power on the left engines
to give themselves a
chance of staying upright
and going in the direction
they wanted to go in
reducing air speed means an
increase in the angle of descent
unfortunately this off course meant
they then descended more rapidly
they have to land soon and they
have to land somewhere very nearby
airspeed isn't the
crew's only concern
request the weather
give me the weather
for Marseille, 671
I really needed the weather
of Marseille to make a plan
for an approach to land either direct
or a circuit or whatever we could do
but air traffic control
isn't responding
request weather
mayday mayday mayday
it was quite a tough call to actually
get the instant weather at that moment
at Marseille airport
that we needed right now
making matters worse
the fuel dump is not
going as expected
fuel tank number
one isn't discharging
that became evident
to the flight engineer
that
the number one fuel
tank wasn't empty
and this would cause
a lateral imbalance across the
airplane which is not a good thing
I've got limited maneuver
are you dumping?
the flight engineer discovers
that a circuit breaker has popped
while pushing the
circuit breaker back in
he was able to reactivate
the number one fuel pomp
and get the fuel jettisoning
from all four tank simultaneously
flight 671 is 30 miles from
the runway in Marseille
mayday mayday mayday
671, request weather
it's raining
no
thunder clouds and the risk of turbulence
will make a difficult landing harder
we were pushed to even get there with
the height available thunderstorm activity
it was really a no go
kabo 671
what's is our distance from runway?
22 miles, sir
we had no plane B
at that point that
was a nasty moment
what we wanted was a
runway and we wanted it quickly
hey, do you see the airport?
I don't see it
flight 671 is in a rapid descent
with limited maneuver ability
less than 9 thousand
feet above southern France
when the crew
finally gets a break
I looked through just
clouds, underneath us
and I glimpsed some
ribboned black tarmac
it was a runway
kabo 671, we have an airport
ahead, what is airport?
it's military field, at
12 o'clock, 6 miles
can we land that?
no, it's too short
too short
how long is runway
on this military airport?
13000 feet
oh yeah
OK
the runway at Istres-Le is long
it's France's flight test center
and it was also a space
shuttle ultimate learning ground
it's probably the
biggest airport in Europe
military airport,
mayday, traffic, 671
the first officer makes contact with
air traffic control at Istres-Le airport
this is Istres-Le
you're clear to
arrival runway 33
we're just overhead
what's the wind?
wind is a 330, 10
knots, gusty 124 knots
we'll make a left hand
pattern from the west
yeah
the french military air traffic
control was one of my gang
I thought he was great
we turn left to land
yes
as they start their turn the
crew lowers the plane's flaps
in preparation for landing
wheels were down a lot, and
the flaps were coming down
so captain Berglund
would have more roll control
but when the flaps are extended
disaster strikes
it was another big explosion
which try to roll us right again
turn left
turn left to land
I'm trying
we missed the runway
they're unable to
line up for landing
671 we have fire on-board
I confirm
fire on-board
I could hear the fire
but didn't see anything
we need another runway
take a runway 15
wind is a 320, 10 knots
after failing to make a hard
left for a landing on runway 33
the crew attempts to circle back
and land on runway opposite it
known as 15
the captain doesn't have the
strength to make the turn on his own
but the first
officer has an idea
I said
I'll take the power
and captain Berglund said to me
be careful
I said I will
I promise
the first officer
adjusts the throttle
to help steer the
plane to the runway
I'm bringing back number one
advancing number 2
it actually turn the airplane left then
he could fly it going towards the runway
which was a miracle
truly was
it's a race against time
to get the plane on the ground
before the wing is incinerated
good descent
you're on axis
flight 671 is flying 50 knots
faster than normal landing speed
captain did a perfect landing
kept it just left
to the center line
but we were safely on the
ground at a great speed
but we were on the ground
if they don't brake soon
they'll overshoot the runway
without hydraulics they have only the
plane emergency break to reduce speed
there was no anti
skid protection
that would have meant the tires
will start scuffing and bursting
which would then reduce
the ability to slow down
stopping was the only
thing that mattered
you want both trust reverses
the flight engineer wanted to use
reverse thrust on the two left engine
because that was the only way
he could see of slowing down
no cut the engines
the first officer didn't
wanna him to do that
because that would pull the
airplane off to the left of the runway
I just reverse engine 2
as a compromise they use reverse
thrust on the inboard left engine
the number 2 engine
which did help reduce
their galloping speed
but pull the airplane
off the runway to the left
the aircraft did come
to a hole in the mud
we're on fire
evacuate evacuate
I realize that we
were on the fire
it was burning and
belching smoke and flame
we needed to get down
get out get away
with two missing engines
a wing on fire
and no brakes
flight 671 has landed
in Istres France
with its cargo and crew safe
to actually have two of the
four engines fall off the wing
virtually unheard of in
the history of aviation
the heroic scape from death
makes headlines around the world
as french investigators arrived
they faced with an
important question
what cause two engines
to fall off a plane?
losing two engines
is a huge thing
so the investigators
had quite a big task
to established what had
happened and more importantly why
and how to prevent
it happening again
the damage 707 is
moved to a hanger
to be examined by the BEA
France's air investigation authority
the level of damage
on this aircraft was
very close to looking
like a total structural failure
I got something
investigators make an early discovery
about the fire on board the plane
these wires from the
cable loom short circuited
that plus the fuel leak from near
the engine 3 area cause the fire
good work
when the engines
came away from the wing
they torn with them
electrical wiring
some of that wiring
still had power available
when the flaps were extended
leaking fuel made contact
with live wires and ignited
get these cleaned up
get a better look what tore
the engines from the wing
investigators are counting on
the plane's flight data recorder
to provide more information
okay
see what it can tell us
it looks like engines 3 and 4 were
producing thrust right up until here
9:50 a.m. one
hour into the flight
the FDR data reveals that both
engines stop working almost concurrently
the flight data recorder basically
show the engines operating as normal
when they left the aircraft
to understand why two perfectly
functioning engines detached from 707 wings
investigators need to
find the missing engines
here is the flight path
this is where they
probably fell off
I'll send a search and
recovery team out there
24 hours into the investigation
the engines of 671 are located on a
mountain side near Séderon France
55 miles north east of
where the plane landed
investigators found the
engines about 800 meters apart
that's very close
their location also suggest the engines
detached at almost the same time
while the team waits for
the engines to be recovered
they turn to the crew
for further insight
we were climbing to 43000 feet to
avoid some pretty bad turbulence
suddenly there were loud sounds
I saw engine 4 was missing
you reported the engine's
missing at 2 different times
is it possibly you
were mistaking?
it's possible
the harness size wearing kept me from
getting a good look out the window at first
you're climbing
to avoid turbulence
how bad was it?
it was severe
I wouldn't want to
get for that again
they'd flown through
extremely heavy turbulence
of a level not
normally encountered
so they were two cumulonimbus
clouds here and here
and they went up
passed 33000 feet
investigators examine the weather
conditions of the time of the incident
looks like there was also a
90 knots jet stream over here
they discover that flight 671
flew through 2 weather conditions
when they reached 33000 feet
those two conditions would
have generated sever turbulence
but he would think it could
withstand the turbulence
did two colliding weather conditions
tear the engines off the 707?
let's see what the
engines can tell us
hey boss
close examination of the engines
gives investigators an important new clue
do you see these
dents on engine 4?
it's shape and diameter
match dents on engine 3
so does these white paint
you could tell from the
shape of the damage
and from transfer
white paint from
one engine to the other engine
that the number 3 had
struck the number 4 engine
and separated it
investigators now need to find
out what cause engine 3 to detached
looks like a clean
break of all 4 fittings
each engine is
attached to a pylon
the pylon is then bolted to
the wing using 4 large fittings
during flight 671 all 4
fittings broke on engine 3
3 of the 4 fittings
broke like this one
you can see from the
surface they broke from stress
this midspar
fitting is different
there is some distortion here
likely broke from
a fatigue fraction
you could see
some characteristics
surface wise
coloration wise
that were consistent
with a fatigue cracking
over time
the inboard midspar fitting
on engine 3 was weakened
because of a crack
cause by metal fatigue
when it snapped off
in sever turbulence
the other fittings broke too
as a metallurgist I want to
take a close look at these things
okay let's see what we got
to establish a detailed history of
flight 671's broken midspar fitting
investigators use an electron
microscope to examine it
I can see multiple arrest lines
with each take off and landing
the crack grows a little bit
at least a mark
and
each little stress cycle
makes the crack a little bigger
these are likely from the flight plane
flew since trans air put it back in service
a few weeks ago
what about before that?
as the team continues
examining the crack midspar fitting
they make an unusual finding
looks like corrosion
the plane had to have been exposed
to moisture over a long period of time
right
looks like the previous owner
had the plane in storage for
13 month prior to incident
where was it stored?
in a field in England
steel will corrode if
it's in a salty atmosphere
or very moist atmosphere
this particular aircraft was stored at
airfields which weren't far from the sea
that explains corrosion
what are those?
those little marks
near the bottom of the fitting
they discover
several tail tail marks
those are corrosion pit marks
corrosion pits are tiny holes
that appear in metal after water
has gain access to that metal and
caused corrosion to takes place
and the pit can be
the start of a long crack
and in this case there
were corrosion pits
that grow into the one crack and
eventually fracture the midspar fitting
so when these
pit marks start to develop?
it's hard to pinpoint exactly
given their distance from
the arrest lines it's suggest that
the pitting started even before
the plane went into storage
the crack doesn't
occur in storage
oxidation does
so that tells us the cracking
occurred before storage
probably years before storage
so how did maintenance
team miss it?
this just arrived from trans air
maintenance records
let's have a look
investigators want to know if
poor maintenance on flight 671
contributed to the crash
you start look at the
age of the parts that failed
and what was the maintenance
requirements for those parts
and did they play a
role in the accident?
in the 1919 Nigeria
airlines like trans air
gain the reputation
for poor maintenance
for a while
Nigeria airways were in facts
banned from united kingdom space
according this Trans air didn't
do a midspar maintenance check
Trans air had only owned that
airplane for a very small amount of times
so it's unlikely that they
performed any maintenance on it so
maybe Trans air inherited the
problem before it was owned by them
looks like the previous owner
did two maintenance checks
one Oct 10th 1991
when the plane was in storage
the other May 1990
before it went to storage
the team learns that the plane
pasted two maintenance checks
in a two year period
prior to the incident
if the metal fatigue
started before the storage
maintenance check should
have caught the problem
there were certain cracks that should
have been picked up which weren't
then one month
into the investigation
another 707 loses engine
the incident is similar to
what happened to flight 671
during take off from
Miami international airport
the number 3 engine is torn off
the wing and then hits engine 4
with the Miami accident, the pilots
managed to land the aircraft safely
with no one being hurt
the NTSB investigates and
discovers that a broken midspar fitting
also cause the engine
to fall off the wing
this was perhaps
history repeating itself
is that from the NTSB?
yep
french investigators review
the NTSB preliminary report
curios about the Miami’s
plane's maintenance history
the maintenance on the 707 Miami was
performed 328 flights before the accident
which is well within the 600
flight recommendation by the FAA
they discover that the plane had
also passed maintenance checks
and reported no fatigue
cracking or corrosion
in both the Miami accident
and the French accident
the midspar fitting had
failed with a very similar way
and had also been maintained specified
by the FAA and Boeing aircraft company
perhaps they weren't
maintaining properly
at a time the midspar fitting
were required to be inspected
in close visual examination
basically
you gain access to the fitting
you wipe it off the best you can
and what you can see
is what you examine
was there a problem with
the inspection process?
investigators interview
a maintenance supervisor
about how engine fittings
are approved for flight
so how do you
inspect the fitting?
you supposed to carry
out close visual inspection
for cracks on the expose
surfaces of the fitting
and
well
cracks can start on
the inside of the fitting
so why is that a problem?
well it's problem
cause you can't see inside
unless you remove the engine
and the pylon from the wing
it's troubling discovery
the midspar fitting is normally inspected
by removing a panel on the pylon
but the entire fitting cannot
be seen from access panel
the engine and pylon
need to be removed
to check the cracks on
the inside of the fitting
Boeing did not require this
assembly of the midspar fitting
the risk assessment
basically said it's not worth it
on this old air frame
so there could be 707 out there with
cracks on its fitting that no one can see
yeah
as an investigator you
always have to wonder
how many more engines
are going to fall off of 707s
listen to this
investigators of flight 671
do a deep dive into the history
of the Boeing 707 midspar fitting
there have been reports more than
35 cracks midspar fitting on the 707
these planes are the
end of their life cycle
707 in Miami had flown
over a 50,000 hours
Trans air 707 had flown
over a 60,000 hours
these was an old fitting on an old airplane
that'd been designed a very long time ago
and when they didn't know
how these materials would age
the consequence of these and perhaps
not the best maintenance or inspection
and that eventually
this fitting just gave up
by 1992
most 707 were considered
too old to fly passengers
and were converted
to freight transport
we need to make sure
this doesn't happen again
investigators conclude that a
hidden fracture in the midspar fitting
almost took the life of the 5
man on Trans air flight 671
the fate of the plane is sealed
when a maintenance inspection
fails to catch the fatigue crack
ask if we can go to 33
the 707 is pushed
to its breaking point
when two weather events collide
the in-flight
turbulence was the last
little bit that was
necessary to cause fracture
basically was the last straw
that held this pylon together
the weaken midspar fitting finally
breaks and both engines are lost
if not for the
heroics of the crew
the plane would have crashed
the 707 is not an easy airplane
to fly when everything is going well
it's a very difficult airplane to
fly when things are going wrong
I've got limited maneuver
you dumping
yeah
captain Berglund skill and
stamina prove remarkable
as he physically keeps
the plane stable until landing
from the beginning of the incident to
when they finally landed on the runway
24 minutes
a 24 minutes that most pilots
wouldn't have had all those
things happen in their entire career
he was just one fantastic pilots
kabo 671
we have no radar contact
say your position please sir
throughout the harrowing flight
flight engineer Boone
troubleshoots and fixes key systems
flight engineer look to this panel
and came up with the solution
as to why the
radar wasn't working
you turn left 180
okay
hey
do you see the airport?
and first officer Emery's quick
thinking and intuition proved vital
kabo 671
we have an airport ahead
what is that airport?
it was an absolute genius decision to
land at a military base with a long runway
it shows an awful lot about
that spirit of pilots and survival
that they somehow coalesce together
they all use their
own individual skills
the BEA recommends that inspection
of the current midspar fitting be modified
to enable the detection
of hidden cracks
all be replaced by
reinforced fittings
the FAA decided to mandate
replacement of the midspar fittings
with a new and
improved midspar fittings
which did not
require inspections
that were ineffective
on the first place
in 1992 the crew of
Trans air cargo 671
recieved the Hugh Gordon-Burge
Award for outstanding airmanship
this flight was a
heroic acheivement
where the crew have recovered
from a virtually impossibe situation
and they deserve
the awards they've got
so a lot of luck and
a bit of team work
and a bit of shouting
and a bit of action
but happy landing