on approach during
a thunderstorm
both runway is wet
severe turbulence
American airlines flight
1572 loses a valuable lifeline
be advised
the tower is closed
there is a leaky
window in the tower
the tower had actually been
abandoned, this is a very unusual situation
NTSB investigators learned that a
supervisor went to the deserted tower
I told them they could land
landing is at your discretion
the runway does
appear to be clear
moments before touchdown
disaster strikes
what's up?
and both of the
plane's engines failed
what role did an
out of service tower
play in jeopardizing the
lives of 78 people on board?
tell them we're going down
on a stormy November night
American airlines flight 1572
cruises 35,000 feet
above Pennsylvania
smother ride up here
rather than 33,000
Captain Kenneth Lee
a former military pilot has been
flying with American airlines for 10 years
that's for sure
First Officer John Richards
also flew with the military
and has 7 years of
commercial aviation experience
this was a very
experienced flight crew
that was very comfortable
with the aircraft they were flying
they're flying the MD-83
a twin engine narrow body jet
it has two turbo fan
engines mounted in a tail
as a t-tail and a
swept main wing
it was one of the last
aircraft that actually had
direct connection between
the controls in the cockpit
and the surfaces on the airplane
better get the cabin
ready for our descent
hi
we're starting our descent now so you can
luck the cabin up and prepare for landing
we'll do
please fasten your seat belt
it's short two hour flight
from Chicago O'Hare airport
to Bradley International Airport
at Windsor locks Connecticut
they are 5 crew and
73 passengers on board
many of them returning home
please put your seat
in the upward position
flight started out
the rather routinely
it was the second day of a
three day leg trip for these guys
American 1572
descend that pilot discretion
maintain flight level 190
pilots , discretion to
190, American 1572
let's go down
the flight is 25
minutes from landing
I'm gonna get the
ATIS real quick
Bradley Airport information
vector 03
ATIS or Automatic
Terminal Information Service
provides pilots with important airport
data like weather and approaches
notice to airman
runway 25 and 15
both runway is wet
severe turbulence
all right
sounds it's gonna
be a bumpy ride
tell the passengers
they'll encounter some
rough weather along the way
but nothing these experienced
crew can't managed
many times I have experienced
the same kinds of winds and weather
and these crew has had
and winds will have a drastic effect
on the airplane and pushing it around
the crew was very
familiar with the weather
and they were highly experienced
enough to handle anything
we've started our descent
right now they've reported some
moderate turbulence on the descent
so make it a little choppy
just watch me the whole way
yeah man, you got it
the pilots prepare
for the landing
any comments
just scream out
you gotta get a
lot of turbulence
you know how to  land it
they support each other
they back each other up
if anything goes wrong or
somebody does something wrong
the other one catches
it and corrects it
50 miles from the airport
the weather worsens
it's a lot of rain
I can see that
the in route controllers
had told them
the weather is really bad due
the thunderstorm and wind shear
wind shear is a sudden
change of wind speed or direction
that can be dangerous
close to the ground
American 1572
descend and maintain 4000
descending 4000
flight 1572 is the last plane
flying into Bradley Airport tonight
approach to 4000
the crew is making a difficult
non-precision approach
a non-precision approach means
you don't have a navigation aid
there's more reliance on the
crew to figure out the altitude
and descends those
altitude correctly
and avoid all the
terrain that's below there
we're established on the in
bound track for the VOR Approach
flaps 5
this type of approach
creates extra work for the pilots
the not precision approach is the
hardest of all the approaches to fly
because it takes so much
attention to fly the approach
it has to be set up correctly
American 1572
be advised
the tower is closed at this time due
to the problem with one of the windows
the non precision
approach and rough weather
aren't the only
challenges facing the crew
copy
there is a leaky
window in the tower
at larger airports
the control tower has two areas for
managing incoming and outgoing flights
approach control typically
located on one of the lower floors
and tower control at the top
Mark Guiod was the air traffic
manager at Bradley Airport for 12 years
once they're within
5 miles of the airport
the approach controller
turns them over to the tower
and bring them in for landing
and taxi them to the gate
but a leaky window
has shut down the tower
forcing the air traffic
controller to leave her post
tower controllers are the
pilot's eyes on the ground
they're the ones that ensure
that the runway is sterile
and clear for them to land on
that there no obstruction
no other traffic
they also provide critical information
in the late stages of the flight
flaps 11 please
you got it
the pilots must now rely on their
own observations to land safely
the pilots were expecting
someone to be able to be in the tower
the controller to see
the conditions of the runway and
to give them the information needed
to see if anything during the
thunderstorm had blown up to the runway
so they can make a safe landing
the approach controller is
closely monitoring the flight
he notices the plane
is veering off course
American 1572 looks like
you're a bit to the left of final
yeah, looks like
we're left of it
copy
7 miles from the airport
captain Lee gets the
plane back on course
so gear down
gear down
I'm going up to the tower
the supervisor in
approach control volunteers
to give the crew of flight
1572 some guidance
American 1572
there is someone in the
tower so unofficially open
but you can change
the tower frequency
it would have been a big relief to
the crew to have someone in the tower
the controller up there to give them the
information they need for the approach
hey tower
American 1572
we are 6 miles from runway 15
landing is at your discretion
the runway does
appear to be clear
copy
any landing is really
at the pilot's discretion
but in this particular case
they need to be extra vigilant
because they didn't have
any official tower assistance
flaps 14
the pilots configure
the aircraft for landing
flaps and slats to 40 40
you're clear to land
10,000 feet
okay
flight 1572 is just 60
seconds from touchdown
what's up?
bells and whistles were going off
lights were flashing
and something had to be done
2.5 miles from Bradley
airport in Connecticut
American airlines flight
1572 has struck something
while descending to the runway
the pilots must act
quickly to avoid crashing
go go around
going around
they pull the nose up
in an attempt to recover
flaps 15, positive rate, gear up
gear up
the crew immediately
began a go around procedure
they raise the gear
they raise the flaps
cram the engines forward
and immediately after that
things went downhill very quickly
left motor's failed
seconds after the pilot
commands the go around
the plane's left
engine loses power
that's the last thing you need to
have happen is a power failure
on one of the engines
there's runway straight ahead
okay
tell them we're going down
tell  emergency
hey tower
call for emergency equipment,
we're going down on the runway
looks like we've got an
emergency on 1572, send the trucks
emergency vehicles
have been dispatched
as the pilots prepare
for an emergency landing
the situation worsens
the right engine also fails
turning the MD-83
into a 60 ton glider
they realized they had a second
power failure which made double trouble
without its engines the plane
has drifted further of course
captain Lee tries to line
it back up with the runway
you gotta do it
you're gonna make it
but they may not have
enough lift to reach it
stall is an aerodynamic
effects when the winds lose lift
and the airplane
loses direction control
the only way to fly out of a stall is
max power which they did not have
hold on guy
hold it down buddy
hold it down
god bless you
you made it
it was a miracle that the
first officer saw the runway
and the crew reacted so quickly
it was a very good reaction
and certainly saved
a lot of people lives
flight 1572 has landed safely
after a treacherous final approach
everyone has survived and remarkably
only one person has suffered a minor injury
the pilots are hailed as heroes for
saving their plane and everyone on board
one of the key things about
something like this is that
you never stop
flying the airplane
and those who do
don't live to tell about it
the events that nearly
brought down flight 1572
are a complete mystery
what we've got so far?
it will be up to investigators from the
national transportation safety board (NTSB)
to find the answers
Bob Benzon heads up the team
I was the investigator in charge with
about a dozen NTSB people underneath me
plus many people
from the industry
aircraft hit the ground hard
approaching the runway threshold
maybe the engines had
something to do with it
did a lost of engine power
cause flight 1572 to crash-land
in front of the runway threshold?
when we first arrived at the accident
site our first order of business was really
to kind of do a reconnaissance
look at the aircraft
this thing looks like
flew through a war zone
and during our
initial examination
the aircraft was very very
damaged, it reminded me of a
something like a B-70
that had gone through
raid on schweinfurt
in world war 2
it was beat to heck
branches sticking
out of a landing gear
engine blade's missing
battered flaps
the aircraft was unflyable
they definitely hit some trees
they sure did
and the engines definitely had
power and shredded those branches
mangled branches in the plane's engines
indicate that they were working normally
the discovery raises
another question
if the engines had power
why they hit the trees
the main question became why the
aircraft was low enough to hit trees
and still make it to the runway
if you're gonna analyze
an accident like this
which is categorized as a
Controlled flight into terrain
you have to understand
where the airplane went
and when it went there
and why it went there
where exactly did
they hit the trees?
to understand why
flight 1572 struck trees
investigators try to identify
the first point of impact
the trees they hit
are on top of the ridge
about 2.5 miles north
west of the runway
we have a team out there now
let's see if the trees of the
ridge were marked on the chart
the approach chart itself when
you look at it have the ridge
mark with the small
dot with the altitude
the chart
has the top of the
ridge at 819 feet
once we get a look at the approach
chart itself that the crew was using
we noted that the ridge line
was just a mere dot with a
number 819 next to it, an altitude
that dot could
have been anything
could have been a
building, a giant tree
other airlines use slightly different
chart that shows topographical features
including this ridge line
did flight 1572 come in too low
because there was a lack of
detail on their approach chart?
do we have the
altitude for the tree strike?
I need an altitude for
the first impact mark
771 feet
they should have been
anywhere near those trees
the team is surprised to discover
that when flight 1572 hit trees
it was 48 feet below the
altitude listed for the ridge line
they weren't just
below the ridge
they dropped 309 feet below
the minimum descent altitude
the minimum descent
altitude or MDA
is the lowest altitude
a crew can decent to
until they're able
to see the runway
it's designed to keep planes
above terrains or obstructions
those altitudes
are hard altitudes
when the FAA builds
those altitudes in there
they have to take in
consideration of all the clearances
the trees
the elevation
to keep the airplane
at a safe altitude
why would they dropped so low?
maybe there is something
wrong with the altimeters
investigators see the airplane
descended too low so the question is
did the crew have
the correct indication?
see if statistic
system is working
Pitot–static system
was quite important
because that system controls
altitude, altimeters
it controls airspeed indicators
and also controls the
vertical velocity indications
did sensors provide incorrect
data to the plane's altimeters?
the MD-83 has three sets of
sensors on the exterior fuselage
they measure air pressure to determine
airspeed, altitude and vertical speed
if one of the static sensors
is leaking or obstructed
it can give pilots
inaccurate information
making them think they're
above or below their actual altitude
if the pitot tube is clogged
you lose those vital instruments
and
that can happen
from variety of reasons
pitot static system have
caused problems before
problem severe
enough to cause crashes
ready?
yep
the test forces air
into the sensor
to determine if the air pressure
is being measured accurately
but it proves to be a dead end
the static system is working
okay
let's see what the
controllers can tell us
it's always valuable
to be able to speed to
the air traffic controllers
after an accident
well often the air traffic controller is
the last person to speak to the crew
prior to an accident
did the crew report anything unusual
on their descent in the Windsor locks?
no
it was standard approach
but weather conditions
weren't great at a time
were there any downdraft?
did strong winds pushed
flight 1572 into the trees?
if an airplane encounters
severe downdrafts
it can push the airplane
down several hundred feet
wind shear poses
a danger to aircraft
in 1985 a severe downdraft slammed
Delta airlines flight 191 into the ground
more than a mile short of
the runway in Dallas taxes
137 people lost their lives
in 1994
a year before flight 1572
close call in Connecticut
USA flight 1016 crash into trees
while attempting to land in a
powerful thunderstorm in north Carolina
it plowed into a
residential neighborhood
killing 37 people
thunder storm have
incredible wind shear
they can have updrafts
200 miles an hour
and then
you know
half a second later after
you passed through that
you'd have downdraft
200 miles an hour
there is a lot of wind
on the airport all night
what about when this
flight was coming through?
there was some wind shear
investigators learned that airport
sensors registered some down drafts
we make sure to
give them updates
like I said it was rough
so they knew what
they were flying into
yes
given a weather conditions
at the time and a unstable air
investigators were able to determine
that they may have been down drafts
up to 3 or 4 hundred
feet per minutes
occurring at the
time of this event
so
if there was a downdraft
these guys would have
been prepared for it
oh yes
it was possible that wind shear could have
pulled the aircraft down into the trees
but a careful look at
the weather at the time
after that we determine
that simply wasn't true
was there anything else
out of ordinary that night?
besides the weather
well the tower was
shutdown at that time
leaky window
one of our supervisors went up
to make sure they landed okay
you mean the tower was
down during their approach
yes
I'd like to speak to the
supervisor who was in the tower
sure
of course
did flight 1572 slammed into trees
due to lack of guidance from the tower?
air traffic control worker is
demanding and it's precise job
if there any major disruptions
either in the tower or
at Donna radar scope
it could effect
aircraft traffic greatly
were there any signs the crew
was having trouble during approach?
not really
it was all normal until
they called the emergency
take me through what happened
they were already 6 miles out
lined up with the runway
runway looked clear so I
told them they could land
we're 6 miles from runway 15
landing is at your discretion
the runway does
appear to be clear
copy
did you give them an
actual clearance for landing?
the tower was closed
I can only give advisories
it's up to them to decide
after that if they want to land
advisories are just
information provided to the pilot
for their own use
they can listen to it they
cannot listen to it, its up to them
in this case the
tower was not open
so therefore he didn't have
authority to issued any clearance
investigators still don't know if poor
weather and a closed control tower
caused the pilots to drop below
the minimum descent altitude
what's up?
and into the trees
let's start at 12:53 when
the crew contacts the tower
investigators turned to the cockpit voice
recording of flight 1572's final approach
to determine why the plane
drops too low and flew into trees
landing is at your discretion
the runway does appear to be clear
and what is showing
right now for winds?
170 at 24
copy
he's checking the runway
giving weather updates
it's all the job so far
the team listens to the supervisors
giving the crew guidance to help them land
it was a good initiative
for him to do that
it was something some people would
not have done based on the fact that the
the tower itself was a
bit of a precarious area
flaps 40
flaps and slats to 40 40
you are clear to land
okay
give me a thousand down
one thousand down
you got it
stop that
a thousand feet a minute
no way
as they neared the ground
the crew decided to make their
final decent at 1000 feet per minute
nearly double what is normal
that in my mind
is quite excessive
you didn't have to
descend that steeply
specially on non
precision approach
where you have a minimum descent altitude
that you should not be going bellow
the faster you descending the
earlier you have to start leveling off
or else you end up going
bellow the target altitude
by the time you correct
and come back up again
according to the descent profile
they're 5 miles from
the airport at 1900 feet
using the Radar beacon
data from air traffic control
investigators track flight 1572's cockpit
conversation throughout the descent
at a 1000 feet per minute
they're bellow their
MDA in less than a minute
sure that's fast but the first officer
should be calling the altitudes
while the aircraft descending the pilot is
supposed to monitor the airplane's MDA
minimum descent altitude
the first officer should call a
1000 above MDA to the captain
and then 100 foot to the MDA
and then the MDA altitude
okay
let's listen to the
first officer call out
there is the 1000 feet
good
he made a 1000 for call out
but they don't hear any
more call outs after that
the first officer called out
the 1000 foot above the MDA
he did not call out the
100 foot above the MDA
investigators then
hear something unusual
a 1000 ..
right
you're going bellow your
what's up?
hang on
was that the minimum
descent altitude call out?
I think it was supposed to be
the team discovers that the first
officer mishandled the remaining call outs
the first officer
started to call out
for the MDA but never
finished the sentence
so he makes half at their minimum
and then doesn't say anything
else until they're bellow it
and by then they hit the trees
why did the pilots make such a
critical error so close to landing?
let's talk to the pilots
this particular case we were very
fortunate to have live crew to interview
we wanna to determine exactly what they
were thinking about during the accident?
walk me through your actions
4 miles from the airport as you
approach minimum descent altitude
the weather was rough, we
were two hours late departing
I was monitoring the instruments
a 1000 ...
so you're
right
okay
and then what
as we got closer to the
minimum descent altitude
I looked outside for the airport
and when I looked back
we were bellow minimums
you're going bellow your
during that time
he was looking out
he was not monitoring the flight
gauges as closely as he should have been
this case the appropriate
procedure would have had
the first officer glue to the
altimeter and the compass
and other instruments
in the cockpit
until the captain said
I see the runway
why didn't you go for go around?
well there was no time
we immediately hit the trees
it was a stressful night
it could be a bit of task
saturation in there
this went from an easy
kind of relax flight with the
little bit of weather difficulty to
oh my gosh, everything's
going wrong really really fast
something doesn't add up
the first officer couldn't have been on his
minimum seconds before hitting the trees
maybe there was an issue
with the altimeter settings
pilots must calibrate the altimeters
based on outside air pressure
which can change dramatically
in extreme weather conditions
pilots frequently
recalibrate the altimeters
to maintain an
accurate altitude reading
altimeter setting
is very important
you can't do a approach
in bad weather unless
you know the altitude
your airplane is
let's see what setting they used
it's a lot of rain
I can see that
in this case cut of this storming
that was going through that area
the pressure was falling rapidly
and when that happens your
altimeter setting goes down quickly
means if you don't
reset your altitude
then your airplane is flying
lower that you think it is
here
the dispatcher updated them
with an altimeter setting 29.23
NTSB investigators check whether
the pilots of American airlines flight 1572
properly set the altimeter during
the stormy approach into Bradley airport
what time is that?
12:30 am
that was 25 minutes
before they hit the trees
and with the changing
weather conditions
they must have received
an update from Bradley ATC
but one thing that the crew considers
and expects from the tower or air traffic
is the update of the
weather as quick as possible
so they can also amend
what they need to do
okay
they first contact the
approach control at 12:43
Bradley approach
American 1572
we are 11,000 feet
investigators expect
the approach controller
to give the crew a
weather updates
including the altimeter
pressure setting
the approach control issue the
altimeter setting on initial contact
when an arriving aircraft
enters their aerospace
the altimeter is displayed as a
digital display in controls tower as well
American 1572
Bradley approach roger
expect VOR runway 15 approach
but the update is never provided
approach didn't update
their altimeter setting
even though the pressure
was dropping rapidly
there is nothing at
all from approach
right up until he passes
them off to the tower
why wouldn't the approach
controller give them a weather update?
good question
let's ask him
one thing that puzzled the
investigators was why the
air traffic controllers
in the Bradley tower
didn't keep the pilots update
with the current altimeter setting?
you mention before that the
weather was quite active that night
yes, it was changing
quickly all night
what was the airport altimeter
setting at the time of the accident?
let me see
29.15
investigators learned
that the altimeter
pressure setting at
the time of the accident
was not the setting the
pilot were originally given
why didn't the crew
receive an updated setting?
I didn't think to
give it to them
sometimes things that you
do over and over and over again
become
too routine
and
late at night when there
is not whole lot going on
sometimes those are the
things that dropped to the cracks
we warned about
that excuse a little bit
but this was what he said
so the pilots didn't have
the current altimeter setting
when they flew the approach
we got the altimeter setting
for the time of the accident
comparing the two
altimeter settings
will reveal how much lower the plane
was flying than it should have been
0.08
the difference in
the altimeter setting
from what they had
put on their instruments
to what was a reality was
about 0.08 inches of mercury
which equates to 76 feet
because the pilots
updated setting
they thought they were 76 feet
higher than they actually were
the discovery is eye opening
once you get close to the
ground 76 feet is a big deal
once you're coming across
the minimum descent altitude
and you have to keep the airplane
level at minimum descent altitude
76 feet is critical
the question is
would they have hit anything
if they have been 76 higher?
well we know they struck
the trees at an altitude 771 feet
add 76 feet to that
they would have hit anything
no impact
if they had the
correct altimeter setting
even though they
went blew the MDA
they still were
gonna be 76 higher
and we probably wouldn't
be talking about this right now
because they would
have missed the trees
that is an explain why they are 309
feet bellow the minimum descent altitude
76 feet of that are ATC
the other 233
feet are pilot error
this was out of the control
of the pilots to a certain extent
that going bellow the MDA
should have been caught by
both the first officer and the captain
this is what
created the accident
in the end they came
down to the crew's decision
investigators now understand
what happened to flight 1572
the outdated altimeter setting
and the rough weather
made that the crew had almost
no room for error on the approach
and when they were descending too fast
and passed their minimum descent altitude
there was no way they could
recover before hitting the trees
only one question
remains unanswered
in spite of hitting the trees
how did they make that landing?
here is the FDR data
NTSB investigators turn to
flight 1572's flight data recorder
to learn how the crew
managed to recover their jet
after they struck the trees
so
they hit the trees
and immediately
pulled the flaps back to
15 and go to max thrust
the data shows that the crew quickly
configure the plane for a go around
go go around
going around
flaps 15
positive rate
gear up
then
just as they begin
their go around
they lose their left engine
the aircraft actually ingested
trees, the tops of the
trees into the engines
left motor's failed
followed by their right engine
here you have a scenario where
something devastated
just happened
we just plow through some
trees on a top of the ridge
2.5 miles away from
the runway and losing
capabilities on this
aircraft by the second
they've go the nose way up
they're losing the speed and
both of their engines are gone
that's recipe for stall if
I have already see one
all of a sudden they were
starting to lose airspeed
they're in a nose high altitude and
that's worse time that could happen
airspeed is what
makes the airplane flying
if there isn't enough air
moving over the wings
the wings stop flying
and that is what
refer to as stall
there is a runway straight ahead
fortunately the first
officer saw the runway
they had to get the airplane
on the ground in a hurry
because it would not be able to keep
on flying with the engine power they had
okay
tell them we are going down
tell them the emergency
so now he's gonna
reconfigure the aircraft again
and remember this is
all happening in seconds
he's gotta focus on trying to save
whatever altitude and airspeed he has left
to make it across the fence
into the runway environment
this is a critical
stage of flight now
because he doesn't have power
all he can do is trade
altitude for airspeed
and we know their flaps
were all the way down 40
flaps 40
all the way down
they're all the way down
he's gonna generate something else
that's gonna get them across the fence
and that's why he
drops 40 degrees flaps
the drag from the
flaps slows them down
but for the first few
seconds it balloons them up
40 degrees of flaps
change the curve of the wing
which increases
the lift of the wing
and gives him that
extra little bounce
to get a little bit further
if he had not have done that of if
he would have delayed it a little bit
the accident could have
been totally catastrophic
you got it dude
you're gonna make it
and glide down to the runway
unfortunately they didn't have
quite enough airspeed and altitudes
so they landed early
kind of scooted and flopped
onto pavement of the runway
they made mistakes going
into the tree strike if you will
and yet did brilliant
job landing the aircraft
that's an incredible
show of airman ship
the crew was actually excellent
in cockpit resource management
in the very difficult situation that
occurred after they the ridge line
they cooperated
they didn't panic
they way these two pilots
work together was remarkable
and
one of the last thing that's on the tape
that's kind of really gives you a chill
is after they make the
runway the first officer says
god bless you
you made it
this is an accident that probably
is not well known to a lot of people
and that's because the aircraft was able
to end up on runway and no body was killed
the captain's impressive recovery
doesn't make up for the crew's errors
the NTSB's final report concludes
that the probable cause of this accident
was the crew flying bellow
the minimum descent altitude
before they could see the runway
we think in essence the
main factor involved in
in the accident was the fact
that the pilots didn't monitor
the altitudes they were
flying through correctly
they should have level off at a
point and they simply did not do so
following the accident
American airlines increase
the MDA requirement by 100 feet
and visibility
requirement by half a mile
for non-precision
approaches to Bradley airport
it's a lot of rain
the NTSB also recommends that in conditions
where pressure is falling rapidly
controllers should issue altimeter
setting updates as frequently as possible
the approach controller issues
the current altimeter setting
that didn't happen either
right, what's important to understand
though in terms of responsibility is that
the captain is the final
authority on the flight
it's ultimately the
captain's responsibility
to ensure the
safety of the flight
in this case he didn't ensure that he
had the most current altimeter setting
this accident was
important to me
because it was one of the few
where no body was killed
no body was hurt
and yet the safety board came up
with some pretty good recommendations
to mitigate some of
the factors that existed