stabilizer motion
help me back
okay
the pilots of Alaska
airlines flight 261
wrestle with an MD-83 nose
diving towards the Pacific ocean
we've got it under control here
no we don't
the airplane
pitched down and rolled
mayday
it actually gets
inverted upside down
amazingly the pilots managed
to keep the aircraft flying
this is like an airshow maneuver
speed brakes
just seconds from impact
the pilots right the aircraft
they had one shot
to save the plane
or all would be lost
here we go
Alaska airlines
flight 261 takes flight
climbing into sunny skies
over Puerto Vallarta Mexico
gear up
gears up
captain Ted Thompson
is an air force veteran
he's flown with Alaska
airlines for 17 years
thank you sir
first officer Bill Tansky has
been flying for almost 4 decades
he's the one flying today
the pilots on 261 were highly
regarded by their fellow pilots
these were really
top-notch aviators
flaps up
flaps
the MD-83 is flying north to
San Francisco for a stopover
from there it's short hop to its
final destination Seattle, Washington
3 flight attendance tend to
the 83 passenger on-board
50 minutes after take off
strange
the pilots become
aware of a problem
points AP TRIM
trim refers to small adjustments
to the horizontal stabilizer
that maintains the
pitch of the aircraft
when that light
goes on tells the crew
you're gonna have a problem
adjusting the nose up or down
which is of course
crucial for flight
the warning light indicates the
horizontal stabilizer is jammed
pushing the nose down slightly
let's check this out
auto pilot off
good idea
wow
what's it doing
it's pushing down
first officer Tansky uses all his physical
strength to keep the plane's nose up
the first officer is
hand-flying the airplane
so he's manually got his
hands on the control yoke
and
increasing there is more and more
pressure that he's having to hold
he's using a lot of arm muscle
so this is something
that they wanna fix
still climbing
that's good
let's get to 310
figure this out
by pulling back on
the control column
the pilots can deflect the
plane's elevator enough
to enable the aircraft
to continue climbing
21 minutes after take off
flight 261 levels
off at 31,000 feet
manual says try
the pickle switch
pickle switches are literally just a little
toggles switch on the control column
and it moves the
horizontal stabilizer
such that it will push
the nose up or down
controls in the cockpit activate
a two foot jack screw in the tail
as the jack screw turns
it moves the
stabilizer up or down
they were having to
go through the manuals
never asking each other
what do you know
what we can do
what we can try
nothing
what about you try?
captain Thompson tries to
activate the horizontal stabilizer
using what pilots
called a suitcase handles
no dice
it's like try to start your car
they were trying
everything they could think of
to get their plane to respond
let's try out auto pilot
they hope the auto pilot
can keep the plane level
plane is steady
right
I'm thinking we get this plane on
the ground sooner rather than later
yeah
maybe LAX
call dispatcher
if you have a control problem
you have to get that
plane on the ground
dispatch
requesting a diversion to LAX
our longitudinal trim
system is inoperative
captain Thompson contacts Alaska
airline flight dispatcher in Seattle
dispatch
copy that
if you want to land in LA
for safety reasons
we'll be looking at over an hour delay
because of the flow problem right now
I didn't really wanna
hear about the flow
I am concerned about
suitable airport
do you have a wind at LAX?
it's 260 at 9
the pilots compare the wind conditions
at Los Angeles and San Francisco airports
the pilots on this flight took such care
considering all their options on runways
there is headwind at LAX
but at San Francisco
there is a cross wind
26 at 9 vs direct cross wind
for safety reasons I think something
that lowers ground speed makes sense
the headwind at LAX will
help make it a safer landing
once your lined up
for the LAX runway
you've got perfect winds
coming right at your nose
it blows off the pacific ocean
it's predictable
it's constant
and it slows down your plane
good to guys of the
horizontal situation
ten minutes after rerouting
a mechanic at Alaska airlines
maintenance facility in Los Angeles
contacts the crew
affirmative
the maintenance facility can talk directly
to the pilots to provide the MD expertise
on the problem that
they're dealing with
did you try the suite-case
and pickle-switches?
yeah we try just about everything if
you've got any hidden circuit breakers
we love to know about them
yeah I look into the circuit
breaker guide as a double check
and the alternate
is inoperative too ha?
yep, our horizontal stabilizer
appears to be jammed
the whole thing
okay
thank you sir
see you when you get to LAX
the response from Alaska
airlines maintenance
was basically no response at all
they provided them no help
the really the most they ever
said to them did you try the
pickle switches and
suite-case handles
which were one of the
first things that they did
let's try the pickle
switches again
you've got it
the captain is warning the
first officer as a reminder
when we click the auto pilot off
be ready
because it's gonna require
a lot of effort from you
right then
let's click the auto pilot off
stabilizer motion
the nose of the plane drops
far more than the
pilots anticipate
holy crap
the airplane pitched
down significantly
and the airframe
is shaking violently
they know something is very
desperately wrong with the airplane
the problem is
suddenly much worse
flight 261 begins to nose dive
what are you doing?
it got worse
they have to get
the nose back up
or
they'll have an unrestricted
descent all the way to the ocean
help me back
okay
the crew of Alaska
airlines flight 261
struggles to regain
control of the MD-83
they pull back on
the control yoke
holding a lot of force
center
Alaska 261
we are in a dive here
I've lost control
of vertical pitch
Alaska 261
say again sir
we are on a vertical
dive at 26,000
they are now 3
minutes from impact
speed brakes
the pilots deploy
the speed brakes
control surfaces on the wings
of their plane that increase drag
any one to slow the plane down
it would also give them
more of a chance physically
to pull the plane
out of the dive
the speed breaks
are rest the dive
using all their strength
the pilots bring the aircraft
back on the control at 24,000 feet
once we get the speed slow
we will be okay
in 80 seconds the plane
has dropped 8,000 feet
the pilots pull out of the
dive with pure brute force
we've got it back
under control here
no we don't
even though they've
managed to pull out of the dive
it requires extreme effort to
keep the nose of the plane level
okay
really wants to pitch down
they're really having to work physically
and holding the nose up on this jet
they're in a fight for
control of the airplane
it's a lot worse than it was
yeah
we're on much worse shape now
this is a very experienced crew
these aviators have had
problems in flights before
but nothing like this
maintenance
are you on?
22 miles from Los Angeles
captain Thompson updates
Alaska airlines maintenance
hoping for advice
on how to land safely
yeah 261
this is maintenance
we've tried both the pickle
switch and suite-case handles
and it ran away
full nose trim down
oh
it ran away full trim
yeah now we're
worse than we were
this explaining that when
he commanded nose up trim
the trim system moved nose down
moved in opposite direction
of a way he commanded it
and it did so very quickly
and it did so
with a lot of force
you're getting full nose trim
down and no nose trim up
correct?
that's affirmative
we went full nose down and
now I'm afraid to tried it again
to see if we can get to go
back in the other direction
he is reluctant to try to
move it again for the concern
that if get worse yet
that they can lose control
of the airplane entirely
if you wanna try
that's okay with me
if not
that's fine
see you at the gate
after the maintenance space at
LAX said I will see you at the gate
the pilots knew
they're on their own
all they have left was
they had themselves
their physical strength
and their wits
to land the plane
the pilots need to figure out
how to control their descend
without using the
plane's trim system
you wanna try trim
switch again or not
no
I don't know
it's up to you man
they're literally test pilots
and they're having to utilize
decades of experience to try to
work their way through 2 solution
we gotta touch with
people back there
yeah
I know
captain Thompson tries
to reassure the passengers
folks, we've had a
flight control problem
we're intending to
go to Los Angeles
we're working on it and I
don't anticipate any problems
once we've got a couple
of systems back on the line
with Los Angeles in sight
the pilots prepare for
an emergency landing
flaps 15
let's go to 11
the pilots test the plane
in a landing configuration
okay, we're pretty stable here
but we gotta get
down to 180 knots
the jet is very badly damaged
and they need to understand
and find a way to
control the pitch of the jet
all the way through the landing
if it's controllable we
ought to try to landed it
first officers Tansky suggests
a risky high speed landing
okay
let's head for LA
their predicament was dire
they would not be
able to pull the plane up
and do a go around
the only chance they had was
one shot get it on the ground
or all would be lost
but as soon as they
come up with the plan
do you feel that?
yeah
the pilots hear thumps
of the back of the plane
then
disaster strikes
the airplane
pitched down and roll
they know that they are
in a life threatening situation
this is pilot's nightmare
you're running out of time
if they do not control the jet
very quickly
they'll lose the airplane
mayday
push and roll
18,000 feet above pacific ocean
flight 261 rolls left
and goes into a dive
this is like an airshow maneuver
blue angels do this
the thunderbirds do this
dropping at 160 feet per second
time is running out
okay
we are inverted
now we gotta get it up
when the airplane is inverted
this is a very difficult situation
because they've got to try to determine
if they can maintain control of it
and get the airplane
back right side up
the plane starts responding
they've pushed on
the control column
to prevent the
possibility of stall
and then they rolled the
airplane toward wings level
in an attempt to
maintain control of it
push push push the blue side up
the top side of the attitude
indicator is blue like the sky
and so they need to get the
blue side of the attitude indicator
back on the top
on the ground
LAX controllers have
lost contact with flight 261
Sky west 5154
traffic
at 1:00 o'clock is Alaska MD-80
do you see them up there?
they look for help
from other pilots
yes sir, definitely in
a nose down position
descending quite rapidly
he's inverted
okay, keep your eye on him
Alaska 261
are you with us yet sir?
30,000 feet over the ocean
the pilot's effort
seem to pay off
the plane's nose starts to rise
but it's still inverted
okay let's kick rudder
left rudder
the pilots are kind of
hanging upside down like bats
and it was very difficult to
reach the rudder and pedal
left rudder
I can't reach it
okay
right rudder
their one hope was it
they could kick that rudder
they could flip the
plane back over
okay
we gotta get it over again
at least upside
down we're flying
as the pilots fight to get
the plane the right way up
the engines on flight 261 failed
there was a
disruption in the airflow
into the engines and
it cause lost of thrust
speed brakes
got it
their demeanor was determine
collected
they were giving
everything they had
the windscreen
is full of the ocean
they're not gonna solve this
here we go
he's hit the water
he's down
search and rescue helicopters
are immediately dispatched
from coast guard stations
search team find debris
floating 2.7 miles north of Anacapa
Island of the coast of California
in addition to pieces of the plane
searchers are finding personal effects
a shoe ,a password, a postcard
aviation safety
advocate Mary Schiavo
represents the families of
6 passengers from flight 261
I remember this
person's possession
all the pictures were still in
the wallet in the pants pocket
except for the
picture of his wife
and so we knew by that
and by how they found things
that he had been clutching
that was really important to her
rescuers search for
survives throughout the night
none are found
all 88 passengers and crew
on board flight 261 are dead
it's terrible tragedy
thing, of course
but
you know we have a real
well established procedure here
for how these
tragedies are handled
investigators from the NTSB
(the National Transportation Safety board)
are assigned to find an
explanation for the crash
LAX maintenance has said the
pilots reported the jammed stabilizer
NTSB system's investigator
Jeff Guzzetti joins the investigation
we knew quite a lot just from
the transmissions between the
flight crew and Los Angeles
maybe they had a
mechanical problem
looks like they've tried
both switches, no luck
plane pitched
full nose trim down
we immediately began to research
the horizontal
stabilizer trim system
to see how it was designed
how it functioned
and how the crew
operated it normally
the leading edge of
the horizontal stabilizer
is raised or lowered
by a jack-screw
when activated it moves up
or down through an acme nut
changing the angle of
the horizontal stabilizer
we need to see the
jack-screw assembly
let's hope it's all one piece
investigators wonder how the
horizontal trim system could have failed
I'll get this to the navy
recovering parts of the stabilizer system
could give investigators important clues
but the wreckage field lies
on the bottom of the ocean
at the depth of 700 feet
well beyond the
reach of scuba divers
we were able to tell the navy
what to look for
what the high priority targets were
us navy crews use side scan sonar
to pinpoint the location of the wreckage
remotely operated vehicles
equipped with robotic arms
are used to recover
pieces of flight 261
the black boxes are retrieved
two days after the crash
9 days into the investigation
essential parts of the horizontal
stabilizer are also recovered
we've got the jack-screw
and with the brain power we had
we had a fighting chance to
find out exactly what went wrong
during this flight
what's this stuff?
investigators wonder
if recovered parts from the
horizontal stabilizer of flight 261
can provide clues
about why it failed
it's some kind of metal
what they see is puzzling
we saw this little
thin piece of metal
that we thought
look like a slinky
that really struck us
to something very odd
why isn't the nut
attached to the jack-screw?
normally the lower end of the
jack-screw is threaded through an acme nut
when we looked at that and saw that
the jack-screw wasn't part of the acme nut
we ask ourselves
how can that happen?
that really just blew our mind
the jack-screw and
the acme nut fell apart
then must have been
separated mid flight
threads 1/8 inch
thick inside the nut
should hold it securely
to the jack-screw
look at this
there is something
unusual about the nut
incredible
it's completely stripped
when we finally look
inside the acme nut
it revealed that there
were no threads inside of it
let's talk to metallurgy
it was shocking and stunning
to us to see something like this
no one thought that you could
get those thick threads to rip out
interesting
metallurgist Joe Epperson examine
the stripped nut and the jack-screw
it became immediately apparent
that what we were looking at
was actually the remainder of
the threads that were inside the nut
looks like the jack-screw
stripped the threads of the acme nut
and the next step in the process
was to figured out how the threads
were reduced to such an extreme degree
and then stripped out of the nut
there is some grease
here on the bottom
the team studies residue
observable on the jack-screw
the way to prevent
wear is by lubrication
with grease
and in the case of
extreme wear of event
you want to look at
is there grease where
it supposed to be?
and there is some
here at the top
in flight the jack-screw
rotates inside the nut
to prevent wear, it needs
to be lubricated regularly
there should be more
grease here in the middle
that's the working area
where it rotates the most
when we first looked
at the jack-screw
there was very minimal size that
there was any grease on it at all
it was in the ocean for a week
did the water washed
the grease away?
no, I don't think so
grease doesn't
washed off that easily
there is still some
remnants here
but none in the middle
we did find a little bit of remnant
of grease at the very upper end
and at the very lower end
there was very
easy to conclude that
being in the ocean had not washed
away the grease from the working area
of the jack-screw
how could it be that there so
little grease on this jack-screw
grease goes through here
during the lubrication process
during maintenance
grease is applied to
the interior of the nut
through small valve
called a zerg fitting
so the zerg fitting is
this fitting right here
and what mechanics have to do
is put a grease gun's hose in here
and then squirt grease
into this little grease fitting
that goes inside this passage
that zerk fitting should
have preserved and kept
the remnants of
whatever grease it saw last
what's that?
it's packed with dried grease
I've been around grease long enough
to know that if you don't replace it
and if you just leave it
eventually it dries up and gets hard
and it basically says that
it had not been replaced
how long has it been
clogged like this?
at least a year
maybe more
finding these blockage suggest
long term abuse to the grease
I'd say we have a
maintenance issue here
time to talk to the airline
we were very suspicious
about how well this
component was lubricated
or whether was
lubricated at all
and so we had our doubts as to
whether or not this component was
being properly maintained by the airline
NTSB investigators travelled to
Alaska airline's operations facility
in San Francisco
you work on the plane in Sept 1999
is that true?
yes I did
they tracked down the
mechanic who was responsible
for the last lubrication of
the jack-screw assembly
4 month before the accident
could you walk us through how you
lubricate the jack-screw assembly?
I'll tell you this
it's not my favorite job
the team learns
that jack-screw lubrication are
done most often on the night shift
outside the hanger
sometimes in the rain
you're working
on high lift trucks
which will sometimes move
with a gust of wind
the airplane moves
with the gust of wind
you're up at 13
feet off the ground
some mechanics
don't like that job
they're not stable up there
to reach the jack-screw
assembly we remove a panel first
how do you apply the grease?
I use a paintbrush
sometimes put a big lob in my
hand to make sure it's on there
aircraft specially large
aircraft need grease
they need to have
lubricants and it's messy
the most effective way is
to fill your hand with grease
and actually move it up
and down on the jack-screw
filling all the screw grooves
filling them with grease
what about greasing
the acme nut?
investigators focus on how the mechanic
grease the acme nut on the jack-screw
we use a grease
gun to the zerk fit
you pump grease unit you
see fresh grease coming out
well how you know whether the
lubrication is being done properly?
and when to stop
pumping the grease gun?
I don't it
would you be able
to see the grease
coming out from the top of
the acme nut during lubrication?
no I can't remember
looking to see if there was
one of the first
things that he tells me
is he couldn't have known
that zerk fitting has taking grease
you have no idea
that it's worked
so we found a variety of ways in which
mechanics lubricated this component
and that gave us some pause
because it's a very
critical component
if you don't lubricated properly
you could end up with an accident
like the one that just happened
the team discovers that the
methods air Alaska mechanics use
to lubricate the
jack-screw assembly
don't follow
maintenance standards
the last time that
jack-screw was lubricated
was about 4 month
before the accident
but it's not just the way the
jack-screw assembly is being lubricated
that bothers the investigators
it's also the frequency
and before that?
Jan 1999
they're doing it every
2500 hours
they can see there is a long
period between lubrication
is that even within regulations?
I'll find out
we knew we had kind of a
research project on our hands
some of the documents that we
requested from the manufacture
from the FAA
from the airline
came in the form of
internal memorandum
from engineering departments
or request from maintenance
to extend an interval
it really began to paint a picture of how
the lubrication intervals were extended
check it out
the airline made multiple request
to extend the interval on lubrication
the interval between lubrication
was 500 hours
the intervals between
lubrication are measures
by the number of hours
the plane is in the air
goes up
to 1200 hours
by 1996
increases all the up
to 2500 hours
they just continue to
extend extend extend
approved by the FAA
yeah, every one of
them was approved
investigators conclude that
the lubrication of jack-screws
was not only conducted poorly
it was also performed
less and less frequently
if you're gonna extend
these lubrication functions
then you better be doing something to
make sure that what you're doing is correct
but even if the lubrication
wasn't be done properly
regular inspections should have
caught the wear on that acme nut
true
they should have
inspected it regularly
was the jack-screw assembly
on flight 261 inspected
when and how it
should have be?
we looked at the maintenance records
for information about the last check
I've got something
investigators dig deeper
into the records of flight 261
to find out how the jack-screw
assembly was inspected
yeah, this doesn't
look right to me
the team finds paper work which
reveals that during routine inspection
a mechanic at the
airline's Oakland facility
observed that the
acme nut was badly worn
do you sure the
rating was 0.040?
a mechanic who
did that wear check
reported that he's
founded to be at the limit
this nut was wearing fast and
something needed to be done
lead mechanic order
the nut to be replaced
this was evidence that someone had caught
the fact that this acme nut was worn out
most the airlines
the decision would be
we'll get the piece to the airplane
as soon as possible and replace it
but the entries crossed out
I don't get it
but when we saw that they
had crossed out the first entry
that was very suspicious
something was up
it was fishy to us
we have to find out
what went on here?
do you remember inspecting
an MD-83 on Sept 27 1997?
I remember it well
investigators
contacted John Liotine
the lead mechanic who reported
the worn acme nut on flight 261
I wrote up the evaluation
the nut is worn down
replace it
it was an alarming discovery
in order for that
aircraft to be safe to fly
that nut assembly
at the very least
must be replaced
there's no doubt in my mind
it was the end of my shift
when I came back
the next workday
the plane was closed up
the plane returned to
service with the worn nut
if the nut had been replaced
the plane would still be flying
and 88 people
would still be alive
how can a maintenance
facility allow the airplane
to be put back in
the revenue service
with the wear that it
found on the acme nut
when investigators
probed further
they learned that the amount of wear on the
acme nut was rechecked by other mechanics
they determined that it
was just within minimum limit
Alaska airline's maintenance
misses a warning sign
the wear on the nut should
at least have been monitored
but it wasn't
the next time that
jack-screw was looked at
was in the NTSB laboratory
the plane flew with the
worn nut for two more years
before it took off from Puerto
Vallarta on the day of the accident
gear up
first officer Tansky and
captain Thompson had no idea
that their stabilizer was
on the verge of failure
strange
points AP TRIM
the team turns to
the voice recorder
to find out how the
devastating chain of events
unfolded on board flight 261
let's check this out
auto pilot off
good idea
wow
30 minutes after take
off from Puerto Vallarta
the warn threads in the acme
nut cause the jack-screw to jam
preventing movement
of the horizontal stabilizer
try again
the captain's trying to
rectify the jammed stabilizer
while cruising at 31,000 feet
the CVR picks up the sound
of a click followed by a thump
we think that the pilot was
moving his thumb switch on his yoke
in an attempt to move the
jack-screw through the nut
the threads finally give way
and the jammed jack-screw
pulls up through the nut
causing the stabilizer
to move upwards
a stopper is all the prevents
it from separating completely
it's got worst
with the horizontal stabilizer
pushing the nose further down
the plane goes into a dive
through sheer brute force
the pilots hold the
jack-screw in place
and recover the plane
okay, it really
wants to pitch down
do you feel that?
stop, let's hear that again
but 8 minutes later
there is another
series of thumps
do you feel that?
the stopper holding
the jack-screw in place
finally gives out
push and roll
the damage to the stabilizer
makes flight 261 uncontrollable
the plane rolls over and
dives towards the ocean
push the blue side up
flying upside down
the crew makes a last-ditch
attempt to right their plane
speed brakes
got it
the pilots of flight 261 give
everything they have to save the plane
it was just total professional
fighting for that plane till the very end
and they express
the realization that
the fight was over
here we go
I was seconded by what
I listened on the CVR
this accident could
have been prevented
they grease that jack-screw
this doesn't happen
the amount of money that
would have saved these lives
it's a cup of coffee
it's literally a few
dollars of grease
I still get angry
about it
in the wake of the accident
the intervals between jack-screw
lubrication at Alaska airlines
is reduced from 2500
hours to 650 hours
we lost 88 people
because of lack of lubrication
this is a maintenance accident
pure in simple
it's truly a tragedy
they just one of those cases that you
work on that's never gonna leave you
not ever
it was tough