staring down a thunderstorm
above the north sea
take a look at that
I don't like it
a modern turboprop is struck
by more than a million volts
after the lightening strike
you obviously looking to see
have we been damaged?
damn it
the plan is not responding
you can fly an aircraft
without a compass
you can fly an
aircraft without a radio
mayday mayday, we've been struck by
lightening and having control difficulties
you can't fly an aircraft
without functioning controls
but investigators can't
figured out how lightening
could have caused the
plane to behave the way it did
look at that
I mean the elevators are trying to
get the nose to pitch down instead of up
you're not come
across an aircraft where
there will be a this difference
between the pilot input
and what the aircraft
was actually doing
oh no
we're dropping
so distracted by that
they failed to see what
was really going on
it's 6:45 pm
Logan air Flight 6780
cruises over the
north sea near Scotland
let's get lower
request flight level 110 please
approach
Logan air Flight 6780
requesting descent to 110
descent to 110
the plane is more than half
way through a 65 minute flight
most of the passengers
live on the Shetland islands
are you done?
yes thank you
I'll take that
many are returning home from
holiday shopping in Aberdeen
air travel is massively
important to residents of Shetland
it's important for work meetings
it's important for sporting
events, for holidays
and it's the fastest
way to travel off island
and so it's quick and convenient
the captain is experienced
he has more than
5000 flying hours
and is the pilot flying tonight
passing flight level 150
the first officer is monitoring the
instruments and handling all communications
approach
Logan 6780
descending to flight level 150
for the IRS
runway 27
she has more than
1000 flying hours
Koei had a good total experience
of course they didn't have a lot
of experience flying up to 2000
but still
it was a normal experienced crew
the Saab 2000 is twin
engine high speed turboprop
it's plane that aviation analyst
Hans Peter Graf knows extremely well
the Saab 2000 is the
most advanced turboprop
still existing and flying
it has suchlike performance
paired with low fuel consumption
and it had real good
performance to fly in and out of a
mountainous terrain
they're traveling north
from Aberdeen Scotland
to Sumburgh on
the Shetland islands
a remote archipelago
prone to winter swells
and even hurricane
Logan air 6780
for your information looks like
the ATIS antenna at Sumburgh
has been struck by lightening
so this seems no functioning
I look the conditions
when I get them
okay
it's been a lot of
that so far this winter
the ATIS or automatic
terminal information service
provides pilots with continues
broadcast of essential information
it broadcasts weather and reports
information every 30 minutes
on which the pilots will base
era approaches and landings
I need your ATIS anyway
Sumburgh information Tango
winds 290 at 34
gusting 47, visibility
I guessed you're
gonna get fight after all
gusting 47
it's gonna get a bit
rough on the way down
the wind at Sumburgh airport
are blowing up to 47 knots
54 miles an hour
thee crew will be facing strong
gale force winds while landing
I traveled by a lot
when it does go windy
we would expect now a little bit
of turbulence on the way we knew
flight of that size
it's a small flight
you do feel and
turbulence more than what
you're within a bigger plane
and but it was nothing unusual
the captain wants to be ready for
any unpredictable weather thrown up
let's brief in case
of a lightning strike
copy that
okay
right
instruments lights are full
in case we have blinded
torches are here
and here on your side
and the emergency elevator
trim switch is over head
any question?
no questions
statistics suggest that
a particular aircraft would
probably get a lightening strike
about 1.5 times a year
you don't know when
it's coming of course and
the thing you're
aware of is that
these lightening strikes can
affects the electronics and
the avionics in the aircraft
Logan air 6780
flight heading 355
ATIS weather from
Sumburgh visibility
3300 now
while there are rain and snow
runway is wet
Logan air Flight 6780
got the weather, thanks
slow it down to 205
roger that
the crew prepares the plane
for the turbulence ahead
let's get them
buckled in back there
16 miles from Sumburgh airport
flight 6780 turns onto its
final approach to the runway
take a look at that
I don't like it
there is some bad weather
developing of the end of the runway
approach
Logan air 6780
as big storm set on
radar just of the runway
I need to discontinue
roger
let me know
all crews going into an airfield
in these source of conditions
will be
vary of the thunderstorms
activity around them
the pilots consider
their options
how much fuels we have left?
2500 kilos
do you want to head
back to Aberdeen?
I want to circle
making another attempt
they abandoned the approach when they saw
a lot of precipitation on the weather radar
just ahead of them
updrafts, downdrafts, wind shears
which are not predictable
so you better go around and
wait or divert to another airport
Logan 6780
we're gonna circle around
turning 180 for now
understood
maintain 2000
he obviously made the decision
that at that time he would
just turn away from the airfield
and properly allow that
weather to passed through
and then have another approach
as the pilot circled for
another landing attempt
crap
it sounded like a gunshot
it was just a very
short sharp noise
and flash
I thought at that point that it was
something that happened to the engines
if you experience a
lightening especially at night
it's a very bright light
you can smell a burnt smell
ozone smell and
that sure is
frightening or fearsome
to every crew
circuit breaker looks fine
after the lightening strike
you obviously looking to see
have we been damaged?
are the instruments
do working correctly?
but something is wrong
controls feel very heavy
damn it
the plane isn't responding
there must be a
degree of panic will set in
when the controls
are just not responding
plane isn't responding
mayday mayday
this is Logan air 6780
we've been struck by lightening
and having control difficulties
please clear the airspace
I knew that there is
definitely something not right
I was terrified
Logan air flight
6780 is in distress
2000 feet above the north sea
mayday mayday
this is Logan air 6780
please clear the airspace
copy
if you can
Say Souls on Board and Fuel Remaining
33 people on board
2500 kg of fuel
copy
all options are available
do you want to land or divert?
without knowing what's
wrong with the plane
that's really fighting me
it's too risky to attempt landing
in a storm at Sumburgh airport
we should divert back to
Aberdeen, better conditions
agree
Aberdeen airport
is 190 miles away
let's try climbing to 4000
6780 we're going to
divert back to Aberdeen
something is wrong
I can't get the plane to climb
how's your side?
it's really heavy
trims aren't doing
anything either
if you grab on the yoke and
the airplane isn't responding
they realize something is wrong
we need to do something
finally the crew
catches a small break
altitude is increasing
keep on it
the plane is climbing
but not as quickly
as it should be
the elevators might be damaged
in two minutes the plane
has barely climb 2000 feet
the first officer worries the lightening
strike may have disabled their instruments
Aberdeen
what's our altitude?
I saw you approaching 4000 feet
but the controller is getting the
exact same reading as the crew
we really not go anywhere fast
pull
I'm almost all the back
let's face it
you can fly an aircraft
without compass
you can fly an
aircraft without a radio
but you can't fly an aircraft
without functioning controls
and then the unthinkable happens
oh no
come on
we're dropping
flight 6078 plunges
uncontrollably towards the north sea
the flight went
into that nose dive so
we knew immediately that
that something wasn't
right with the plane
that's your height now
the pilots wrestle
with their controls
as the planes speed towards
the water at 350 miles an hour
you're descending
2000 feet
1800 feet
dive was so fast
you just felt like your
heart was your mouth
I had no idea how
close we were to the sea
you couldn't see anything
that was just pitch black
it was terrifying
it was really scary
you're descending
nothings working
come on
the airplane is less than
10 seconds from impact
must be incredibly frightening
because the pilots would
be aware of rate of decent
the would have
be aware of altitude
and they would be aware
of how much time left they had
to fatal recovery
speeds
in a last ditch effort
to save the plane
the captain increases
engine power
we're climbing
some increase in the power may increase
the amount of airflow over the wings
and give a little bit more lift
to allow the aircraft to
pull out of its descent
we were traveling at such speed
that when the plane started
pulling up again it was a
kind of sensation of
being on a roller coaster
it was definitely a relief to start
climbing after that nose pitch
the pilots have avoided
near catastrophe
but now they need to get their
plane back to Aberdeen safely
in the moments after that we had
a period of just
terrible turbulence
much turbulence
I've ever experienced
the man behind me start vomiting
it was kind of a flight
was quiet though
was kind of quiet
requesting flight level 240
roger
climb and maintain 240
controls are looking better now
ladies and gentleman
this is the captain
it was at that point
the pilot came on and
told us we've been struck
by lightening and we were
we were heading back to Aberdeen
we had some
flight control issues
everything is under control now
we'll be landing in
Aberdeen in 15 minutes
and please expect to see some emergency
services on the ground when we land
not to panic
it's just standard precaution
thank you
you go through moment like that
yeah, you panic until
you're on the ground
let's fly a straighter approach
I'm get this plane on the
ground as soon as possible
the pilots of Logan
air flight 6078
are on final approach
to Aberdeen airport
Aberdeen
establish on the localizer
runway 16
not knowing which
instruments they can trust
the pilots carefully
configure the plane for landing
flaps 35
controls feel normal
having avoided
disaster twice already
their soul focus is to get the
plane safely on the ground
speed looks good
decision height
on my side
continue
the pilot came on and told us
we'd be expected a normal landing
but the emergency services
would be on the runway
we want to be alarmed
if we saw the lights
all right
50 knots
coming out of reverse
checked
the landing was
smooth in Aberdeen
I was just glad that
we were on the ground
happy to be on solid ground
me too
I brushed into tears
it was relief more
probably than anything
a little bit of
shock probably too
it's up to investigators at the air
accidents investigation branch (AAIB)
to figure out what went wrong
David Miller is the deputy
chief overseeing the investigation
I decided that this would
be a full investigation
because of the closeness
this aircraft came to disaster
we then dispatched
small team of investigators
to the operators based to interview
the crew and to examine the aircraft
very quickly the flight data and cockpit
voice recorder are recovered from Saab 2000
very well
the normal price has for investigation
is the investigators take the recorder
the cockpit voice recorder
and the flight data recorder
bring them back to the
laboratories and recover the data
looks to be in pretty good shape
unusually sir
yeah
investigators need to confirm the
crew's report of a lightening strike
as well as the flight attendant's
account of seeing an orb of light
passed through the cabin
ball lightening is rare and
little understood phenomena
known to precede lightening
strikes inside airplanes
all right
well there is no
damage on the wing tip
the lightening can strike
almost anywhere on the aircraft
but it tends to strike on the
leading edge of the wings
on the radome at
the front of the aircraft
marks on the radio
investigators see signs of a lightening
strike on the nose of the aircraft
looks like some surface
damaged as well
yeah
the point of strike
will often leave scar
localize burning
sometimes a small hole
right let's see where
it exited the aircraft
elevators look fine
hang on
have a look at that exhaust cone
oh yeah
that's where the
lightening exited
it could have possibly
completely melted
there is little bit of burning damage
both to the front of the aircraft
and the exit point of the lightening strike
which was at the very tale of the aircraft
where the auxiliary power
unit exhaust was placed
oh
crap
the team now knows how
the lightening struck the plane
controls feel very heavy
so one of the first thing
you gotta have a look at
what was the effect
of the lightening strike?
where the systems damaged?
were there malfunctions?
okay
you're ready
the AAIB tests the
plane's flight control
to see if they're working
okay
check the rudder
looks good
how about the elevators?
yeah, elevators are working too
everything checks out
investigators are perplexed
if the plane was
functioning properly
why did it become so difficult to
control after the lightening strike?
there were no abnormalities
no system defects that we can find
either structurally or within the avionics
beyond that
it looked like a completely
normal serviceable aircraft
AAIB investigators interviewed
the pilots of flight 6078
we're fortunate enough
as in these circumstances
to have a surviving flight crew
then their recollections are really
important for us to understand
exactly how the event
progressed from their perspective
so what happened after the
lightening struck the plane?
after the lightening struck
the auto pilot disconnected
I have control
the crew of the aircraft
become aware
early shortly after
the lightening strike
the aircraft wasn't responding as they
expected to their flight control inputs
and then what happened?
we had control issues
plane wouldn't climb
we tried everything and
the plane wasn't responding
the pilot flying
was finding that he was having to
put an increasing strong backward effort
on the control column
to rise the nose of aircraft
I can't get the plane to climb
how's your side?
it's really heavy
trims not doing anything either
the aircraft wasn't responding
the way that he expected
and then
and then we enter
the steep nose dive
and the control issues continued
nothing working
come on
pull up
speed
and wasn't until after
we increased power
we were able to get
the aircraft under control
oh really
why did the crew believe that they had
control restrictions and control problems?
when in fact testing of the aircraft
show that there were no faults
lest have a listen
shall we?
puzzled by the crew's account of
the incident on board flight 6078
investigators turn to the cockpit
voice recorder for answers
it will answers many questions
as to why things were
happening the way they were
and how the crew were working
together and interacting together
but something's not right
Aberdeen
this is for when they
land back at Aberdeen
stop it and
go back to the top
play it again please
that's what there is
well that's not gonna
help us very much now, is it?
the CVR has recorded over
the critical moments of the flight
it's a major setback
for the investigation
we discover that the cockpit voice
recorder which only last for 30 minutes
has been overwritten
by subsequent events
so there was no record
of crew conversation
and how they
interacted with each other
and so you have to look
elsewhere for information
right
this is what we know so far
the lightening struck
the auto pilot disconnected
they had control problems
then
the plane did a nose dive
let's review the data
will the data recorder provide the
answers they need to solve this case?
flight data recorders
often add a level of detail
that simply can't be gain
from the witnesses themselves
and crucially
quite often the information that's
gathered from a recording device
offers a slightly different
perspective to what we might get from
personal recollections
so
this is where the
lightening struck at 2000 feet
right and then the next
2.5 minutes there is a slow
uneven climb to 4000 feet
and then they are in a very steep nose
dive 20 seconds towards the north sea
that's 500 feet per minute
investigators are struck by how
close the flight came to total disaster
it was 7 seconds
from plunging into the sea
before they finally manage
to pull out at 1100 feet
the aircraft had a very
high rate of descent
in a moments before
reached that height
and so we were really very
close to very serious accident
what were the pilots doing
to recover from the dive?
look at the control column data
right after the lightening strike
crew pull back on the control
column to pitched the nose up
I have control
controls feel really heavy
look at the line, I mean
they're having a very difficult
time getting that plane to climb
we know from the data that the
aircraft climb to around about 4000 feet
the pilot was finding that he was
having to put an increasing strong
backward effort on the control
column to raise the nose of the aircraft
and the aircraft wasn't
responding the way the he expected
the FDR data confirms the pilots
were tackling a control problem
but why?
the captain said they
were also applying pitch trim
pitched trim moves the
tail elevator up and down
to maintain the
pitch of the aircraft
can we take a look at
the pitch trim data please?
right
investigators make
a puzzling discovery
look at that
the elevators trying to get the
nose to pitch down instead of up
after the lightening strike
some unknown force was
fighting the pilot's inputs
to both the control
column and the pitch trim
it's very difficult
to imagine what
let's say 80 pound
force feels like
normal control pressures
are much much lower than that
sort of 10 to 20 pounds
so an 80 pound pull is really extraordinary
and very difficult to maintain
something is wrong
I can't get the plane to climb
how's your side?
it's really heavy
trim is not doing
anything either
we found that although the pilots
were applying a significant nose up pitch
control input while pulling
the stick back towards them
the aircraft was
actually trims nose down
whatever was trimming
the pitch control system
was effectively overcoming
the effort of the pilots
the crew said
the lightening struck
the autopilot disconnected
then they had control problems
can we take a look at
the auto pilot database?
finally the team
zeros in on the answer
the auto pilot was on
almost the entire time
the pilots themselves were very clear in
their recollection that it had disengaged
while the evidence we had indicated that
the autopilot had in fact remained engaged
it's no wonder the pilot
had control problems
the auto pilot was to set to
keep the plane 2000 feet
right and whenever the pilot's
trying to get the plane to climb
the autopilot would engaged
and bring the plane back down
back to a signed up altitude
investigators discover that
after the lightening strike
the pilots were in a
tug of war with the plane
I can't get the plane to climb
how's your side?
it's really heavy
so then we have to
look at why did the crew
misunderstand the
status of the aircraft
the AAIB contacts the
captain of flight 6078
to better understand why he
taught the auto pilot disconnected
when in fact it hadn't
the Saab 340
okay
thanks
he said he assumed the lightening
would disable the auto pilot
the team learns the pilot trained for
lightening strikes on another airplane
the Saab 340
the change from Saab
340 to the Saab 2000
you can say it's like changing
from a motor bike to a bus
all systems are different
performance is different
you're flying a totally
different airplane
during the training of Saab 340
the commander had experienced a
simulated lightening strike to the aircraft
which cause both
generators to fail
and in doing so
cause the auto the
pilot to disconnect
I have control
so when the lightening
strike happened for real
his first thought were
the auto pilot has failed
the controls feel very heavy
I must control
the aircraft myself
and in fact the lightening
strike had had minimal effect
on the aircraft
would you pull up the control
data column again please?
if the lightning didn't
disconnect the autopilot
investigators wonder why it remained
engaged for more than 2 minutes
as the pilots struggled
with the controls
wouldn't the force applied to the
control column and the pitched trim
have overwritten the autopilot?
in most aircraft
if the pilot intervenes
on the controls
and tries to apply a
forced against the autopilot
the autopilot
decided to disengage
one way of thinking about this is to
imagine you're driving down a highway
in a car on cruise control
and you're getting close
to a car in front of you
so you press the break
and what you expect to
happen is for the car to slow down
you don't expect the cruise
control to oppose the break
and add more power to
maintain 65 miles an hour
but that's essentially what
was happening in this case
the autopilot was attempting
to keep the plane at 2000 feet
despite all attempts
by crew to climb
says here
applying an override force to the column
will not cause the auto pilot to disengaged
and the Saab 2000
the autopilot would not
disconnect when you exert force
on the control columns
there is more
pressing the main
pitch trim switches
also has no effect to cause
the autopilot disengage
the team is
surprised to discover
there is no force override for
the autopilot in the Saab 2000
something's wrong
I can't get the plane to climb
one thing the pilot would
have done as he pulled back
have feeling the force
on the control column
he would have used the switches
on the control column, to apply
trim inappropriate way
how's your side
it's really heavy
trims not doing anything either
but when the autopilot
engaged in this model of aircraft
the trim switches are inhibited
so no matter how much they
selected those trim switches
they were having
absolutely no effects
investigators soon
discover that the Saab 2000
is unique
look at that
it's one of the few
planes in existence
that doesn't have
an autopilot override
every plane has an
autopilot override function
except for the Saab 2000
it just had a different design to
all the other aircraft we're aware of
and really to discover that the autopilot
had greater authority than the human pilots
was a bit of revelation for us
it's still doesn't explain
why the crew didn't know
the autopilot was on
almost the entire time
wouldn't be some sort of
indicator on the cockpit?
yeah, I show you
look over here
when the autopilot is
connected that will be a green AP
what does a control panel look
like when the autopilot goes off?
like this
when that autopilot is not
connected it will be a white AP
but the letters AP remain
that's it
that's it just goes
from green to white
one could argue weather
that visual clue is enough
to warn the crew
status of the autopilot
I have control
it's not as if the AP disappears when it's
not engaged and appears when it is engaged
oh no
come on
we're dropping
all we have here is color
change between green and white
and sometimes is very
difficult to perceived
when you're in a
high stress situation
investigators believed
that the auto pilot visual indication might
have been too small for the pilots to see
as they struggle to
control their plane
sure there would have
been alarm warnings
yes right here
it says the plane's computer
would have sound the caution chime
even if the pilots missed the
visual indications for the autopilot
caution chimes would have alerted
them when they adjust the pitched trim
the captain didn't say anything
about hearing any chimes
right so
what's going on them?
they're trimming against the
auto pilot for more than 10 seconds
a chime will announce to say that
there is a pitch miss trim situation
we see from the data it's highly
likely that the alert would have occurred
but the crew don't
recall having heard it
nothings working
come on
so why did the
pilots of flight 6078
ignore all warnings telling them
that the autopilot was in control?
AAIB investigators have learned
that after the lightening strike
the crew of Logan air flight 6078
didn't recall hearing audible warnings
that the auto pilot was engaged
and set to maintain 2000 feet
the lightening struck the plane
and for 2.5 minutes
the crew struggle with the
controls to get the plane to climb
right, they were
so distracted by that
failed to see what
was really going on
could stress have affected
that perception of the situation?
you have to bear in mind
of course this was at night
in turbulent poor weather
heavy rain
and the lightening strike would
have been really quite bright
and the noise would
have been alarming
so it's sort of understandable
their performance was degraded
because of the stress situation
I have control
the couple of things
happen when we get stressed
we tend to focus on
fewer and fewer things
and we tend to not
notice the other things
and that can be
either visual cues or
auditory cues
so we get what's called
cognitive tunneling
and one aspect to that is
an essential deafness so
an alert might occur
but we might not hear it
it's very difficult
for a crew to
break the vicious circle of
cognitive tunneling where
a concentrating on one event
and not looking on the bigger picture
controls feel really heavy
but if the pilots were suffering
from cognitive tunneling
how would they able to
regain control of the plane?
okay
look at this
the AAIB makes one
last horrifying discovery
the only reason the
autopilot ever disengaged
was because of a random glitch
in the plane's computer system
reason for disconnection
was that there was a
a momentary lost
of data of computer
and we know that's one of the conditions
that caused the autopilot disconnect
and that's what cause it
to disconnect in this case
if the autopilot wouldn't
disconnected more than 7 seconds later
the plane would have gone
into the ocean in a night
at over 300 knots
this was a fatal
action by pure lock
investigators believed
they finally understand
what caused the terrifying incident
on board Logan air flight 6078
while circling away from a
bad storm at Sumburgh airport
roger that
we'll wait till the storm ...
the crew startled and
disoriented by a lightening strike
in a moment of high stress the captain
believes the autopilot has disengaged
I have control
when it hasn't
the autopilot remain engaged and
they didn't realize that was the case
so effectively from that point until it
disengaged they were fighting the autopilot
they wanted to climb
it wanted to descend
because of the way the flight control
configures the autopilot was going to win
engaged in a tug of
war with the aircraft
cognitive tunneling takes over
something is wrong
I can't get the plane to climb
how's your side?
the highly stressed pilots don't
register the audible warnings
telling them that the
autopilot is still engaged
it's really heavy
trim is not doing
anything either
the final blow is one of a kind
autopilot system without a force override
I have every sympathy for crews being
startled with something unusual happens
whether there is an explosive engine
failure or lightening strike in this case
but the training must kick in
and the crew must revert to
in effect as I said sit on
your hands for a few moments
make an assessment
of what's happened
what's gone wrong
what's working, what's not working
and then deal with
the situation from there
oh no
come on
we're dropping
if it wasn't for a split second
fluke error in the computer system
and the relentless
efforts of the crew
speed
flight 6078 would have slammed
into the north sea at 380 miles per hour
I would say it was a nervous
flight for a couple of years
so I've just kind of gone
through the emotions of
sort of building myself up to noon
it's gonna be fine
the final report recommend several
safety changes to the autopilot system
within my recommendations looking at
how aircraft could be certified in future
so make sure that no future design could
be certified where neither operation of the
control column nor operation
of the pitch control switches
would result in
disconnection of the autopilot
for investigators the
lessons of Logan air 6078
go beyond this one near tragedy
you can only go so far in
educating human operators
in how system works
ultimately we have to recognize
that they will behave instinctively
particularly when under stress
that's the real challenge for
the future of automated systems