a business jet shuttling
passengers to Akron, Ohio
no no no
slams into a residential neighborhood
less than 2 miles from the runway
we have a plane into a house
heavy fire
there are no survivors
investigators searched the
wreckage but find few clues
the aircraft was burned down
to almost nothing on the hill
but a close examination
of radar data
provides a lead
they're clear to descend
and then they wait
full two minutes
why?
we really wondered what is the
situation in the cockpit at that time?
hey you guys you know
where you are going
it's going to be some weather so
I'd like to have your
update with the flight
well did you hear that?
execuflight Flight 1526
is climbing towards
cruising altitude
over the us Midwest
let's keep climbing
with 150 feet per minute
roger
on board are 7 executives from a
Florida base property management company
sorry
they've charted the
luxury jet from execuflight
a private carrier based
in Fort Lauderdale
Donnie Shackleford is a former
captain who flew with execuflight
execuflight caters to the people of
south Florida for business purposes
also to entrepreneurs,
athletes and even entertainers
17,000 feet
roger
leveling off
execuflight 1526 is flying
a short 35 minute flight
north east from
Dayton to Akron Ohio
first officer Renato Marchese is the
pilot flying the twin engine Hawker 700
he's logged more than 4000
hours flying various private jets
Captain Oscar Chávez
is originally from Colombia
and he's logged over 6000 hours
flying private jets and cargo planes
the captain had flown
with me as the first officer
he was to get pilot
Oscar and Renato both same to enjoy flight
a great deal
it was a passion
for both of them
hey guys
we've just reached
our cruising altitude
you know the drill
we'll be landing at
Akron in half an hour
anyone else want a drink?
the Hawker 700 passenger
experience was more than comfortable
they had a good galley
had plenty of headroom
the interior was updated
it was a very nice airplane
cheers
zipline 1526
decent to 13000
zipline is
execuflight's call sign
descending to 13000 feet
thank you zipline 1526
let me check the weather
automated weather observation
wind 290 at 07
overcast 1800
temperature 0.9 Celsius
right
we have overcast weather
the crew prepares for
possible bad weather in Akron
okay
let's see
Akron
right
heading
24 at 9
flight 1526 continues its decent
Akron airport is less
than 20 minutes away
I'm gonna go check
to see where we're at
hey you guys know
where you're going?
you bet
look
it says we're here on the chart
I'd love to have you
updated all the time
but there's going to
be some weather
so we can't be distracted
it's not like the airlines
where you have a close door
there is an open door I mean they
can .. to the cockpit and ask questions
as flight 1526
descends to 9000 feet
Akron visibility 1.5 mist
sky condition
overcast 600 broken
the crew learns the weather
in Akron is getting worst
temperature 11 Celsius
they need to know if it's
still possible to land there
1.5 mile of visibility
what visibility does
this approach want?
1.25 miles
all right
so we have visibility
6 minutes from Akron, the
crew has a new distraction
a flight instructor
he's teaching a student pilot
how to land in bad weather
on the same runway
assigned to flight 1526
zipline 1526
we do have another aircraft that's inbound
to the airport that is slower than you
flight heading 360
reduce speed to 170
descend and maintain 3000
the crew is asked
to alter their course
delay the descent and
maintain their altitude at 3000 feet
speed is 170
and 360
zipline 1526
the piper is on the ground
you are clear for localize 25 approach
clear for localize at 25, thank you
zipline 1526
the piper radios flight 1526
with the weather update
hey guys
we just land on the localizer
and broke out
right at the minimum
appreciated
they said we broke
out right at minimum
which means you're at the minimum
visibility necessary for the approach
flight 1526 is now 4
miles from the runway
as it starts its final approach
everything is all set
standby
2.5 miles from the airport
the pilots are still
searching for the runway
finally the plane breaks
through the clouds
ground
keep going
okay okay
level up that
I got it
pull up
hey what's going on?
no no no
we have a plane into a house
heavy fire
we have a lot of wires down
execuflight 1526 has crashed
into a two story residential building
everyone on board is dead
the NTSB must now determine
what caused this fatal?
execuflight 1526 plunged into a
residential neighborhood in Akron, Ohio
incredibly
none of the residences
were home during the crash
but the neighborhood is on edge
you just don't think
of a plane would drop
in a residential area like this
this is crazy
looks like the
left wing hit first
when NTSB investigators
arrived on scene
they notice a large gouge
leading to the crash site
one of the first thing I notice as walking
up was a large gouge in the front yard
in front of one of
the town homes
it obviously told me that there was
a control problem with this airplane
on the approach
flaps at 45
investigators closely
examine the wreckage
to determine how the
plane was configured
one of the things that we did learn
very early on was flaps were at a
45 degree or 4
configuration for this landing
we knew they were trying to land
so
they configure the land
then they crashed less than
two miles from the runway
why?
let's take a look at the engines
did the engines fail as the
plane approach the airport?
it's a pretty bad shape
one of the things that we were looking for
with the engines at the accident site was
if there were operating
really wanted to see if there was
dirt concrete bits that type of thing
inside the engine
it's like a building insulation
soil
those gave us indications and add
impact these things were producing power
the NTSB is no further ahead in
solving the mystery of flight 1526
a team is dispatched
to air traffic control
hoping the controller
can provide some insight
no mayday call
nothing unusual
well
they were delayed by a
piper that was ahead of them
I instructed them
to change heading
reduce speed
and maintain
until cleared
which I did it
14:49:22
when they were 5 miles out
zipline 1526
the piper is on the ground
you are clear for
localize at 25 approach
the piper didn't
affect their landing
the piper was on the ground
when the business jet was
still about 5 miles from the airport
ample distance
for a safe landing
at the crash site investigators comb
through the wreckage for more clues
what I needed to know was
was there anything in
the accident wreckage
that was recoverable from
an operational standpoint
the material that the pilots used
the cockpit
things that can be documented
that's what I wanted to see
hey check this out
we found manuals that pilots
were required to have on board
this is something
grab an evidence bag
it was damaged and it was burnt
but we were able to examine it
investigators then make the
most significant discoveries so far
we found angle of attack
indicator in the cockpit wreckage
that's important because
at the certain angle of attack
wing will stall
what angle were you?
it was damaged extensively
but I could see that the
needle was in the red band
when the angle of attack
indicates that it's in the red
you stall
another words
this wing was no longer flying
as simple as that
investigators determine that the
plane stalled as it approach the airport
now they must understand
why?
pull up
that's great
get that to Washington
the cockpit voice recorder from
execuflight Flight 1526 is recovered
and sent to NTSB
headquarters for analysis
when we found out the aircraft did have
a cockpit voice recorder, the first thing
we were very interested in doing is
making sure it got back to our labs
I didn't know if we
had good information
the CVR is doubly
important in this case
since the Hawker 700 wasn't
equipped with the flight data recorder
flight data recorders are incredibly
important because they give us a
no question look and precisely what the
flight dynamics were all the way to impact
this investigations are
like a jigsaw puzzle and
with the flight data recorder
the pieces of puzzles are much
bigger and easier to put together
but not having a flight data recorder it
didn't give us a whole lot of information
early on in the investigation
while investigators wait
for the voice recording
they worked with what they have
the documents found
in the cockpit wreckage
the weight and balanced
look at that
we found that the weight and balance
didn't account for the auxiliary power unit
say
a little jet engine in the back that helps
power the aircraft when it's on the ground
so they had no APU
the team wonders how this compares
to what they discovered at the crash site
hello APU
we saw that the APU was on board
cause we found it on the wreckage
looks like they were carrying
more weight than they thought
investigators believed
they found an error
in the plane's documented
weight and balance
were they too heavy?
I wonder how much this
plane truly weight
the pilots made their calculations
without accounting for an APU
but there clearly
was one on board
we certainly had a concern about
weather or not the airplane
was within its weight and balance
the NTSB calculates the actual
weight of the plane during its final flight
the APU weights 300 pounds
and according to the aircraft refueler
they were loaded with 8160 pounds of fuel
but they only burn down 7700
so how much in total
were they over by?
they were only 286
pounds over weight
the plane's actual weight was slightly
more than what the pilots recorded
it wouldn't really made a
performance difference on the aircraft
the weight of the APU and the
additional fuel was not enough
to effect the balance
of the airplane
but it did tell us that this crew in this
company wasn't following their procedures
appropriately
somebody wasn't watching what
they were supposed to be doing
investigators need to look elsewhere
to explain why flight 1526 stall
we knew that there is not a
flight data recorder on this airplane
so that's frustrating because we don't
have the precise details about the airspeed
the altitude and
attitude of the aircraft
to solve the case
the NTSB begins compiling
what data they do have
the radar data from
air traffic control
show me what you've got so far
a turning point in investigation
came when our our engineer
was able to recreate our aircraft
performance from the radar data
okay
they're 150 knots
4 minutes before the crash
keep going
our aircraft performance expert was able
to estimate the air speed, the airplane
the angle of attack, the attitude
the altitude and rate of descent
as a plane approach to airport
you expect the
airspeed to decrease
it drops from 300 down to 150
everything normal
investigators find nothing
unusual about the flight
until they focus on
the last two minutes
look here
the speed drops to 130 knots
and then keeps dropping to 98 knots
no wonder they stall
the thing that really stood out
was the excessive rate of descent
at the very end was 98 knots
which is gonna
stall the airplane
airspeed is life
it's one most important point of
flying any airplane but specially
specially a jet
maybe they were trying
to stay clear the piper
I doubt it
controller told them the runway
was clear 3 minutes before it stalled
the airspeed data leaves
investigators with more questions
let's look at the altitude data
the team reviews the
plane's descent profile
for the period
leading up to the crash
the early part of the
descent looks pretty normal
they're doing a dive
and drive approach
they level off at 9000
5000, 4000
but look that
that's odd
you blow that up
they make an important discovery
look
they hold it 3000 feet
for an entire two minute
that's way too long
and then they plunged steeply
bring up the final approach
they were supposed to take
it's not even close
on normal approaches of the glide
path allows the airplane to descent
general 3 degree path all
the way down to the runway
looks like they started
their final approach too late
and then after
race to catch up
the data shows that after
delaying their approach
the pilots descended
very steeply
and at twice the normal rate
once they started diving the
airplane down to 2000 feet a minute
to get to that lower altitude
that approach was unstable
and at that point of time they
should have executed to go around
controller told us
they acknowledged
his instruction to descent
zipline 1526
the piper is on the ground
you are clear for localize
25 approach
clear for localize at 25
thank you
they're clear to descent
and then they wait
full two minutes
why?
we really wondered what is the
situation in the cockpit at that time
NTSB investigators turn to the
cockpit voice recorder from flight 1526
to understand why the pilots
delayed their final descent into Akron
take it from the first
instruction about that piper
zipline 1526 we do have an aircraft inbound
to the airport that is slower than you
flight heading 360
reduce speed 170
descend and maintain 3000
down to 3000
170 is the speed
and 360
zipline 1526
down to 3000
he want 170 knots
okay
somebody lower the landing gear to
start slowing the airplane up and creating
drag to hopefully get
a little bit more spacing
between them and
the other airplane
did you hear what he's said?
there is another
plane on the approach
it's slower than us, we don't
know if it's on the ground yet
the captain was very concern about
the space between them and training flight
and was saying
that to the copilot
did you hear that?
investigators hear the sound
of engine trust decreasing
let's see the airspeed again
the airspeed drops
from 170 down to 140
that's way slower than
you need to be going
look
you're going 140
zipline 1526
the piper is on the ground
you're clear for localize
25 approach
clear for localize at 25
thank you
flight 1526 is now at 3000 feet
and position to flight
straight into Akron airport
they should start their descent
why did the pilots delay their descent
for 2 minutes forcing them to catch up?
you're going 120
you can't keep
decreasing your speed
once the copilot received a warning
from the captain that they were too slow
the copilot should have
increased thrust significantly
but instead the
pilots get into a debate
when you get 120?
it's more like 125
which is the approach speed
but you still got
the flaps to go
when they go down
this is what I'm saying if you
continue decreasing your speed
but why?
because we're gonna stall
I don't wanna stall
how do we ...
stop
they are so busy
arguing about their speed
that they forget to
start their descent
there is about 2 minutes of conversation
concerning the airplane speed
the pilot and first officer were actually
argument that they was getting too slow
they delay of almost
2 minutes was critical
he's already too slow and he's
over flown the altitude it should be in
now they've got to
chase the approach
now he's got to get
the airplane down fast
okay
what investigators hear
next is even more shocking
hey guys
we just landed on the localizer
and broke out right at minimum
they were notified that the smaller
airplane had landed safely on the runway
full flaps
stop
full flaps at that speed
what was he thinking?
bring up the
altitude graph again
okay that's why the plane
starts to drop like a rock
the team finally
understands why flight 1526
ended up in a 2000
feet per minute descent
twice the recommended rate
the first officer was racing to
get the plane back on course
the airplane is too high
is too slow
and with full flaps
rather than partial flaps
they really needed
to get down in a hurry
and really that is a
turning point when we said
this airplane is not configure
properly for the approach
and this puts the crew and
passengers in really a lot of danger
he should have just
called the missed approach
try it again
investigators now need to understand why
the pilots continue their dangerous descent
when we look at the
errors that the pilots made
we really had to wonder
what was their background?
NTSB investigators Sathya Silver
examines the pilots' personnel records
to see if they explain their
behavior on the day of the accident
the first officer had more
than 4000 hours of flight time
he was the pilot in
command for 3200 hours
and he passed all his courses
yep
yeah just turned 50
no sign of drug or
alcohol in the system
but
take a look at this
looks like he flew all night
two nights before the accident
could it have been fatigue?
for the first officer
what we found was
he did not have the
rest several days earlier
that regulation required
see what the airline has to say
so we wanted to take a look and
see if a chronic fatigue problem
may have manifested itself
several days later to hopefully
explain why this crew and particularly
first officer was making so many mistakes
thanks for coming in
happy to help out
silver interviews execuflight
Donnie Shackleford
who had flown with first officer
Marchese leading up to the crash
tell me about your last
flight with the first officer
two days before the accident
we flew into Fort Lauderdale
they want me to fly
to Mexico over night
like now
that would me fine to go
considering the duty time issue
as long as they remained
overnight in Mexico
so
did he sleep
overnight in Mexico?
nope
came right back before Lauderdale
I talked to him the
night before the crash
he told me that he was
worn out from the other trip
even though he was legal as far as the
number of hours between he was not rested
he should not have
been on that flight
the fact that the first officer
had to fly an overnight flight
and not sleep when
his body wanted to sleep
resulted in circadian disruption
we know that human
beings have limits
if you're not getting the appropriate
sleep over time your attitude
can go to the heck in a hand-basket
and that can crash airplanes
because the first officer did
have the required amount of sleep
the night before the crash
investigators can't definitively
point to sleep deprivation
as the cause of their
poor decision making
there is something about
the flight that still trouble silver
how often would the first
officer be the pilot flying?
only if there were
no paying passengers
why?
company policy
the company did have
a procedure to enable
first officer to get
experience flying the aircraft
and those were in empty legs
where passengers weren't on board
Renato should not
have been flying
it should have been Oscar
Silva discovers that the captain
violated standard operating procedures
what we don't know and what is a
little confusing is why in this case
when you had
passengers in the back
you had weather that
was gonna be a factor and
an approach that was gonna
be relatively challenging
why this captain decided to
allow that his first officer to fly?
the NTSB wants to know why
captain Chávez broke company policy
allowing his first officer flying
the plane with clients on board
take a look at this
the captain didn't
get much sleep either
he got a full night
sleep before the crash
but he didn't get a full 8
hours for 4 nights before that
maybe he was also fatigue
that's possible
as we looked for their back
into his records it looks like
the days prior
he actually only averaged
about 6 hours of sleep
investigators listen for any indication
of fatigue on the cockpit voice recorder
let's pick up where we left off
the start of a final descent
descending from 3000 feet
the crew begins
their landing checklist
ignition
everything is all set
stand by
fuel damper
auto pilot
he just stopped
in the middle of
his landing checklist
it's like he's distracted
there were checklist that
were supposed to be done
all the way through we
found on cockpit voice recorder
all the checklist that they should have
complied with were never completed
instead of finishing
the checklist
the captain's focus turns
to the plane's erratic descent
you're diving
don't dive
2000 feet per minute
body
yeah
2000 feet per minute
don't go 2000 feet per minute
with me there?
the copilot was being
coached so much by this captain
that at this point, this is the very
serious portion of the approach
you're gonna go down
into weather that's very low
and very significant
the captain should
have taken control
when it's time for the captain
to say I've got the airplane
cause you're not
performing well enough
there should be no
question and no hesitation
why wouldn't he take over?
investigators hear more than the
effects of fatigue on the recording
by having the first officer fly
this captain then
was dividing his time being a
captain and also being an instructor
we found he wasn't appropriately
managing the cockpit as a captain
don't go 2000 feet per minute when
you're 500 feet above the ground
bring up the
altitude graph again
they're less than
500 feet off the ground
it's below their
minimum descent altitude
it's critical that you do not
descent below that altitude
until you have a visual view
of the airport or the runway
but they continue to descent
ground
god, he can see the
ground but not runway
they're coming
down from 3000 feet
they've got to get to the
minimum descent altitude
which is only 500
feet above the ground
there is not much room to
work with if you screw this up
keep going
the CVR reveals that the captain
violated a fundamental rule
by continuing descent
without a runway insight
you don't see the field
then you do a go around
because the pilot was
still looking for the airport
while descending
below minimum altitude
neither of them notice
they're decaying airspeed
okay level up now
got it
pull up
they've been too slow
for the last little while
and they don't recognize even
with stick shaker banging away
then they are aerodynamic stall
pull up
that doomed them
they weren't able to
recover from the stall
this is perfect stall
of their own making
investigators find enough evidence
on the voice recording to conclude
that fatigue was likely one component
of the crew's poor decision making
we found that
the captain's behavior could
have been attributed to fatigue
but fatigue alone
doesn't explain the long list of
botched procedures on flight 1526
they broke so many rules, makes
you wonder who trained them
they weren't following
their procedures
they missed
checklist and call outs
they've got the wrong
way on the approach
they were flying in
the wrong configuration
we decided to go back and
take a look at their training
what was it that led up to
them making these mistakes?
the NTSB orders up the
employment and training records
of the crew of flight
1526 for the last five years
you're not gonna believe this
they are shocked
by what they find
the captain's termination notice
says that he was
fired from his last job
investigators learned that
the captain was dismissed
because he failed
to show up for training
get this
the first officer was terminated because
his performance was below standard
the first officer was let go because
he struggle during flight training
both these guys
had training issues
and were fired because of them
and execuflight knew about it
the captain's fire
employment was suspect
in terms of why was he dismissed
the first officer's hiring
in this particular case
smacks of just warm body hiring
having somebody with 98 degree
temperature putting in the right seat
and say we've got a
copilot cause he's licensed
so
why did execuflight
hire these guys?
we start to wonder
did the company know
about these deficiency?
if they did
did they address them?
okay, thanks again
bye
I just got off the phone
with the president
he said he knew about their history
but hired them anyway
the president of execuflight
said that he'd hired the captain
because of his extensive
experience in the Hawker aircraft
as well as flights that had
personally taken with the captain
prior to his employment
the first officer was hired based on
a recommendation from another pilot
as well as one flight that he
had taken with him personally
he said that they didn't
contact their previous employers
it's very very important in hiring
a pilot to do what the law says
and what the regulation say
contact the previous employers
and have an opportunity
to know if this individual
has some bad habits
that you strongly don't
want in your operation
execuflight did give
them CRM training
basically cockpit resource
management training is
teaching pilots
to work as a team
and using all the
available tools together
so they are operating as one
but when the investigators examine
the airline CRM training program
they are underwhelmed
not much of a training manual
the regulations required execuflight to
have cockpit resource management training
and it did
what we found was their
training was insufficient
and their evaluation of
the crew was not proper
this was an accident
waiting to happen
the NTSB concludes
that the probable
cause of the crash
was the crew's
mismanagement of their approach
deviation from
operating procedures
and execuflight's lax
hiring and training practices
we determine that
execuflight did not
enforce and didn't
make sure that the pilots were
following standard operating procedures
in their report, the NTSB
makes several recommendations
for private operators
like execuflight
they include better training for
pilots on non precision approaches
like the one into Akron
and the installation
of flight data recorders
that could also be used to
monitor the progress of their flights
the NTSB recommendations
really comes down to
what kind of scrutiny
you have on your pilots
do you know what's
going on in a cockpit?
do you know what
your pilots are doing?
standard operating procedures
these are incredibly important
it's like we say
airspeed is life, well
adherence the standard
operating procedures is life
and of we begin to
remove the structure
you go back in time and you
lose the benefit of all the lessons
that we have paid so nearly
for in the past by crashes