on an early morning
take off in Kentucky
100 knots
check
two experienced pilots struggled to
get their regional get off the ground
rotate
and crashed into a nearby field
this was a catastrophic accident
investigators try to piece
together what went wrong
get those to Washington
and end up with more
questions than answers
what the heck could stop there?
only by retracing the taxi route
all the cues are right there
plane's site
and listening to the
cockpit discussions
that's weird
with no light
yeah
do investigators
discover the grim truth?
they finally realize
something is wrong
but it's already too late
it's almost 6 in the morning
in Lexington Kentucky
the pilots of Comair Flight 5191
prepare for their
preflight briefing
in command is
captain Jeffrey Clay
an experience pilot with
more than 4700 flying hours
man I was feeling I could eat a little
more when I get a seat belt like this
first officer James Polehinke
is a also a seasoned pilot
with more than 6500 flying hours
you up for flying this leg?
yeah I'll take us to Atlanta
both the captain and the first
officer were very highly regarded
an outstanding
professional reputation
and individuals that had flown with
them had nothing but high marks and
and bring very favorable
comments as far as their qualities
the crew is flying a
Bombardier CRJ100
a small twin engine jet designed
for short commuter flights
Shawn Pruchnicki flew that
aircraft for comair for 10 years
the CRJ is an aircraft
that's built for short haul flights
for example the Lexington to
Atlanta less than an hour type flight
it's really what these
planes are designed to do
ladies and gentleman
we'd like to take this time
to welcome you on board
Comair Flight 5191 direct to Atlanta
we'll try to keep this
as quite as possible
hopefully you catch a
nap on the way there
so pleasure having
you on board today
they are 47 passengers and
one flight attendant on today's flight
the pilots begin their briefing
take off procedures off of
he said what airline?
24?
it's 22
something that we
do prior to take off is
we do a flight briefing
between the two members
primer reason we do this is
to make sure that everyone has
the same amount of information
and knowledge to
safely depart the airport
all right
22 to short taxi
any question?
no questions, before starting
you're leisure
in the cabin passengers
prepare for take off
seat belt
please
today they're bound
for Atlanta Georgia
just a 67 minute flight
straight south from
Lexington Blue Grass Airport
comair 191 is ready to taxi
comair 191
taxi to runway 22
altimeter 3000
winds are 200 at 8
3000 and taxi to 22
comair 191
Lexington air traffic controller
clears flight 5191 to the runway
and then turns his
attention to another plane
eagle flight
runway 22
clear for take off
with few planes
at this small airport
in near perfect weather
this flight is far from challenging
for this seasoned pilots
during the taxi
the captain is responsible
primary for navigating the
aircraft on the airport surface
the first officer is running
numerous checklist
in verifying that the
aircraft is safe for departure
folks, we're gonna be
underway momentarily
so sit back
relax and enjoy the flight
we're all ready captain
thank you
cabin report received
before take off checks complete
ready?
all set
and sure leisure comair 121
ready to go
comair 191
Lexington tower
runway heading
clear for take off
clear for take off 191
lights set
take off config it's okay
all yours
captain Clay hands control of aircraft
to first officer Polehinke for take off
my brakes
my controls
set thrust please
thrust set
that's weird
with no lights
100 knots
checks
something's not right
rotate
5191 prepares to lift off
damn it
comair flight 5191
hurtles into a field
less than a half of a
mile from the runway
this is Lexington
alert 3
west side of the runway
to the comair
regional jet taking off
we knew something was wrong
we never get an alert 3
we never get one
public safety officer Pete
Maupin rushes to the scene
it's hot
I mean it's very hot
there were explosives
can we save anybody?
that was what I was
thinking when I saw this
fall apart
49 people are dead after the
tragic take off of comair flight 5191
first officer Polehinke
is the only survivor
first responders, quick actions
were the reason that first officer
Polehinke survived this accident
he was so dramatically
injured that they recognized
that time was of the essence
and transported him to the
hospital out of waiting for ambulance
he back me for saving his life
I told him that was my job
but I was glad
the question NTSB
investigators now need to answer
is why comair flight 5191
couldn't get up the ground?
as soon as the fires are put
out and the crash site is safe
NTSB investigators
begin looking for clues
to discover why comair
flight 5191 crashed
less than a half a mile from
Lexington Blue Grass Airport
make sure every
scrap is documented
we need a clear picture the
path this plane took before impact
lead investigator Joe Sedor is among
the first who arrived at the crash site
in this case it was
quite interesting because
initially we didn't have much
an airplane crashed
we didn't know it was on the airport
off the airport
we actually started at the final
resting place for the wreckage
and then we walk
back towards the airport
first impact point is there
and the plane hit
those trees over there
is impact marks more
than 20 feet up those trunks
we were looking at the
trajectory of the airplane
clearly looked like it took off
just about end of the runway
and immediately started contacting
trees into the wreckage site
the wreckage path
tells investigators that the plane
was struggling to get off the grounds
was it engine trouble?
or something else
looks like it took
off from runway 26
hang on
26 wasn't in use last night
Lexington airport
has two runways
runway 26
and runway 22
according to flight plan there were
supposed to take off from runway 22
so how the heck did
they end up over here?
investigators are surprised
to discover that flight 5191
took off from the wrong runway
well at that point done because we
knew that it was a wrong runway take off
the question is why?
and it's wondered
that doesn’t make sense
did they misunderstand
their instructions?
or deliberately change their plan
to take off from a different runway
it's gotta be something on that CVR
about why they were on runway 26
get those to Washington
the flight recorder and
the cockpit voice recorder
were retrieved and flown
back here to Washington DC
but being on the wrong runway
doesn't explain why the plane
barely made it off the ground
let's take a closer
look at those engines
when the engines are examined
what the investigator
is looking for is damage
the more damage if there is and
the type of damage tells us that
if it was turning at high speed
or turning at lower speed
they were seining all right
evidence of deformed blades suggests
the engines were running on impact
all the indications were that both
engines were operating at high power
when the breakup
sequence started
there is no problem
with the engines
something else must have
kept them from getting airborne
maybe they were too heavy
with engine failure ruled out
the team wonders if the plane was
loaded with too much weight to take off
there is a certain maximum weight
that the aircraft can take off safely with
so what we do is
we calculate the load that's on
the aircraft at the time of the accident
here it is
CRJ's max take off weight
is 50,178 pounds
the load manifested
the plane weight
49,087 pounds on that day
it's close but it's
within their limit
the aircraft wasn't
too heavy to take off
and that aircraft on that day
with that weight how much runway
would be needed to take off safely?
using the actual
weight of the aircraft
and the CRJ 100 specifications
investigators calculate how much
runway the plane needed to lift off
the weight of the aircraft
affects how fast they have
to be going to be able to lift off
and that is a
directly correlated to
how much runway it takes to
be able to achieve that speed
3744 feet
and runway 26 is
3501 feet
investigators reach an
astonishing conclusion
runway 26 is 243 feet short
they ran out of runway
they now understand why
the plane couldn't get airborne
but they're still mystified
why didn't flight 5191 take
off from the longer runway?
hate to say this but you're not gonna get
any answers from the first officer either
his injures are very severe
the first officer is medically
unfit to be interviewed
it's a big lost to
the investigation
it can be frustrating
when you're not able to speak with
people you'd like to speak with, but
as investigators we need to
work with the data that we have
investigators look for
other clues that might reveal
why flight 5191 ended up on the
runway they were not clear to use
they
left the gate here
they taxi along here
they're supposed to
leave the runway 22 here
but they end up
here
the question is why?
so when we're looking
and trying to understand
why this flight crew thought
they are on runway 22
we looked at anything
that was different
anything that the flight crew
may have misunderstood
with regard to both
the airport and the charts
or any of their training
hey look at this
our guys got some
shuts to the runway
hey check this out
taxi way to runway 22
is blocked up by construction
there were numerous
construction projects
that were in place with the Lexington
airport the day of the accident
okay sure
was that in the chart?
normally when a
taxi way is closed
pilots received an interim
airport chart with an alternate route
no nothing on the chart
investigators are
amazed to learn
that the crew's airport chart only
showed the taxi route before construction
not the updated taxi route
it's a surprise to see if
the airport construction
had not been updated in the
charts that the flight crew had
it's a disturbing find
could out of date taxi charts have misled
the pilots into taking off from a runway
that was too short
for their plane?
so they get down there
they find their taxi way is blocked
they don't have anything to
tell them how to get to runway 22
that could trick you up
but something doesn't add up
comair flight 5191
wasn't the only plane
departing Lexington that morning
other planes left before them and
none of them ended up on runway 26
eagle flight runway 22
clear for take off
the other two flights
took off prior to 5191
and receive the same information
that the flight from 5191 received
and did not have any difficulties
and navigating to the runway
the fact that two other aircraft were
able to depart successfully that morning
cause us to look deeper
maybe there is something
on the security footage
investigators turn their
attention to CCTV footage
in the hopes that it will explain why
comair 5191 took off from the wrong runway
we were able to retrieve security footage
from cameras on the parking garage
that showed our aircraft
taxing out that morning
all right
let's see what they
were actually up to
investigators quickly confirmed
how straight forward the taxi route was
taxi short
there is no other aircraft inside
our assessment based on
examination of surveillance video showed
that it was a nominal taxi
the taxi route from
the ramp to runway 22
was straight forward and only
required one runway crossing 26
wait stop right there
it looks like they stop then they
hold short line for the runway 26
before take off plane stopped
or hold short of the runway
until they're clear to
proceed by air traffic control
they were on their way to runway 22
why the heck would they stopped there?
investigators are
startled by the discovery
we noticed at that time that the
aircraft had stopped prior to runway 26
for over 50 seconds
this is unusual because there is
no real reason for them to stop there
we need to see the taxi route
all right
were there clues telling the
pilots they were in the wrong place
one of our main
questions when we realized
that they stopped 50 seconds at
the hold short-line for runway 26 was
what could they
have been seeing?
to better understand why
the pilots of comair flight 5191
stopped at the hold short
line for the wrong runway
all right
let's get started
investigators
retrace their taxi route
we want to understand what
the flight crew was seeing
in order to do that we had
to do a taxi demonstration
to identify all the signage
the markings and the cues
available to the flight crew
here on the left
there is a sign for runway 26
straight ahead
I can see the whole
short line for runway 26
I mean it's clear as day
things that we were looking for
during that taxi demo were things like
the quality of the
markings on the taxi way
the signage
whether was illuminated or not
the taxi line splits three ways
investigators can see what
the pilots would have seen
from the whole
short line for runway 26
the line on the left
goes to runway 26
the line in the middle
is the route to runway 22
the line on the right is
runway 20’s old taxi route
blocked by barricades
I can clearly see
the signs telling us
that there we're at the
hold short line for runway 26
I mean it's hard to miss that
investigators discover
that the crew had clear cues
that they were at hold
short line for runway 26
not 22
the question remains how
did they miss those cues?
okay let's go to 26
the test plane follows the
line on the left to runway 26
okay see
that's where they should
have taken the taxiway
and stopped the whole
short line for runway 22
investigators are
surprised to learn
that even as flight 5191
was turning onto runway 26
the crew had a
clear view of the sign
pointing to the runway
they were meant to be on
there were no features in the environment
in terms of the signs, marking, or lighting
that showed they
were on runway 22
all the cues are right there
plane site
Joe Sedor then uncovers
one more disturbing fact
when we taxied from the taxiway
onto and turned onto runway 26
all of the lights on runway 26 were
out and there is no lights in the distance
as an experienced pilot
I look at that and say
why did this flight crew
take off from this runway?
we need to know what
was going on in that cockpit
that is weird with no lights
yeah
the cockpit voice recorder from comair
flight 5991 is finally ready to be reviewed
okay let's hear what we've got
it maybe the only
hope of explaining
why the crew ended up
on an out of service runway
instead of the one
they were clear to use
in this type of human
factor's accident
it's very difficult because we have to try
to determine what the pilots were thinking
the main tools that we use
in order to determine that
is the cockpit voice recorder
the CVR was very important in understanding
what the flight crew was talking about
and what they were doing
during the taxi and the take off
you up for flying this leg?
I'll take us to Atlanta
okay so the first officer is going to fly
that's standard stuff
the flight crew were conducting
themselves in a professional manner
ground briefing, comair standard,
run the checklist at your leisure
keep me out of trouble
I'll do the same thing for you
I'll do the same
whenever you're ready
okay here comes the taxi brief
takeoff procedure off
said what runway? 24
it's 22
the ILS is out on 22
the other night, the runway identifier
lights were out all over the place
all right
22 is short taxi
any questions?
no question before
starting at your leisure
something in the briefing
surprises investigators
stop it right there
is that not a short brief to you?
they discover that the crew used an
abbreviated version of the taxi brief
called comair standard
pull up the comair
standard taxi route
the is no mention of
of crossing runways
or stopping to call ATC if
they're unsure where they are
investigators are baffled to discover
that even the shortened taxi brief
with 8 checklist items
including a very crucial one
wasn't followed
they never brief on the
runway they had to cross
to get to runway 22
the crew's abbreviated
briefing that morning
was a deviation from standard
operating procedure that we identified
had the crew done
a full taxi briefing
they would have discussed the need
to cross runway 26 on the way to 22
they missed an opportunity
to review the airport diagram
and determine that they
need to cross runway 26
an intervening runway
before they reach runway 22
let's see their taxi checklist
flight controls
check left and the right trims
engage 07.2
radar terrain displaced
taxi checklist completed
finish up the before takeoff
checklist at your leisure
one other thing on the CVR we
heard was the captain using the term
at your leisure
it was used so many
time on the CVR
what this told us is that
this flight crew was relaxed
maybe they were a
little bit too relaxed
yeah I know 3 guys at Kennedy
actually two guys
one went but he did
get through the same
oh really
then a first officer from Cincinnati
he got through the second part and
that's as far as they got
can you stop it right there
investigators cannot
believe what they're hearing
what the heck is
he talking about?
instead of focusing
on their checklist
the crew of 5191 were having a casual
conversation during a critical moment
it's a major breach of what's
called the sterile cockpit rule
the sterile cockpit rule requires
that pilots were refrain from
non-operational conversation
during significant portions of flight
one of the key reasons
for the sterile cockpit rules is
that non pertinent
conversation can be distracting
that's as far as they got
and then he actually
got off the position
did he take it? yeah he took it
oh okay
the captain should be shutting his
conversation down not encouraging it
although the first officer
started the conversation
the captain is responsible
for assuring that
sterile cockpit rules and
enforced and distractions
do not enter the cockpit that
could affect the safety of flight
after 40 seconds of
casual conversation
second engine started
anti ice probes
windshield low
investigators hear the pilots
turned to their take off checklist
now they finally
get back to the jobs
we're surprised by that
that non pertinent conversation
was in a critical area when the flight
crew is making their taxi out to the runway
where the flight crew needs to
be 100 percent flying the aircraft
could that period of inattention
hold a key to this
tragic accident?
okay let's see what
we've got so far
investigators wonder if
a causal conversation is
at the heart of the crash
of Comair Flight 5191
we skipped out of their briefing
and would have told them
they needed to cross 26
to get to 22
then for almost a minute
they violate the
sterile cockpit rule
let's see what happens
when they get here
investigators hope the
crew will give some indication
why they stopped at the
hold shortline for runway 26
thrust reverses are armed
auto cross flow is manual
ignition is off
altimeters are 3000
cross the board
cross checked
I'll check in with the cabin
that's it
it was surprising to us that
there was no conversation
about their location
on the airfield
or confusion about it
while they were holding
short on runway 26
we know they were distracted
and when they
stop their chit chat
they don't seem to recognize
know or check where they are
we got no information base on
the conversation of the flight crew
while they're holding short
that they were disoriented
no indications at all
investigators are amazed
by what they hear next
at your leisure comair 121
ready to go
comair 191
Lexington tower
fly runway heading
clear for take off
hold there
so they're completely relaxed
when they asked for clearance
in fact so relaxed
that they're distracted
that the first officer uses
the wrong flight number
investigators
realized the grim truth
these guys actually thought
they were lined up for runway 22
the fact that they
stopped at runway 26
and subsequently
called for take off
indicates that they lost awareness
that they had not crossed runway 26
they turn onto runway 26
then what
keep going
final checks completed
all yours James
first officer takes the controls
so he's looking at
probably for the first time
at this time the captain
taxied the aircraft
out onto the runway
transport controls
to the first officer
so before this
time the first officer
was heads down in the cockpit
my breaks
my controls
when the first officer
looked out he saw a runway
but he may not have perceived
that it was a narrower runway than
runway 22
they're looking down runway 26
why don't they see the
sign for 22 off to the right?
neither pilot cross checked their location
at the time that they took for runway
set thrust point
thrust set
that is weird with no lights
yeah
hold on
runway 26 is not
in use, so it's not lit
they see the lights
for 22 until they cross it
they're looking down
pitched dark runway
and it doesn't faze them
investigators wonder if the
pilots were confused about
what the runway
should have looked like
when they began the
take off roll on runway 26
they had no centerline lights
or edge lights on this runway
however based on the first officer's
previous experience the night before
he did not expect to see lights
the ILS is out on 22
other night, the runway identifier
lights were out all over the place
so it would not necessarily have
been on an unusual site picture
such decision making based
on a person mistaken assessment
is called confirmation bias
confirmation bias is where the flight
crew expects something to be there
even though it might
not actually to be there
he notice there is no
lights on the runway
but he just accepted the fact
what happened next?
100 knots
checks
the pilots now see they're
almost out of runway
rotate
and don't have the
required speed to get airborne
wow
damn it
that's it
they finally realize something
is wrong and it's too late
based on our calculation
the crew needed to recognize
that they were on
the wrong runway
and successfully reject the take off
about 20 seconds into the take off roll
however their recognition
did not occur until much later
when the captain called
rotate at the lower speed
than it was required
investigators have
unraveled the mystery
of what happened inside
the cockpit of flight 5191
they start out by
skipping the full briefing
then after long
discussion about the airline
they lose sight
about where they are
they stop at the wrong place
and they completely miss all the
signage that they are at the wrong runway
by the time they figure
out the mistake, it's too late
these guys are going
through the motions
when they should have
been of full attention
the crew's failure to use
available cues and aids
to identify and check
the plane's location
let to the tragedy of
comair flight 5191
but the team still has
one unanswered question
why didn't the controller tell them
they were at the wrong runway?
investigators wonder if the air
traffic controller of comair flight 5191
could have picked
up the crew's error
and prevented the accident
happy to answer any questions
with the air traffic controller
we were trying to understand
did the controller have an opportunity to
see this airplane take the wrong runway?
and prevent the accident
605 they asked for
take off clearance
runway 22 was
free so I gave comair
clearance for take off
at your leisure comair 121
ready to go
comair 191
Lexington tower
fly runway heading
clear for take off
runway heading
clear for take off 191
and what did you do next?
I saw the plane proceed
towards runway 26
and then scanned runway 22 to
make sure there were no vehicles on it
did you watch
the flight take off?
not if I have other jobs to do
investigators make
one final discovery
and then I turned over
here to cut my flight strips
and why would you start
cutting your flight strips then?
I wasn't busy
it only takes a few minutes
and there was no reason to
think that they have any problems
17 years
I've never seen a plane that
size try to take off from runway 26
the controller was not
watching the airplane
and assumed that the airplane was
going to take off on the correct runway
because this is
such a simple airport
and because there
was no other traffic
on the airport at the
time of the accident
and if you hadn't turned away
would have notice that they
were on the wrong place?
I might have
FAA regulations do not require
controllers to monitor every take off
but if the controller had been watching the
runway instead of counting flight strips
he might have notice
flight 5191's mistake
he was not actually required
nor or any any controllers required
to actually watch an
aircraft during its take off roll
had they have been
required to do that
this would have given an opportunity
to have the take off aborted
the NTSB concludes that
several factors led the pilots
to lose track of their position
on their way to the runway
contributing to that was the flight
crew's failure to maintain sterile cockpit
and have a non
pertinent conversation
prior to take off
this crash happened because of a
period of distraction
during what was perceived
as a relatively simple taxi
and it illustrates
the perils of distraction
in that it can take you off task
it can cause you
to lose awareness
and in this case both crew
members lost awareness
of where they were
on that airport surface
and made a mistake
that was extremely consequential
among the NTSB's recommendations
is a basic technological change
to prevent pilots from getting lost
the CRJ100 at the time
had sophisticated avionics
but it lacked a simple GPS system
available in cars of the same era
install moving map GPS displays
in CRJ100 cockpits
the NTSB also makes
recommendations for flight crews
require pilots to check that
they are at the assigned runway
before crossing
the hold short line
first officer James Polehinke
the lone survivor
of comair flight 5191
suffered severe injuries
including the
lost of his left leg
he never return to
commercial aviation
this was a catastrophic accident
it affected scores
and scores of lives
but the legacy of this accident
are the safety changes that
have been made to prevent
this type of accident from
happening in the future
this accident shows that there
are threats in any environment
no matter how docile they seem
in that flight crews
have to be aware and
have to be looking for all
the threats at all the time