pull over
a Boeing 727 spirals out
of control over Michigan
you're watching the world
spinning outside the window
this would be sheer start terror
speed 20
come on
no no no
investigators track
down pieces of debris
slat number 7
broken in 2
and interview fellow pilots
off the record
they even risked their own lives
okay, test number 9
to find out what caused TWA
flight 841's uncontrollable plunge
do you feel that?
it was insane
my hands are still shaking
44 year old captain
Harvey "Hoot" Gibson
has just returned from the
most harrowing flight of his life
tell me what happened
a representative from the federal
aviation administration takes his statement
we cruise over Michigan
that sure is a strong headwind
captain Gibson is a
trained stunt pilot
who has a clean 16 year record
with Trans World Airlines
sure thing
hoot
first officer Scott Kennedy has
been flying with TWA for 13 years
we're good to go
any time you want to
flight engineer Gary
Banks is an air force veteran
who is being with TWA
for the last 10 years
the crew of flight 841 had just the right
kind of experience you would want for a
727 crew
center
TWA 841
we'd like to try
flight level 390
roger TWA 841
climb and maintain flight level 390
they were blocking a 100
knots of wind on their nose
so he was looking for
better winds up higher
the higher you go
you essentially go faster
through the thinner air
and that will hopefully get
you a better ground speed
I take that off your hands
27 year old mark moscicki
is today's lead flight attendant
he and 3 other attendants look
after the 82 passengers on board
it was an evening flight
was leaving JFK
it was the first time I've
flown with this cockpit crew
everything was absolutely smooth
they're flying the narrow
body Boeing 727 aircraft
the 727 was massively overbuilt
it was very sturdy airplane
it's like driving sport
car or fighter plane
it was very light
on the controls
it had that feeling that you could
just put it where ever you want
after a 45 minute
delay in New York
the flight to Minneapolis
will take about 3.5 hours
they programmed 39,000 feet
they've got right up there
and sure enough they
were gaining speed
they were probably gonna cut 10
to 15 minutes off there in route time
I'll do another
ground speed check
our settings adjusted
everything looks good
after meal service, moscicki
takes a moment to eat his own meal
I sat in my jump seat
very shortly however
there was very rupt buffering
of the aircraft
it wasn't turbulence
what the heck?
the captain notice
something was strange
the wing had started to drop and the
auto pilot was compensating for that
I've got control
disengaging the auto pilot was
the right thing to do at that time
that's the first thing you think of
something is wrong with the auto pilot
what's going on?
without any warning, the
plane banks hard to the right
airspeed 240
come on
but if the plane
still doesn't respond
then you think the
same about your plane
the plane just
kept rolling right
and started rattling
really hard too
I would be trying the rudder
and if that's not doing the job
I start trying to
flight with the engines
but 727, the engines are all
clustered together in the back
that probably wouldn't
help you that much
so this would be
sheer stark terror
shutting the throttles
the captain tries to slow
the plane to regain control
but the aircraft
isn't responding
get them up
desperate to slow the plane,
Gibson deploys the speed brakes
speed brakes are flight control surfaces
that increase drag and improve roll control
you're gonna put those
out to try slow yourself down
because really bad things are gonna start
happening soon if you keep accelerating
come on
but deploying the speed
brakes proved useless
I've got up from my jump seat
to see if perhaps
the engine was on fire
and I never made it
high above Saginaw Michigan
the Boeing 727 drops
into an uncontrolled dive
and spins upside down
something was extremely wrong
there seem to be no
control over airplane
people were just
absolutely terrified
I sincerely didn't think that we
had wings left on the airplane
TWA 841
it's center
center
Jesus
something is seriously wrong
you would have your
hands full of airplane
you're watching the world
spinning outside the window
you're being pressed by g-forces
it also must have been insanely noisy
it would be very difficult
trying troubleshoot the problem
TWA 841
do you read me?
the controllers watch helplessly as
TWA 841 plummets towards the ground
once the nose comes
down on an airliner
they want to pick up speed and
hurry if he pointed at the ground
I kept clenching my
jaws and biting my teeth
to keep blood in my head
the g-forces were so extreme
I thought that I was
going passed out
the blood is literally being
drained out of your head
and you will first
lose your vision,
that's called graying out
and then the next
thing is you black out
which is where you
lose consciousness
because your heart just
can't pump the blood
up to your brain against
all that force of gravity
the speed is 220
I can't
TWA 841 spiraling towards the
earth at the rate of 540 feet per second
to feel 6 g
the only people that would
experience that would be military pilots
you're gonna feel an incredible
weight on every part of you
and whatever
position your body is in
your head
your arms
they're gonna stay that way
so you're not gonna
be able to move
I could see ground lights
and I knew that we were
approaching the ground very quickly
that point you go
from abject terror
into almost acceptance
no no no
come on baby
pull up
we were falling so fast
captain Hoot Gibson
recounts his recent nightmare
piloting TWA flight
841 over Michigan
air speed is 390
but Gibson isn't giving up
come on baby
pull up
he has an idea
put the gear down
if nothing else
will slow you down
the gear will slow you down
and hopefully the
plane's hold together
that's it
that's it baby
what's saved them was
putting the gear down
because otherwise they would
have been big smoking crater
a matter of seconds
we're pitching up
30 degrees
you know suddenly
we were climbing
it was like coming out of
the bottom of a roller coaster
you would feel like
you are being crushed
the average person
would feel like they
weight 900 pounds
Scott give me the altitude
Gary, pitch and airspeed
5200 feet, Jesus
which way is up?
moon
it's pitch-black and you've
just been spiraling
down towards the earth
and you're probably disoriented
he sees the moon and that's up
you can sort the rest out later
but get away from the ground
TWA 841 has come
within seconds of impact
and now climbs back
towards the night sky
airspeed is 160
though the pilots are flying
again they're not out of danger
the steep climb is
physically demanding
and the crew struggles
to maintain focus
10,500
11,000
that's it
that's it hoot
leveling 110
this is your captain speaking
as you've noticed
we've had a little
bit of problem
but everything seems
to be under control
we lost system A hydraulics
fluid is down
pressure is down
as the crew recovers
from the terrifying incident
they assess
damage to the aircraft
a deafening rattle makes
the tense situation worse
okay
I'm gonna fly the airplane
you guys for running
the emergencies
he had them diagnose the problem
while he flew the airplane
knowing that you
can't do both effectively
turn (pop) emergency switches
to depressurize and check quantity
the fluid is zero
it’s all gone
with the damage to hydraulic
system the aircraft is severely impaired
I think we gotta land
Detroit is our best option
okay
we're 60 miles out
when they decided to divert
they selected Detroit
with reasonable weather
long runways
it's a developed airport
with crash fire rescue
center
go ahead
TWA 841
okay listen
we had a problem
we lost about 20,000 feet
we need vectors to Detroit
45 miles for Detroit now
if you like to come left
heading 160
vectors to Detroit
okay
turn left 160
TWA 841
remove your glasses, earrings
and anything else that might be sharp
place anything soft in your
lap to cushion the impact
30 miles from the airport
flight attendance prepare the
cabin for an emergency landing
passengers were amazingly
quite I mean they looked at us
for a complete direction
15 miles to Detroit now
nice and easy
I mean flaps 15
unaware of the
extent of the damage
Gibson tests the
aircraft's control ability
flaps 15
woo woo woo
retract the flaps
extending the flaps causes
the plane to roll sharply to the left
you're going to land
without flaps at this point
which means you're
going to go very fast
much faster than you
would ever land this airplane
only fast
there is no other way
this is our only approach
with ruptured hydraulic
and a compromised plane
the pilots of TWA 841 have only
one shot landing at Detroit airport
landing check is complete
coming through 200 feet
I was pretty convinced that we'd
probably scrapping down the runway
lots of sparks and flames
race
220 knots in this case
just insane rate of
speed for landing
reverse thrust
come on
stop
escort these
passengers off the plane
he's just put this badly
damaged airplane down
at about 90 knots faster
than a normal landing speed
this guys is good
he's really good
hoot
it's unbelievable
what the heck went so
wrong with that plane?
I have a faintest idea
investigators from the national
transportation safety board
arrived in Detroit
to determine what went
wrong with TWA flight 841
they look in good shape
let's get the data on these
the flight data recorder
and cockpit voice recorder
are removed from the
aircraft and sent for analysis
let's check that out
slat number 7 is missing
slats and flats are control surfaces on
the leading and trailing edges of the wing
they are always
extended in tandem
both devices increase lift at low
speed during take off and landing
it's pretty banged up
investigators wonder
why the slat came off
hydraulic lines are ruptured too
looks like the actuator
for the slat is damaged
the actuator is part of a
mechanism that pushes a piston
to unlock the slat
allowing it to either
deploy or retract
let's get the actuator off the wing
so we can get a better look at it
one of the interesting remnants of this
inspections was the number 7 slat actuator
look at how it's broken
and scrape marks inside either
investigators uncover
an important clue
it's like came off
in extended position
number 7 slat
actuator had broken
the piston inside it was gone
and they could recognize from
looking at the opening of the fracture
that the piston had been
in the deployed position
a slat should never
deploy at cruising speed
maybe the slat
extended by accident
only way to know for sure
test hydraulic system
for the slat to have been
deployed uncommanded
required the failure of the hydraulic
system and failure of the locking mechanism
I'll start with flaps 2
flaps 15
looks good
next flaps 20
flaps 20
investigators run through
every flap setting possible
alright
let's wrap it up
everything's working fine
the functional test demonstrated
that the hydraulic system worked
it did not cause an
uncommanded slat deployment
this what we've got from Boeing
did the locking mechanism
on the 727's wing somehow fail?
releasing the slat?
for a slat to unlock accidentally
the pin inside the actuator must
be subjected to more than 70 G force
70 G
there's no way the locking mechanism
experience that level of stress
a 70 G pull through by an
aircraft just doesn't happen
the investigators were faced with
the serious challenge of where to go next
take a look
investigators get a break when
debris from flight 841 is recovered
7 miles north of
Saginaw Michigan
slat number 7
broken in two
look at this
is the number 7 slat t-bolt
t-bolts are part of the
slat track assemblies
the number 7 slat t-bolt was
attach to the in-board side of the slat
which deploys and
retracts inside the wing
let's send this to the lab
they hope metallurgical
analysis will offer some clues
but an important
question remains
why did the slat extend?
there is only one other
way slat could extend
through pilot action
this was something that had been
probably commanded in the cockpit
and a it was
distressing to everybody
why would a pilot do something as dangerous
as extending the slats at cruising speed?
I can't find anything in the
cabin about slats and flaps
investigators review
the crew's statements
they look for any mention that flaps
and slats were deployed mid flight
there is nothing from
other crew members either
I have an idea
thanks for meeting with me
the NTSB consult with pilot
to learn why they might
extend the flap or slat mid flight
off the record
flaps yes
slats no
flaps
investigators learned of an unauthorized
procedure used by some pilots
that could save fuel
and potentially time
I thought that was impossible
it is
if you pop the breaker
the procedure involves deploying
trailing edge flaps by two degrees
by pulling the circuit
breaker for slats
the flaps can be extended
while preventing the slats from
automatically deploying at the same time
just one of those things
every body knows about
but I've never heard
anyone ever admit to it
ready
instigators turn to the
cockpit voice recorder
for evidence that TWA 841's pilots
used the unauthorized procedure
escort these
passengers off the plane
hang on
did you start the
tape at the beginning?
yes, it's fully rewound
play again
just to make sure
escort these
passengers off the plane
plane is already on the ground
this can only point to one thing
the pilots erased the tape
the CVR contained no
information whatsoever
which was unfortunate
to say at least
we have to talk to Gibson
the team flies to California to
question captain Gibson in person
the safety board
conduct public hearings
they questioned the flight crew
I told and I thought it was
I said
I said the airplane
is gonna roll
and the
the captain admits to routinely erasing the
cockpit voice recorder after every flight
even though that isn't
step on any checklist
do you usually
erase the recorder?
I usually do
yes
it's just not credible
the after the crew had
been through what they did
where they came
within seconds of dying
that the captain wanna erase the
CVR as a matter of habit or routine
something is wrong here
captain Gibson's vague explanation
doesn't sit well with investigators
given what happened they suspect the flight
crew attempted the unsanctioned procedure
and then try to
cover up their actions
the only reason he would erase
the CVR was to keep information
from what he knew
would be an investigation
investigators believed
he had something to hide
maybe the FDR
data can tell us more
the team studies
TWA 841 flight data
to uncover any evidence that the
crew attempted a mid flight flap extension
wow three picks up speed
in 44 seconds the plane goes
from 229 knots to over 400 knots
it's incredible
look at this
close inspection of the data
gives the team an important clue
it's odd
are those oscillations?
yes in the G-trace
the G-trace shows
the level of G forces
being put on the plane
through out the flight
let's get this section blown up
the G-trace showed
the G-force of the airplane
were sort of increasing and
decreasing in a certain rhythmic pattern
very very unusual
oscillation start 39,000
feet just before the upset
it showed up one two three
13 seconds before the roll starts
looks like the plane was
really bouncing around
what the heck?
the data tells investigators that
the plane was moving erratically
for 13 seconds
before the first roll
here is thought
what if there is flap
and slat configuration
that could cause the vibration
let's find out
we've reached 39,000 feet
NTSB investigators take
an unprecedented risk
in an attempt to replicate the
oscillations recorded on TWA 841's G-trace
okay we've got more than a
dozen configurations and maneuvers
they run a test flight
to determine if these anomalies
resulted from a mid flight slat extension
conducting a flight test would
enable them to perform a maneuvers
that could be compared to what the
flight data recorder recorded on 841
229 knots
okay test number one
start by popping the breaker
okay slats are retracted
ready
flaps two
investigators try to match
the unusual oscillations
by testing different flaps
and slat configuration
test number two
flaps five
slats remain retracted
NTSB investigators
they'll do anything
they love that stuff
but I would have
been pretty scared
okay test number 9
flaps two slats two
three six and seven
flaps two
ready
do you feel that?
the flight test gives investigators
a tantalizing new lead
investigators are very
careful with flight test
to take the same aircraft to
record parameters carefully
all those things have
to factor into a flight test
in order to be a very
use to the investigation
here is the data from the test
scenario number
9 should match up
to confirm their results, investigators
compare the data with the FDR G-trace
it's perfect match
the flight has showed that
extending the flaps and slats
would create in the airplane
oscillations found on 841
so this was the test when
plane was shaking the most
this is the one
flaps two
slats two, three, six
and seven deployed
and are retracted
13 seconds later
they now have evidence
that TWA 841's crew
enact the unauthorized procedure
of pulling a slat circuit breaker
and then deploying
the flaps independently
but if that's what the crew did
why did the slats deploy?
and nearly bring down the plane
what the heck?
the slats are gonna shake because you're
going faster than the limiting airspeed
so I would expect it to get very
noisy and probably to buff it quite a bit
the test flight indicates the
slats circuit breaker was reset
which cause the slats to deploy
so we know the pilots popped the
breaker to in enact the procedure
but why they did
push it back in?
why did it take the crew 13
seconds to realize the problem?
and then retract the slats
investigators searched for answers
in all of the crew's statements
the lead flight
attendant remembered
that the flight engineer was out of
the cockpit before the vibrations began
let's see that
I'm gonna take a bathroom
break and get rid of these trays
I notice the cockpit door open
and I saw the flight engineer
coming out with the meal trays
I didn't want to think I was
shirking my responsibilities
I immediately met him
let me get these for you
thank you
I was kind of
surprise I've never had
a cockpit member actually
bring those trays back to the cabin
they waited for us
that's it
the flight engineer
was out of the cockpit
and out of the loop
investigators now have a theory
about what happened in the
cockpit on the night of April the 4th
flight engineer leaves the
cockpit to return the trays
with Banks out of the cockpit
Gibson launches
unauthorized procedure
the pilots deploy the flaps
what do you say we get to
Minneapolis a little quicker?
okay
how we're gonna do that?
watch this
flaps 2
fancy trick
heard about it but
I've never tried it
I could see, the junior crew
members saying he is the boss
let's do it
he says it's okay
it's okay
today that would be unthinkable
flight engineer returns and
notices a breaker is popped
what would any good
flight engineer do?
it pushes it back in
flight engineer banks returns and
notices the slat circuit breaker is pulled
he returns the breaker
to the normal position
unaware that the captain
had pulled it deliberately
to prevent the slats from
extending along with the flaps
exactly
normal operations resume
with flaps set for two
slats extend automatically
the cockpit begins to vibrate
what the heck?
what did you just do?
what do you mean?
just now
what did you just do?
breaker was popped up
push it back where it should be
Jesus
flaps up
Scott
we're going reverse
investigators have figured out
how TWA 841's crew might
have lost control of the Boeing 727
but they're still missing a
key piece of the puzzle
how come slat number 7 never
retracted along with the rest of the slats?
metallurgical report is in
investigators turn to results from
a metallurgical analysis of the t-bolt
from the number 7
slat on TWA flight 841
he found some shrink
preexisting metal fatigue
the team discovers
a fracture in the t-bolt
which would have caused the the
slat to sag on the inside when extended
the slat is kept in the
forward part of the wing
which gets all of the air forces
as the airplane progresses
at point 8 times speed of sound
that's gonna hit enormous air pressure
so all that air pressure
twists the sagged slat
slat number 7 can
no longer retract
under the extreme air
loads of a diving plane
it finally rips off
investigators finally understand
how TWA 841 went into a horrifying
dive above Saginaw Michigan
on the night of
the April 4th 1979
I'm gonna take a bathroom break
I'll grab these trays
unaware the captain was
conducting an unsanctioned procedure
disengaging the slats circuit
breaker to deploy only the flaps
the flight engineer
resets the popped breaker
what did you just do?
what do you mean?
pressure seconds passed as the captain
tries to figured out what's happened
meanwhile the aircraft
flies at a high speed
with its flaps and slats
extended perilously
the captain, passengers and
flight attendants start to the
feeling the vibration
of the airplane
caused by extension of the
slats and flaps at 39,000 feet
flaps up
flaps up Scot
I have control
the flaps and slats retract
except for the damaged
number 7 slat on the right wing
the number 7
slat if it's extended
you're gonna have more drag on
the right side than on the left wing
and that's gonna cause
that wing to descent
in other words it's gonna
put the airplane in a right turn
which is exactly what happened
come on
level up
but it's too late
little does the crew know
slat number 7 is still extended
keeping the plane in a roll
we're going reverse
TWA 841's flight crew is unable
to regain control of the aircraft
then in a stroke of
incredible good luck
slats number 7 rips off the plane
just 8,000 feet above the ground
the departure of the slat allowed the
return of control ability to the aircraft
with the wing symmetry
partially restored
and the landing gear deployed
it's just enough to slow the plane
and allowed the crew to regain control
and ultimately land the
battered 727 at Detroit
reverse thrust
the NTSB recommends
additional warnings to flight crews
about the dangers of high speed
deployment of flaps and slats
no punitive action is
taken against the crew
NTSB conclusions
are not a criminal thing
there not a blamed thing
they're trying to
prevent the next accident
by offering up a probable
cause that needs to be corrected
the pilots maintained
their innocents
claiming they did not deliberately
extend the flaps mid flight
captain Gibson took it to
his grave with him in 2015
the other two
guys aren't talking
following this accident
newer planes now come
equipped with flight computers
that prevent the deployment of
flaps and slats above certain altitudes
their speculation over
manipulation of controls
all that sort of thing
I've given a great deal of
thought over the past 41 years
and have come with the conclusion
that I'll never know what happened