Martin-air Flight 495
is minutes from
landing at Faro Portugal
the left engine was
making a rattling sound
all of a sudden we
heard an enormous bang
it was total destruction
56 people are dead
wow
look at this
investigators quickly find some
intriguing evidence of the crash site
there was a 2 inch deep cut
down the left side of the runway
this is very strange
the landing gear is
completely severed
if the aircraft were overweight
it could exceed the design limit
causing it to break and shear
these guys were 71000
pounds underweight
it wasn't too heavy
so what went wrong?
Martin-air Flight 495 is
nearing Portugal southern coast
approach
Martin-air Flight 495
good morning
the captain is 56 year
old H. W. van Staveren
75 DME
and out of 2404
level 70
a highly experienced
pilot and flight instructor
he's been with
Martin-air for 24 years
descending to level 70
the first officer is 31 year old
R. J. Clemenkowff
he's been flying with the
dutch company for 3 years
the youngest member of the team is
29 year old flight engineer Gary Glans
it was our last flight before
the Christmas holidays
everyone was in a good mood
my job as flight engineer
I'm responsible for
the aircraft in general
to make sure that everything
is operating properly
and overall trying to be a third
set of eyes for the flying pilots
the crew is flying a DC-10
a three engine wide body jet
in the 19th the DC-10
was one of the type of aircraft
most used for operators world wide
they're now less than
half of hour from landing
there are 13 crew members
and 327 passengers on board
most are residents
of the Netherlands
we were heading for
a vocation for weekend
the south of particle
of the Algarve
going to warmer
weather than Netherlands
and fleeing busy year we had
flight 495 is near the
end of 2.5 hour trip
from Amsterdam to
Portugal’s Faro airport
8 letter word for apple sources
orchards
I was traveling with evol
then my girlfriend
now my wife
I was lucky we could
sit at the front row
so I had a lot of leg
space to move around
oh
raining cats and dogs over there
as they descends
towards Faro airport
the pilots expect to
encounter some bad weather
we knew that we're going
to encounter rain-showers
thunderstorm or something that
you have to incredibly aware of
and ensure that they
don't effect your flight path
we do everything to avoid them
because they can produce
unexpected wind-changes
micro-burst
wind-shears
when a thunderstorm
moves over an active runway
the potential for wind shear
can make it too dangerous
for an aircraft to land
it wasn't something that we
felt was going to be a major issue
it's just something to monitor
if the weather worsens
they can divert north to Lisbon
but right now
it isn't necessary
Martin-air 461
runway visual
just minutes ahead another
Martin-air flight is landing at Faro
clear to land runway 11
the weather report indicates
that closest thunderstorm
is approximately 7 miles
to the west of the runway
knowing other airplanes
were flying that same approach
and nobody had reported
any significant issues
made us feel, we were
safe to continue onwards
495 is turning inbound
8 miles out
Martin-air 495 starts its
final approach to runway 11
the captain chose to
be the pilot monitoring
so he could oversee
the whole approach
and let the first officer
focus on just flying the aircraft
they descend
into the rain-clouds
confident the nearest
thunderstorm is still miles away
495, report at minimum
some runway insight
runway surface
conditions are flood
roger
with wet runway conditions
the crew configures the plane to
make what's called a positive landing
a positive touchdown
is when the main wheels
penetrate the water
layer on the runway
and improve the stopping
ability of the aircraft
gear down
with a wet runway
you do wanna touchdown
at positive firm rate
rather than trying to float
down for a softer touchdown
altimeters
set 3 times
4 miles from touchdown
the pilots make
their final checks
spoilers
armed
flaps
slats
flap zero
land
the left engine was
making quite a noise
and a rattling sound
every time it came full power
the plane was pitching
up and pitching down
so that was not reassuring
Martin-air 495
clear to land runway 11
the winds
15 knots
maximum 20
clear to land
flight 495 is less than a
minute from touching down
when the weather gets much worse
windshield went to ice
I can't see anything
I'm on it
wipers run fast
I was squeezing hands
firmer and firmer with evol
it was dead quite into plane
the plane is now just a
few seconds from landing
all of sudden
we heard an enormous bang
I fell out of the chair
then I saw the kitchen
doors into pieces
I was pretty sure we
were gonna be crush
flight 495 slides more than 350
feet off the runway at Faro airport
fire fighter and rescue
crews raced to the site
incredibly many of the
passengers and the flight crew
survived
there were people screaming
and crying and running
I didn't see my girlfriend
my first thought was oh, I
won't ever see evol again
those lucky enough to escape
search for loved ones
all of a sudden
I heard my name
then I saw in a distance
I saw evol downing there
we found each other
the injured are taken
to nearby hospitals
of the 340 people on board
54 passengers and 2 cabin
crew members are dead
making this one of Portugal’s worst
aviation disaster in more than a decade
a detail investigation
is now underway
into why this
plane hit the tarmac
and burst into flames
see if we can find
the flight recorders
got it
investigators from Portugal’s
general directorate of civil aviation
and from the American NTSB
arrived to inspect the
wreckage of Martin-air Flight 495
a DC-10 is a big aircraft
and there were pieces of it
all around
the right wing dislodge
from the rest of the aircraft
the wing structure is the
strongest structure on whole aircraft
so it had to have major amount
of stress to make that wing depart
amazing so many survived
the wreckage showed that the
aircraft was mostly destroyed by fire
80 to 90 percent of the people
died from the post impact fire
we were very concerned because if you
have something that suspect on an aircraft
that's been flown
all over the world
you wanna find it
that's great
nice work
let's hope we get
the data back quickly
investigators recover
the black boxes
containing the flight data
recorder and cockpit voice recorder
we needed to try to understand
what happened in the
final moments of the flight
in terms of speed
in terms of decisions
and also what happened
just before the touchdown
wow
look at this
a quarter of a mile from
the runway threshold
investigators discover the
aircraft's initial point of impact
there was a 2 inch deep cut
down the left side of the runway
it hit here
and veered off to the right
it's deep
it must come down hard
scratches we saw on
the runway revealed to us
that plane had landed very hard
so that's why the
marks were deep
maybe one of the engines failed
why did the plane land so hard?
was it a problem
with landing gear?
was it the a with speed?
or was it a problem with engine?
so we need to investigate that
is that all of them?
see what we've got
you always look at the engines
and there was substantial damage
we had to determine
was there some
kind of malfunction?
in the engine
investigators examine a key
component from the engines oil block
called a magnetic chip detector
a magnetic chip detector is
a small cylinder shape device
located inside the
engines oil filter
when an engine part wears
pieces or chips of broken metal adhere to a
magnet as they pass through the oil filter
it's known as making metal
wires the more metal on
this detector than expected
what part of the
engine is wearing?
the alloys are slightly different
they were at different rates
so they can tell by
laboratory analysis
what part of the
engine is wearing
and how rapidly
it's so clean
no chips
there is no evidence of metallic
debris inside the oil system
engines look fine
from the tests
conducted on the engines
it was concluded that the engines
did not contribute to the accident
at this point of investigation
we really didn't have a good
idea of what to look for next
we just had to keep going
this is very strange
they soon realize that
part of the right landing gear
is broken
the fact that part of the
right landing gear fractured
is very unusual
it's almost impossible
to make it fail
the forces necessary to
shear the landing gear like that
is massive
landing gear is
design and tested
to be able to withstand
the shock of 200 ton landing
it should never fracture
we had to confirm weather there
was something wrong with that gear
and the metal used
or maybe the maintenance on it
anything that would cause
the gear to fail in any way
and if it was a design problem
that's a big deal
the landing gear
failing on impact
would explain
this tragic accident
did we get this piece
of landing gear yet?
not yet
the landing gear collapsed
that was perhaps the most important
question that we had to deal with
while investigators wait for the
right landing gear of flight 495
they considered what could
have caused it to fracture
maybe the plane was too heavy
if the aircraft were over weight
and made a very firm touch down
then the loads imparted could exceed the
design limit causing it to break and shear
let's check the load manifest
the plane and a cargo
were roughly 218,000 pounds
it was 340 people on board
let's call it 53,000 pounds
and fuel
fuel was
20,000 pounds
so total weight on landing
was 353,000 pounds
give or take
max weight is 424,000 pounds
so
these guys
were 70,000 pounds underweight
it wasn't too heavy
the weight of the plane is not what
cause the landing gear to fail on touchdown
how about weight distribution?
you have to have the baggage
and the weight distributed properly
so the aircraft will fly the
way the pilots wanted to
by the book
it was properly loaded
properly stored
properly locked down
so it wasn't really an issue
with weight and balance ruled out
investigators are finally able to
test the right landing gear itself
service records are up to date
let's see if this steel
wasn't strong enough
another thing they
were looking for
is any preexistence
weaknesses on the steel
if this occurred in the
manufacturing process
it could affect the aircraft in
operations all around the world
they performed something
called a Vickers hardness test
Vickers hardness test is
an industry standard test
to evaluate the strength of a
particular component or piece of metal
a pyramid shaped diamond
is presses into the steel
leaving an indent or dimple
you can measure the depth
and the diameter of the dimple
and drive the metallurgical
strength of what you're testing
hardness value 658
so the steal was strong enough
investigators find no weakness in metal
used to make the plane's landing gear
it was determined there was
nothing wrong with the landing gear
whatever went wrong
it happened before the
airplane touch the runway
there are still no clues that's gonna help
explain why the landing gear fractured
the next step in the investigation was
to look at how the crew was operating
during the last
phase of the landing
this is interesting
official statements
made by the pilots
may shed some lights on the
final moments of Martin-air Flight 495
after the accident the
investigators came to all three of us
we had close sessions
the captain said
the flight was normal
the approach was normal
at 200 feet
we were on the center line
they should have been okay
but a few seconds later
the captain sees lightening
I suddenly felt a high sink rate
it all happened so fast
the aircraft actually
fell out of the sky
according to the captain
he saw lightening just seconds
before the aircraft began to lose altitude
rapidly
sink rate
the airplane fell like
god toke his hands
rounded into the ground
well
get this
the first officer state is
the weather was bad
and it was raining heavily
it was gusty and very turbulent
investigators wonder
if sudden wind changes
could have been contributed
to the crash of flight 495
the flight crew indicated
to the investigators
that they were in an
area of a lot of wind shear
a very dynamic weather condition
they were in turbulence
things were
changing very rapidly
did the pilot encounter
wind shear on final approach?
the team interviews
the air traffic controller
to better understand the conditions
the pilots were experiencing
can you tell me what
happened with flight 495?
everything seemed
perfectly normal
they were on
their final approach
and confirmed they
had a runway insight
then I clear them to land
Martin-air Flight 495
clear to land
runway 11
the wind
15 knots
max 20
the controls were quite confident
that they performed well the task
so they didn't find that
they did anything wrong
and they gave the
correct information
did they report any
issues with the plane?
no not at all
what about the weather?
there was rain
but
other planes were taking off
and landing without difficulty
Martin-air Flight 461
runway visual
just minutes before the crash
the controller was in contact
with an aircraft that took off
and another that landed
on the same runway
clear to land runway 11
neither flight reported extreme
weather over the runway
what about wind shear?
did the runway sensors
pick up anything?
faro airport is equipped
with two anemometers
that measure both
wind speed and direction
located on runway 29
and runway 11
if the anemometers detect a sudden
change in wind speed of 50 knots or greater
a wind shear warning
is automatically triggered
yes, they were
wind shear warnings
but they happened after the
aircraft had already crashed
if flight 495 was hit by an extreme gust
of wind before it crashed to the runway
the system would
have detected it
it didn't
there was a conflicting information
between what the crew said
and what the air
traffic controller reports
the crew statements don't match
the controllers account of the weather
thank you
the best thing to substantiate
what went on
was to take a really
deep look at what the
pilots were saying to
each other in the cockpit
let's start with
their approach brief
a week after the
crash of flight 495
data from the cockpit voice
recorder is ready to be reviewed
approach at 50 flaps
you can't approach in
minimum and field in sight
you look outside
wet runway
here the wipers
roger
as the crew prepares
for the approach
they become aware of
weather conditions at faro airport
we have to make
a positive landing
yes
okay
so
obviously they worried
about the runway conditions
in a positive landing
the aircraft touches down firmly
enough to penetrate the water
allowing the wheels to grip
the tarmac and slow the airplane
they wanna put it down hard to avoid
hydroplaning and running out of the runway
so what went wrong?
did the pilots somehow botch their
plan as they approach the runway?
clear
speed is a bit low
speed is low
low
okay
now speed is an issue
going on to a wet runway
the airspeed control
is very very important
so if you don't have too much
the airplane floats
but if you don't have too little
you end up impacting the runway quite hard
now
let's hear more
speed is okay
wind shield went into ice
I can't see anything
I'm on it
wipers run fast
as the plane gets
closer to the ground
the crew contends
with stormy conditions
a bit low
low
yes
throttles
why does the captain
yelled throttles?
for the captain to say this
at this moment
it raises the question
did they have an issue in
the final phase of landing?
let's look at the descent profile
if flight 495 flawing
on the right trajectory
the FDR will confirm it
here we are
the flight data recorder
gives objective clear data on
what the airplane was actually doing
was the airplane being
flown at the proper speed
the changes in the airspeed
were they indicative of a
severe weather condition?
and how were the pilots
responding to those changes
auto pilot is on
okay
so
they're descending
at the standard angle
and
they dipped here and recover
looks fine
at 200 feet which is about
20 seconds from landing
they were on a normal glide path
something happened between
that and touchdown
let's look at the airspeed data
so
looks like they're flying
steady at a 145 knots
until here
and airspeed jumps
and then drops all
the way to a 139 knots
investigators spot evidence
of airspeed fluctuations
during the last
minute of the flight
these fluctuations in airspeed
can be caused by wind gusts
as they got closer to landing
speed is a bit low
speed is low
speed is okay
was the captain concern
their speed wasn't fast enough
to compensate for
the strong headwind
these fluctuations seem to extremely
be caused by the 20 knots winds
reported by the controller
we need a full analysis of the
weather conditions on final approach
investigators ask the
Netherlands aerospace laboratory
to perform an
in depth weather study
to determine if the winds were
stronger than what was reported
to flight 495
what about auto throttle data
let's take a look
the fluctuations
and the auto throttle
correspond to the
airspeed fluctuations
if there is an
increase in airspeed
the auto throttle system will decrease
the power that is being commanded
the amount of thrust that
the engines are producing
if the airspeed falls low
the auto throttle system
will command increase thrust
to bring the airplane up to
the commanded airspeed
the auto throttles were indeed adjusting
for the dramatic changes in airspeed
well
look at that
102% power
investigators discover a very
high surge in engine power
3 quarters of a mile from
the runway threshold
the 102 percent command
by the auto throttle system
is a massive amount of power
it would be similar to the amount of
power that you would use for take off
too much power try to land with
and then here
power drops to 40%
the team discovers that the
power drops to a minimum
or engine idle
shortly thereafter
that's way too fast for the auto
throttle system to perform on its own
for the engines to decelerate
as quickly as they did
means that the levers were
moved faster than auto throttle
clutches can
physically move them
the only way the throttles
were moved that quick
would be if the
pilots was manually
adjusting them down to 40%
the auto throttle system
could make large corrections
and you have to make manual adjustments
if the throttle aren't keeping up
the first officer who
was the flying pilot
made a decision to override
the auto throttle system
and to pull the power way back
and in fact he pulled it all
the way back to flight idle
with so little power
they would have
dropped like a rock
according to the data
they would drop in a
thousand feet per minute
one thousand feet is well beyond
the operational limit of 600
feet per minute for the DC-10
as a consequence
of the reduce power
the plane hit the runway with
enough force to crack the landing gear
I've never experience
a landing as hard as that
I crushed my teeth and my mouth
it was hard beyond compare
investigators are left
with the key question
why would the crew
reduce power by so much?
so far from the runway threshold
this is the dutch weather record
investigators turn
to a weather analysis
prepared by the Netherlands
aerospace laboratory
to determine if the weather
affected the crew's actions
during their final approach
looks like the weather was
worse than what they thought
really
they had no less than
3 separate micro-bursts
in the last minute of flight
wow
okay
a micro-burst is a column of air
that descends from rain clouds
hits the ground
and fans out horizontally
it leads to significant
fluctuations in a plane's airspeed
when exactly?
the first one was it 700 feet
the second was
between 600 and 300 feet
and the last one was
between 200 and 110 feet
this last one was the worst
the wind speed jumped from
the reported 20 knots to 40 knots
wow
that would have triggered
a wind shear alert if
one was installed on the plane
then wind shifts from a
head-wind to a tail-wind
a sudden shift from
head-wind to tail-wind
is the worse type of
wind-shear because
a head-wind improves
your angle of attack
to ensure that
aircraft has good lift
when the wind switches
around to a tail-wind
you lose that
aerodynamic performance
if you don't have the thrust
to compensate for, right away
the aircraft will drop
let's compare this to
the auto throttle data
they lined up
for every micro-burst
there's a corresponding
increase in engine power
as the auto throttles try to
maintain the plane's speed
the auto throttle was
going up and down
it was trying very hard to fight
against those heavy down-bursts
the down-burst causes
a decrease in stability
which means turbulence
induce roll and pitch oscillations
would have been a bumpy ride
yeah
as they pass through
each micro-burst
the auto-throttles were
adjusting to the shifts in wind gusts
in the final moments
the approach was under
extreme weather conditions
there were a lot of
oscillations in speed
and that create a lot of stress
for the pilot flying at that time
the first officer likely would
have been overwhelmed
by the unexpected
changes in the weather
and knowing that he needed to make a
positive landing at the runway threshold
he sees the power
spike to a 102%
and takes a corrective action
in order to get the
plane on the ground
the first officer overrides the auto
throttle and reduces the power to idle
investigators now see just
how unfortunate his timing was
he cut the power at the exact same
time that last down-burst hit them
throttles
the captain tries to stop
the plane's uncontrolled descent
but he's too late
the captain should
have stepped in sooner
it should have recognize
something was not right
the captain really should have
taken over and landed himself
investigators suspect to the
sudden change in weather
combined with the pilot's
decision to cut the power too early
caused the aircraft to land with more
force than it was build to withstand
but one question
remains unanswered
if the winds were gusting
at 40 knots
half mile from the runway
wouldn't the winds at the runway be
gusting stronger than the 20 knots reported
by the controller
the team returns with their
findings to the air traffic controller
who oversaw
Martin-air Flight 495
you reported that the
winds on runway 11
were gusting up to 20 knots
that's correct
but that doesn't seem right
the dutch weather study confirmed
that there were 3 micro-burst
in the last minute of flight
with gust much higher than that
can you show me the
actual data from runway 11?
according to the raw data
the winds were actually
gusting at 35 knots
that sounds more like it
but
how could you have
under-reported the wind conditions?
we receive wind data every
30 seconds from this device
it must have been
switched to runway 29
instead of runway 11
investigators discover the the
air traffic controllers at Faro airport
had mistakenly selected the
wind reading on runway 29
instead of runway 11
airports are large places
that when you have anemometers
one opposite into the airport
you would expect that frequently
there would be a difference
in direction and velocity
of the reported wind
Martin-air 495
clear to land runway 11
the wind 150
15 knots maximum 20
clear to land
the controllers information
that they provided to the crew
was not representative of what
was actually occurring on the runway
wet runway
cross winds
that's completely
different picture
if the pilots were aware
they would have go around
investigators have figured out
what brought down flight 495
495 is turning in-bound
copy
report at minimum
so on runway insight
runway surface
conditions are flood
roger 495
gear down
with the runway at Faro
underwater
the crew plans a positive
touch-down at the runway threshold
clear to land
runway 11
the wind 150
15 knots maximum 20
but they're unaware of the
severity of the weather conditions
I can't see anything
I'm on it
they hit by a serious of
unexpected micro-bursts
causing the engine power
to shoot up automatically
concerned that the excess power
is too great for a positive landing
the first officer reduces the power to
idle just as the last micro-burst occurs
that makes them
vulnerable to strong winds
and the aircraft
dropped from 155
flight 495 slams to the ground
at the 1000 feet per minute
the danger of being slow and
encountering a down-draft is
you may not be
able to recover in time
and that can be a disastrous
they could have come
with the high speed
they could have performed
a missed approach
but the truth is the
flight crew try their best
this wasn't an accident
where we can see negligence
or cross-error
in the aftermath of their report
into the crash of Martin-air Flight 495
investigators make a
serious of recommendations
this accident was going to
be yet another example of
inappropriate
wind shear recovery
being applied in
a timely fashion
so this is additional
pilot training
this is wind shear detection
systems on airplanes
this is a more aggressive approach
to go around in unstable conditions
shortly after the crash
Faro airport modernize their
wind senses and displays
to comply with
international regulations
the critical information that
controllers provide to pilots
needs to be accurate
so these are some of the lessons that
the industry learned and implemented
following this accident
you know one of the things I was
told when I was coming a pilot is
never let your guard down
you can be having a
beautiful wonderful flight
and in the blink of eye
the things can change
it's just ingrained in my mind
always be ready
for the unexpected