after losing their
electric generators
okay
beacons off
the pilots of Air
Illinois Flight 710
shut down one system after another
to conserve their battery power
it was probably the most
sickening feelings for both of them
but efforts proved futile
all the passengers
and crew are killed
NTSB investigators examine the
plane's electrical components for clues
there's no short circuit
what about the batteries?
no signs of arching
the cockpit voice recording
raises more questions
are you using these lights here?
I'll get that one down
they're doing the right thing
turning things
off to reduce load
so what happened?
have you got a flash light?
Air Illinois Flight 710 departs from
capital airport in Springfield Illinois
gear up
32 year old captain Lester Smith
has been with air Illinois almost 5 years
he's one of its most
experienced pilots
gear is up
first officer Frank Tudor has
been with the airline for 3 years
he is considered one
of its top first officers
1000 feet
the pilots are flying a
Hawker Siddeley 748
the rugged turboprop is design
to land on shorter runways
these Hawker Siddeley 748
was one of the number of
aircraft built to replace the DC-3
as a commuter / cargo
/ military type aircraft
but primarily used
as a commuter aircraft
its the ideal plane
for a regional airline
that connects big cities
to small towns in Illinois
Illinois 710
radar identify
continue to 3000 feet
clear to Carbondale
Illinois 710, 3000 feet
thank you
good night
heading 175
less than two
minutes after take off
it's the generator again
a generators warning
light comes on
the aircraft is equipped
with two 9 kw generators
that supply power to the battery
banks and electrical systems
one of the generators has failed
isolating it now
the first officer disconnects
the right generator
to protect the rest of the
aircraft's electrical system
when something like this happens
and you have a generator failure
one of the most
importance steps is to
disconnect that generator from
the system as quickly as possible
Jeanene Urban is a
former air Illinois pilot
who landed the plane in
Springfield 3 hour earlier
the generators are each
rated to be able to carry
the entire load
so if one generator goes down
you can continue
to your destination
it's not an emergency
tonight 40 minute flight
is taking 7 passengers 146 miles
from Springfield to Carbondale Illinois
Springfield
Illinois 710
we've experienced a
slight electrical problem
we'll keep you advised
Illinois 710, do you intend
to return to Springfield?
negative, continuing
to Carbondale
3000 feet
the captain decides it's
safe to continue the flight
I understand, you're
continuing to Carbondale
roger
there's dense cloud
cover this evening
the conditions that
Carbondale were
what is called IFR
Instrument flight rules
they would have been
operating in the clouds
needed their instruments
to be able to fly the airplane
they were flying in the
deteriorating weather conditions
it's something that every year
airline pilot is trained to handle
but it doesn't give you
much room for error
4 minutes after take off
the first officer checks
the status of the generators
zero voltage and
amps on the left side
he discovers that the
left generator is dead
the right generator is
putting out 27.5 volts
the right generator now
appears to be working
but the first officer is unable to
reconnect it to the electrical system
I can't get it to come online
the right generator
is as good as dead
with both generators out
all the systems are
feeding off the batteries
instead of the generators
it's not a good situation
the aircraft has
4 Ni-Ca batteries
with no generators
the batteries are
now powering lights
instruments
navigational equipment
and everything in
the passenger cabin
how are the batteries?
we're down to 22.5 volts
so now they were operating
on only battery power
the priority problem is that the
batteries are only designed to operate
for about 30 minutes
under the best case scenario
Illinois 710 is now 32
minutes from its destination
if they don't reduce
the drain on the batteries
it will be almost impossible
to land without lights
instruments or a radio
okay
beacons off
nav lights are off
are you using these lights here?
I'll get that one down
the pilots quickly shut
down non essentials systems
the sooner they start
shutting things down
the longer the
battery is going to last
how are the batteries?
pretty good
21.5
the efforts to conserve battery
powers seemed to be paying off
should it last to Carbondale?
yeah
mid way to their destination
the weather deteriorate
the weather that Frank and Lester
encounter trying to get down to Carbondale
was much stormy than Springfield
there were level 2
and 3 thunderstorms
45 miles from Carbondale
the crew tunes into a signal
that will provide a precise
bearing to the airport
meanwhile air traffic control
transfers the flight to the approach
frequency for southern Illinois
air Illinois flight 710
contact Kansas city
center on frequency 125.3
25.3
roger
air Illinois 710
they were getting
close to the airport
and that approach control
facility would have lined them up
for an instrument approach
after contacting
approach control
the situation worsens
I don't know if we have
enough juice to get out of this
the radios and transponder
on flight 710 have shut down
the pilots are now on their own
Illinois 710
I've lost radar contact
flight 710 has disappeared
from air traffic control's radar
Illinois 710
Kansas city
they had no capability
at this point to get help
it was probably the most
sickening feeling for both of them
that you or I could imagine
watch my altitude
I'm going down to 240 feet
concerned their
instruments are about to fail
the captain attempts
to get below the clouds
he was desperately
hoping that he could see
the airport beacon
or some runway lights
and land that airplane visually
just 8 minutes from landing
have you got a flash light?
yeah
the batteries are
almost depleted
here we go
you wanna shine it up here
trying to illuminate the
instruments with the flash light
in a dark cockpit
is very abnormal
and as he pointed at
instrument that's dis-functioning
or one that's not
we're losing everything
down to 30 volts
watch my altitude frank
it would have been
a total panic situation
and realizing that
they were out of options
okay
rapidly losing electrical power
and operating in total darkness
the pilots of Illinois flight 710
desperately try to land their plane
the conditions at
Carbondale were
such that one mile of
visibility in light rain and fog
his chance of seeing anything
were minimum a best
do you have any instruments?
do you have a horizon?
they're in a dark cockpit
instruments are failing
they can't see anything outside
they were now into
a critical emergency
okay
you bank in left
6 degrees
okay
correcting to the right
a little more
Illinois 710
Kansas city
do you read?
I would be very surprise they
knew that they were going to hit
I would be very surprised
they saw the ground at all
air Illinois flight 710 crashes
25 miles north of
Carbondale airport
the wreckage scattered
across farm land
near the town of Pinckneyville
all 7 passengers and 3
crew members are dead
the national transportation
safety board (NTSB)
begins an investigation to
determine what happened to flight 710
let's see what we've got here
they begin by reviewing
the debris pattern
it's half a mile long
and
roughly 200 feet wide
investigators get a sense
of the vast impact area
which extends across
two small wooded areas
a field and a pond
they came in at a shallow angle
the wreckage pattern gave
us the idea that this was a
a fairly high speed
low angle impact
to be able to spread
the wreckage like this
over a half a mile
first point of
impact is right here
there's ground scars and debris
heading north
Carbondale airport is
25 miles to the south
investigators determine
that at the time of the crash
flight 710 was flying in the
opposite direction to its destination
with the aircraft
traveling the way it was
at that speed and
in a wrong direction
it made us wonder
was the aircraft
actually under control?
so first ground scare here
followed by a few more
and the 200 feet
in front of that
the right wing tip
near the first impact marks
investigators discover fragments
of a green navigation light
from their plane's
right wing tip
it was bank to the right
when it hit the ground
we had the right wing tip
we knew that was the
first thing that hit the ground
and we could measure
approximately 30 degree right bang
did the crew report any
issues to air traffic controller?
yeah
they did
Springfield
Illinois 710
we have experienced
the slight electrical problem
we'll keep you advised
investigators learned that 90
seconds after taking off from Springfield
the crew reported
an electrical problem
anything else
that's it
just the electrical problem
we'll need to take a good look
at all the electrical components
the pilot reported a
slight electrical problem
and it was up to
us to figured it out
what his problem was
and why they crashed
is these everything?
investigators examine
electrical components
for evidence of malfunctions
wires are clean
there is no short circuit
this inverter is in bad shape
hard to tell they
were working or not
what about the batteries?
4 Ni-Ca batteries are
powered by 2 generators
each battery contains
18 individual battery cells
no signs of arching or short
circuit as a result of the impact
we were able to recover total
of 10 cells from the batteries
and they were all
in descent shape
see if they can hold a charge
under normal conditions the
batteries should be fully charged
they're dead
the batteries are
able to hold its charge
but for some reason
they were run down
did the generators malfunction?
and failed to
charge the batteries
now the left generator
aircraft engines power
a generator's shaft
to rotate a metal core
wrapped in copper coil
this is known as an armature
the armature spins rapidly
between the poles of a magnet
to generate electricity
banding wire is come off
banding wire is used to hold the armature
together as it spins inside the assembly
if the banding wire comes lose
the armature could jam
soldering is melted
the motor must have overheated
investigators discover evidence
that the left generator failed
this happened before the crash
we know that there
was no fire on the aircraft
so we believed that the solder
melted due the internal heating
but we don't know why
they then inspect
the right generator
the banding wire
is intact in this one
looks fine
we did a resistance test
check the brushes
and we looked at all the
mechanical working to the generator
we were not able to
find any reason why
the right generator would
not charge the batteries
how did they crashed?
with 4 working batteries
and one working generator
from examination of the wreckage
we were not able to find
any reason for the accident
we were hoping the
the voice recorder
would give us clues as
to what really happened
the recording starts around
4 minutes after take off
investigators turned to flight
710's cockpit voice recorder
to determine how an aircraft with
one functioning generator crashed
short of its destination
zero voltage and
amps on the left side
just like we suspected
the CVR recording confirms that the left
generator failed shortly after take off
the right generator
is putting a 27.5 volts
but I can't get
it to come online
investigators can't understand
why the right generator was
disconnected from electrical system
if it was operational
then they hear an
astonishing statement
from the first
officer to the captain
when we lost the left one
I reached up and shut
off the right generator
because I assume the
problem was the right side
isolating it now
there are two shut off
switches for the generators
one for the left generators
and one for the right
the first officer
disconnects the right one
to protect the rest of the
aircraft electrical system
but he soon realizes that
it's the left one that has issue
not the right
why doesn't he
just reconnect it?
he tries
but it doesn't work
the right generator was not
charging the batteries
so that we know all they
had to power the aircraft
was the charge remaining on
the battery shortly after take off
maybe there is a problem
with the switching unit
if the generator switching
unit doesn't working
then the generator will
not come back online
so we were quite interested in learning
what we could about this component
it's pretty rough shape
looking for signs
of a malfunction
investigators examine the
right generator control switch
I can't tell 100 percent
it's possible it failed
before the crash
the switching unit was
heavily damaged from the crash
we were not able to determine
if that's even why the
generator would not come online
even if the switch was broken, it
doesn't explain the pilot's actions
the first officer says
I assume the problem
was with the right side
why would he assume
something like that?
it made us wonder if there is a
problem with that generator in the past
take a look at this
maintenance reports
the team reviews the maintenance records
for the Hawker Siddeley's generators
check it out
no less than 8 separate pilot complains
and repairs on the right generator
voltage fluctuations
recurring problems
at the regulator
causing the right
generator to shut down
two weeks before the crash
there were issues with the
right generator almost everyday
they were doing maintenance
they were troubleshooting it
they were changing parts
and they couldn't fixed it
air Illinois had one Hawker Siddeley
and 3 flight crews flying that plane
I'm sure that they all knew that
the right generator had
had problems in the past
they probably all experienced
at one time or another
the first officer had been
on some of those flights
where the right generator
had actually disconnected
thank goodness
I was not
that would explain
why the first officer disconnected
the right generator instead of left one
investigators suspect that
on the night of the crash
it's the generator again
the first officer made
the immediate assumption
that the right generator
had malfunctioned
the reaction that the first officer had
about taking the right generator offline
probably falls into a phenomenon
that's called expectation bias
he has experiences in the past
and assumed that was
going to be the problem
without really looking at the
indication that were available to him
it still doesn't explain the crash
even though both
generators were offline
investigators know the aircraft's
batteries were in working order
how are the batteries?
pretty good
they're at 21.5
should it last to Carbondale?
yeah
it was really important to know
did the batteries have enough
endurance to get to the airport?
let's see how they
managed their battery power
investigators return to
the cockpit voice recorder
to determine why flight 710 run out of
battery power before reaching Carbondale
how are the batteries there?
we're down to 22.5 volts
okay
beacons off
nav lights are off
just minutes after discovering
both generators are down
the pilots turn off
non essential systems
to save their batteries
they're doing the right thing
turning things
off to reduce load
but is it enough?
according to the manufacture, they
needed to reduce the load to 70 amps
amps measure the strength
of an electrical current
the more amps drawn on a battery
the faster the
battery will discharge
if the crew would have
reduced the load to 70 amps
that would have given them
minimum of 30 minutes of endurance
that might have been enough time
to get them to the Carbondale airport
let's see if they got their
load down to 70 amps
well
we know they
turned off the beacons
navigation lights
investigators make an inventory
of the instruments the crew
turned off and what they left on
in order to calculate
the load on the batteries
what else?
are you using these lights here?
I'll get that one down
we were not able to determine
what was powered up or
on or off based on
the flight recorder
should it last to Carbondale?
so we had to rely on the
conversations between the two pilots
what to leave on
and what to turn off
DME instruments
weather radar
main cabin lights
one of the main radios
cooling fan
and the transponder
the weather radar and the
radios draw a lot of power
and so shedding those if you
can is a prudent thing to do
looks like they kept the rest
of the flight instruments on and
that's it
they used a 110 amps
investigators discover the crew did not
properly reduce the drew on their batteries
I wonder they didn't
make it to the Carbondale
this important with load shedding
and getting down to 70 amps
seems to be lost on the crew
as there seems to be no discussion
whatsoever about amperage to determine
if their changes in electrical system
were actually making a difference
and the longevity
of the batteries
so why did the pilots believed they had
enough power to reach their destination
the team checks to see how the
pilots monitored the state of the batteries
says here fully charged
the batteries is at 24 volts
let's see how they did
how are the batteries there?
we're down to 22.5 volts
8 minutes into the flight
they used up 1.5 volts
7 minutes later
how are the batteries?
pretty good
they're at 21.5
the battery charge
drops another volt
to 21.5
the first officer says the
battery should last to Carbondale
they're half way through the flight
he's feeling good
and then 9 minutes later
he checks again
it's 20 volts
so they think
they're doing alright
and then minutes later
the radios go dead
we're losing everything
down to 30 volts
they're talking
about having 20 volt
and then they all of a
sudden they have 30 volt
so they're monitoring the volt
but it's as if the sudden
drop caught them by surprise
the reason this is significant
is because Ni-Ca batteries
will maintain their voltage almost right
until the end that the batteries are dead
much different than
Lead-acid batteries
which is where you see a
gradual decline in voltage
that characteristic
of Ni-Ca batteries
may explain why there was such a
sudden drop in the battery voltage
I don't know if we have
enough juice to get out of this
if they would have known the
characteristic of the Ni-Ca battery
it might've sent them
a message saying
we better get on this right away
get this low reduce
investigators find another reason
why the crew may have missed
how fast their batteries
will discharging
they never mentioned their amps
looks like the only thing
they monitored were the volts
volt measure the potential
output of the battery
not how long it will last
amps tell you how much
electricity is being drawn
it was very surprising that they
weren't monitoring the amperage
because that was going to tell them
how much longer they had on the batteries
did the crew have the proper training to
monitor the endurance of the batteries?
investigators interview
other air Illinois pilots
so what did you find out?
to determine their ability to monitor
and calculate battery endurance
well
we know that they're all trained on battery
management for a dual generator problem
but
when I ask them how long they thought
the battery would have last on the flight
some calculated 30 minutes
others
less than an hour
five pilots gave us
five different answers
and they were not all correct
that became obvious to us there was
definitely a training issue involved here
are you using these lights here?
I'll get that one down
the lack of training explains
why the pilots thought they had
enough power to reach Carbondale
but that doesn't
solve a bigger mystery
this is their flight path
why didn't the pilots land
the plane at another airport?
before completely
running out of battery power
one, two, three, four,
five different airports
they were only five minutes
away from Springfield
yet they elected to go
40 minutes to Carbondale
and there were several airports
in between that they missed
they could have landed
anytime along the way
their decision not to land caused
the pilots judgments into question
it's time to look into
their backgrounds
here is the captain's file
investigators dig into the
backgrounds of flight 710 pilots
for clues that explain their unusual
reaction to an electrical failure
the captain was
perfectly qualified
same with the FO
gear up
the two pilots were among the most
experienced flight crew on the roster
gear is up
with the combined 5000 flying hours
between them on the Hawker Siddeley
here is something
the captain lived in Carbondale
maybe he wanted get home
in aviation what we describe
as get home itis is when
we try to make it to the destination
because of our strong desire to do so
and get place a significant
role in our decision making
investigators talk to
other pilots of the company
including first officer
Jeanene Urban
how well did you
know the pilots?
I flew with the captain
I was get friends
with the first officer
I thought very highly
of the first officer Frank
I knew the flight
attendant Barbie
and liked her a lot
it was a very emotional thing that
hear that both of them had been killed
what sort of pilot
was the captain?
I'd say average
in aviation community when someone
is characterized as an average pilot
that usually means
he's not too good
why is that?
the captain really prided
himself on getting there on time
it was not uncommon
for him to take risks
looks like we've
got some weather
shall I call for deviation?
it doesn't look too bad
we'll be fine
according to air Illinois pilots
the captain would
often fly too close
or through dangerous
storms to save flight time
if I made any
comments or suggestions
about a safety issue like the
thunderstorm or anything else
he would do something spiteful
just to prove that
he was the captain
in order to keep schedule
he'd also speed up
which would set off
the over speed alarm
pull the circuit breaker
would you?
what?
really
pilots said he would ordered them
to disable the over speed warning
so that they could fly faster
it was always about
getting there faster
the captain behavior
is troublesome
we wanted to know if
the company the airline
was putting undue pressure on
the pilots to make the schedule
this pressure to get there on time
was it from management?
no
it was all the captain
the interviews with the
other pilots indicated
that there was no undue
pressure to skirt the rules
in the case of captain
that pressure was self imposed
investigators conclude that captain
Smith often stretched the rules
what about the first officer?
Frank was the best
and he knew the plane
and its systems very well
so why didn't the
first officer speak up
when captain Smith made
the decision to carry on
Illinois 710
do you intend to
return to Springfield?
negative, continuing to
Carbondale, 3000 feet
in a no time did we
hear the first officer
challenge the captain's
decision to go into Carbondale
we found this very perplexing
I asked how he could fly with the
captain because he took so many chances
and he said all I just
try to keep an eye on the
situation and not let him
get us into anything
that I can't get us out of
we're losing everything
down to 30 volts
watch my altitude frank
well that didn't
workout very well at all
the captain should have made the decision
to return to the Springfield airport
and if so, none of this
would have happened
thank you
investigators conclude
that the risk taking captain
and a non-assertive
first officer
was a dangerous combination
let's pick it up
from where they realize they don't have
enough power to make it to Carbondale
the team returns to the
cockpit voice recording
to see if they can uncover why
the plane ended up so far off course
watch my altitude
going down to 2400 feet
okay
stop the tape
why would the captain decide
to drop down to 2400 feet?
the cloud ceiling near
Carbondale was almost 2,000 feet
so maybe he was
popping in out of the clouds
to see something on the ground
play on
have you got a flash light?
yeah
here we go
you wanna shine it up here
just as the captain
tries to see the ground
the cockpit lights go out
and plunge them
into total darkness
we're losing everything
down to 30 volts
watch my altitude Frank
okay
they make it to 2400 feet
and captain plans to level off
spot the runway and
continue his descent
but that's not what happens
okay, you're banking left
6 degrees
okay correcting to the right
just minutes later, they ended up crashing
in completely the opposite direction
a little more
so the question is
what happened?
how did they go from
leveling off at 2400 feet
to then hitting the ground
in the opposite direction?
investigators examine the
final moments of flight 710
to determine what ultimately
brought the plane down
how does the recording end?
the recording eerily slows down
and then
silence
the batteries just died
the captain is asking
for a horizon reading
on the attitude
directional indicator (ADI)
the ADI uses an
electrically power gyroscopic
to indicate the
aircraft's pitch and roll
relative to the earth horizon
it's night time
indiscernible horizon
low visibility
your ADI is everything that you need to
be able to keep the airplane wings level
it lost the lights on
their instruments
some of them
are starting to fail
he asked the first officer
to shine a light on their ADI
okay, you banked left
6 degrees
okay
correcting to the right
investigators can only
surmise what happened next
even if all the
instruments had failed
the ADI would still
look like it's working
the ADI gyroscope
spins at about 15,000 rpm
even after the power shuts down
it will continue rotating
for several minutes
so look like it's working
but it really is not
as the ADI winds down
it slowly tilts to one side
imagine that ADI starts
slowly falling to left
he correct by
rolling to the right
okay, you banked left
6 degrees
okay, correcting to the right
a little more
it may have appeared to them
that the ADI was working correctly
but they're really banking
to the right losing altitude
they probably
followed that failing ADI
right into the ground
they couldn't see where they are
they couldn't see any lights and
it would be over an instant
in the final report
investigators conclude
that the fatal accident
was a consequence of the captain's decision
to continue the flight toward Carbondale
instead of returning to the nearby
departure airport after the lost of power
the cause of this accident
was not a catastrophic failure
that suddenly cause
the airplane to crash
it was the decision
by the captain
to continue flight
on battery power
after they lost the generators
also adding to the problem was a
lack of crew resource management
or CRM
no part of crew resource
management training is that
crews are trained
to act as a team
and first officers are
taught and encourage
to question the captain's decision
making and actions, if they do not agree
speak up
don't worry about if it
upsets somebody ego
it's not worth dying over
investigators site
inadequate crew training
to assess battery endurance
as another contributing factor
it should have been
discussed in their training
in their training materials
and in the flight manual
as a result of this accident
the NTSB also recommends
independently powered ADIs
on all transport airplanes
so that if all power was lost
they still had the ability
to keep the airplane straight
level for at least 30 minutes
this recommendation
was implemented in 1997
flight 710 brought
national attention
and increased scrutiny
of small commuter airlines
six month after the accident
air Illinois filed for bankruptcy
and ceased operations
it's something we
we learn by our mistakes
the first priority is the
safety of the passengers
is gotta be the
most important factor