on approach to
Raleigh–Durham Airport
did we just have a flameout?
the pilots decide
to abort their landing
when you have an engine failure
you lose 80 percent
of your performance
let's go
miss approach
but the plan falls apart
we were going down
only five of the 20
people on board survived
NTSB investigators are puzzled
by the wreckage of flight 3379
it appears the engines
were rotating full power
so what went wrong?
only by taking a test
flight to the brink of disaster
flying to the left
will an astonishing sequence
of events be revealed
this airplane had to crash
American Eagle Flight 3379 approaches
Raleigh–Durham International Airport
okay
can you do the descent
checklist please?
in the cockpit
Captain Michael Hillis
and First Officer Matthew Sailor
prepare for landing
altimeter 3031
set, cross checked
3031 set
cross checked
these were young pilots
just starting off in their career
they were looking to go
work at the major airlines
where the pay and benefits
were substantially better
the pilots are flying
a jet stream 3201
a twin turboprop airplane
designed for short flights
it's a workhorse for regional
airlines like American eagle
turboprop engines run more
efficiently at lower altitudes
they're actually
more fuel efficient
so on these short haul routes
the jet stream pretty
much fit that market
flight 3379 took off at 6:00 pm
from Greensboro North Carolina
it's 35 minute flight to
Raleigh–Durham airport
well folks at this time
we're about 10.8 miles from
Raleigh–Durham International Airport
about five minutes out, we're
about to begin our approach
weather tonight is not
very good at Raleigh
2 mile of visibility
because of rain and fog
and winds towards the
north 6 miles an hour
there are 18 passengers
on board tonight
among them college
student Lauren Anderson
I had been up the night before
I'd stayed up all night
holding all nighter
wrote a paper and slid under
the door of my English professor
that morning
so I was pretty tired
it'd been long week of finals
I was ready to get home
Eagle Flight 3379
reduce to 170 then
descent and maintain 3,000
10 miles from Raleigh–Durham
flight 3379 is clear
to begin its descent
170 then 3,000
the flight crew
reduces engine power
in a turboprop plane
the engine power and the propeller
speed are controlled separately
the jet stream 32
had no autopilot
so
you were always hand-flying
it was one of the most demanding
airplanes on the pilot's flying skills
descending to 3,000 feet
the crew keeps a
close eye on the weather
get a chance
look at your window and
see if you see any of that ice
yeah I was looking out there
I don't see anything right now
icing can be a major
threat to an aircraft
and not only increases
the weight of it
but also spoils the
aerodynamics over the wing
icing isn't the only
hazard facing the pilots
Eagle Flight 3379
caution wake turbulence
you're spacing on a 727
turn left 190
there is 727 landing
ahead of flight 3379
which creates a potential
hazard for the jet stream
heavy aircraft tend to generate
very strong horizontal tornadoes
called vortexes
that come off the wing tips
if small aircraft has an
encounter with wake turbulence
it could be so powerful
that it's beyond the control
of the pilot to counteract it
left 190
for safety the pilots make a
minor adjustment to their course
eagle flight 3379
Raleigh
clear to land
wind
010 at 8
traffic 3.5 mile final
clear to land
once the Boeing 727 touches down
flight 3379 will
be clear to land
we didn't anticipate any issues
it was the same old same old
I probably had taken that
flight 3 times already that year
and gear down
gear down
the pilots configure
the plane for landing
flaps 20
just minutes before touch down
why is that ignition light on?
did we just have a flameout?
the engine ignition
light illuminates
seeing the ignition light
come on during approach
would typically raise a concern
if combustion is interrupted for any
reason is what pilots call a flameout
or an engine failure
not sure what's going on with it
if there is an engine failure
the pilots need to
reconsider landing
the pilot would have to make the
decision weather to continue the approach
or abort the approach
see what the problem is
what do you want me to do?
are you going to continue?
okay
yeah
I'm gonna continue
just back me up
captain Hillis decides to land
all right
let's go
missed approach
but then
he reverses his decision
a go around or a missed approach
would have given the pilot more
time to run an engine failure check list
when you're on final you really don't
have that much time to complete it
set max power
now at 1500 feet
captain Hillis aborts the landing
when you have an engine failure
you're not only lost
half of your power
you lose 80 percent
of your performance
flight 3379 isn't climbing
and it's losing speed
at 1400 feet
the plane stalling
have you got it?
yeah
they're unable to climb
they're starting to lose
directional control of the aircraft
flight 3379 is turning
steadily to the left
veering further off course
things are getting bad real fast
and they're running out of time
here
plunging rapidly
towards the ground
the pilots fight to
recover their plane
there's no flight
attendant on the plane
there is a lot of commotion
and you could hear
some kind of warning siren
I was scared
people were scared
we knew we were crashing, I knew
we were going down
I just brace myself
literally putting my hand and
my foot on the seat in front of me
I had a moment that
okay I need to survive
I need to live through this
when we crashed
I just remember
hitting the ground
very very fast very hard
flight 3379 has just plowed through
the dense wood of north Carolina
it's now a pile of
burning wreckage
the plane split literally in between
my seat and the seat in front of me
I can remember
taking my seat belt off
and hearing people moaning
people screaming
I couldn't see anything
I don't know if I
lost my contacts
or I just had fuel in my eyes
I couldn't walk
but
my adrenaline was pumping
I was in fight and flight mode
my intuition was
that I had to survive
and somehow I got
away from the fire
Morrisville firefighter David Farrel
is one of the first responders on site
when your heart racing
I mean
you know you're
probably encounter
on the worst things
you've ever been in your life
you could see the fire
your heart was in your throat
your adrenaline was pumping
you're scared
as I got closer to the scene
someone call me out
and I look down
I saw a female
pulling herself
away from the fire
and she couldn't move her legs
he had asked my
name and I told him
I needed to find my suitcase
and then I needed to get home
that's it you
you're gonna make it
you're not going
down on my watch
you threw the worse of this,
we're going to get you out of here
Lauren Anderson is
one of only five survivals
50 others are killed
I did break bones in my hand
my clavicle
broke my ribs
puncture my lungs
I've broken dislocated my back
tibia, fibula
break in my left leg
bounce my ankle
Captain Michael Hillis and First Officer
Matthew Sailor are among the dead
national transportation safety board
investigators are on site by morning
anyone find the data recorders?
team is still looking
the weather wasn't
great last night
now we need the
pilot's record device
and weather data
in this particular accident, icing
was very paramount because
3379 was the second
accident for American eagle
just a few weeks past
we'd had another jet stream
involved with icing conditions
was icing the reason flight 3379
failed to make it to the airport?
just 4 miles away
landing gear is down
do you know how
the flaps was set?
I'll check with the
guy in the cockpit
stretch here
what can you tell us
about the flaps selector?
the cockpit section was
particularly damaged
a lot of controls on the instruments
were unable to document
the flaps like are used
in 20 degree position
copy that
the flap extension was
also very interesting because
it was in the
landing configuration
thank you very much
the plane was iced
up as they were landing
and that's trouble
we had to start
making major inquiries
into the possibility of
an icing involvement
these are pilot reports from 5
other planes flying into Raleigh
we do a pilot's
reporting light icing
but
just traced at high altitudes
investigators learned that the other
pilots flying near Raleigh–Durham
weren't reporting any
significant issues with icing
the icing although it
was present in the area
was absolutely no factor
in the accident investigation
they're all set to land
so what went wrong
maybe they had engine trouble
the investigators had
done major challenge
try to figured out if one of the
engines had malfunctioned in some way
can you bring that
blade over here, please?
thank you
thank you sir
now is this blade
from left propeller?
yes, this is from
the right propeller
the team examines the propellers
for an indication that
they were rotating
the way the blade is damaged
provides a clue
if you've got turning
propellers on your airplane
they tend to grab into
things and bend forward
as they hit the debris
of trees and so on
it appears the engines
were rotating full power
so it's 4 miles from the airport
it's configured to land
what happened?
as we spent more time
on site with 3379 wreckage
the questions just kept coming
it made it very clear that
this accident was
gonna be a real puzzler
were pilots reporting any
problem during approach?
let me look
NTSB investigators hope the pilots
conversations with air traffic controllers
can shed some light on
why flight 3379 crashed
before reaching
Raleigh–Durham Airport
they're the last people
to talk to the crew
and we wanna know if
there was anything unusual
in their conversations
no there wasn't anything
out of the ordinary
eagle flight 3379
reduce to 170 then
descent and maintain 3000
the controller tells investigators that
flight 3379 approach seem routine
170 then 3000
was there any conflicting
traffic as they were coming in?
well
yes
there was a 727 landing
right ahead of them
I warned them about
wake turbulence
eagle flight 3379
caution wake turbulence
you're spacing on a 727
turn left 190
the wake turbulence
issue is particularly critical
this would be a factor that
we're gonna have to deal with
thank you very much
how fast does a
wake vortex descent?
300 feet per minute
investigators compare
the flight path of flight 3379
with the estimated
path of the wake vortex
all right
let's see what we got
they used recorded radar
returns for both planes
and factoring the weather
at the time of the accident
looks like flight 3379 missed it
above more than 600 feet
the jet stream did not fly
throw any of those vortexes
wake turbulence did not affect
the flight path of the accident aircraft
but the radar data reveals that
something happened along the flight path
kind of severe off course
after missing the wake vortexes
he's off to the left
why?
why is this aircraft
over here to the left of
the final approach path
configured to land?
okay
can you do the descent
checklist please?
the team turn to the
cockpit voice recorder
hoping they might
find an explanation
for the unusual left turn
we were gonna
really have to look at
what was going on
on the flight deck
with the cockpit crew
what were they saying
what were their intentions
altimeter 3031
set
cross checked
pressurization
set and checked
ice protection is on
investigators hear the
captain and first officer
planning the
approach with precision
okay
reviewed
so far so good
the flight crew seems to
be working in perfect tandem
as flight 3379
approaches the airport
why is that ignition light on?
did we just have a flame out?
did he just say flame out?
when the captain talks
about the ignition flight
that
all of a sudden
that came out of no where
we had a flame out
we lost the left one?
yeah
they discover that the
ignition light illuminated
moments before the crash
this ignition light introduce
the thought of the lost engine
considering the physical
evidence we've seen
this idea was very strange
you would expect during that period that
there would be some sort of confirmation
nothing happened
other than absolute quite
we needed to try and
figure out what was going on
this is the engine sound waves
from when the ignition light is on
another way for investigators to
determine if the engines were operating
is to analyze their sound on
the cockpit voice recording
this study is attempting to home
in on blade passing frequencies
blade passing meaning
all these revolutions
of the propeller
conflict comparison
they compare the engine
sounds from flight 3379
to other engines
operating at 100 percent
we were looking at the acoustics
of the engine performance
and it's relatively easy to match that
against the acoustics of a working engine
literally almost identical
investigators hear evidence that
both engines were running at full speed
the sound analysis told us the
sound generated by the engines
on this aircraft were consistent
with two engines generating power
the ignition light
must've misled the pilots
in believing the left
engine flamed out
but really
it hadn't
this sound analysis put the
idea of an engine failure to bed
it just wasn't a
factor in the accident
this discovery leaves
investigators puzzled
why was that ignition light on if there
was nothing wrong with the engine?
why is that ignition light on?
did we just have a flame out?
investigators examine
jet stream manuals
to determine why an
ignition light would come on
even though the plane
engines were fully operational
so why activated?
it's wired to negative
torque system
negative torque occurs
when the air loads on the propellers
cause then to drive the engines
instead of the engines
driving the propellers
it can be a sign of a flame out
the same scenario
you would have is
when you put your car in
low gear going down a hill
and use the transmission to drag
says the ignition
light will activate
they advance the
propeller speed too quickly
there is a situation when
you would be in a low power
setting on your torque and
as you go speeds high
in preparation for landing
if you move those speed
levers up too quickly
that can trigger the negative
torque to cause that light to come on
go ahead
flaps 10
investigators return to the CVR
to learn if the pilots mention
increasing the propeller speed
let's go ahead and go speed type
they hear captain Hillis advancing the
propellers to a 100 percent for landing
why is that ignition light on?
there it is
advance the propeller
speed and boom
the ignition light illuminates
the team discovers that the
pilots created negative torque
negative torque doesn't necessary
mean there was an engine failure
you would get a transient
situation for a second or two
that could trigger
that light to come on
we had a flame out
he missed diagnoses
the situation
surely he checks engines' rpm
what do you want me to do?
are you gonna continue?
okay
yeah
I'm gonna continue
just back me up
he's not even checking to see
if there is an actual engine failure
look at your instruments
determine whether or not the
both engines are generating power
it's not that hard
they're trained for that
100 percent full power
if you don't know if you
have an engine failure
but you're responding to
a potential engine failure
that's not very good
and that could very
easily cause an accident
let's go
miss approach
so what actions did the pilots
take during the missed approach?
okay so how did they configure
the plane for missed approach?
set engine power max
set max power
as they should have
what else?
it's not mention reducing the
flaps to 10 or retracting landing gear
a go around would be done
by informing the other pilot then
applying max power
retract the gear
retract the flaps
but the pilot's failure to raise
the gear or retract the flaps
doesn't explain the accident
how does that configuration cause
the plane to veer left and crashed?
well there is only
one way to find out
there was a necessity
to conduct a flight test
because we really wanted to figure
out what the crew had introduced
in the configuration
that would make the aircraft
deviate from this intended flight path
okay let's go max power
investigators turn
to test pilots for help
they'll take a jet-stream
3201 to its limit
to try to solve the mystery
sometimes you have to put
yourself in an uncomfortable position
and you know what's gonna
happen if you go too far
max power
flaps at 20
they start by duplicating the configuration
the pilots had set for the missed approach
flaps 20
gear down
good
okay it's slower than a regular
missed approach but still doable
so why did fly 3379 turn
to the left and crashed?
let's do the same
configuration but
put max power on the
right engine but not the left
roger that
they try a different
configuration
in the hope of recreating
the pilot's actions
max power
right engine
I can't climb like this
investigators finally understand how
captain hillis executed the missed approach
set max power
believing his left
engine has failed
the captain increases
power only to the right engine
the imbalance in engine power robs the
plane of the airspeed it needs to climb out
with the gear down
and the flaps extended
the flight test told us an
airplane with that configuration
could not have
been fallen safely
it had to crash
investigators conclude
that the captain didn't configure his
plane correctly for a missed approach
if the captain thought
one of his engines fail
they should have performed
single engine missed approach
they didn't do that either
so he set himself up for
a nearly unflyable airplane
you got it
yeah
NTSB investigators focus
squarely on the captain of flight 3379
29 year old
Michael Hillis
to come across an accident where response
was botched as thoroughly as this one
it begs the question:
how did he get there?
he's got 2,294 turboprops
3,499 total flying hours
NTSB investigators scrutinize the personnel
records of the pilots of flight 3379
we want to find out the
background of the pilots
is there anything in their
performance that can reveal
something about
their performance
in the night of the accident
from American eagle files
the team learns
that Michael Hillis was licensed
to fly multiple turboprop airplanes
in march 1991
we've got single engine
missed approaches today
are you ready for that?
yes sir
investigators dig deeper
into captain hillis's pilot records
right
I'm cutting your left engine
we like to see an
airman with airmanship
so we had to look back
at the training information
look this
trainers evaluation
okay you're losing airspeed that you're
gonna need how do you get it back?
not sure
this is telling
he's messing up single
engine missed approaches
it was very obvious that this captain
was having serious troubles with his
airmanship development
single engine missed approaches
engine failures
when is this?
April 1992
that was two years
before the accident
it's more than enough
time to improve
he makes captain
a few month later
by the time pilots
become airline pilots
they're pretty good
the selection
process is so rigorous
that you don't get
to be an airline pilot
unless you have
considerable capabilities
it's all have here
of any American eagle pilots
we'll talk about them
let's find out
the NTSB wants to know
more about Hillis's career
usually in the pilot file
there will be some notes
about the issues that have been encountered
by other persons flying with the captain
what can you tell me
about Michael Hillis?
we're pretty
broken up about this
investigators track down American
eagle Raleigh–Durham base manager
unfortunately we have a lot
of complains about his flying
I was really surprise
to hear him say that
complains
several first officers that
flew with him at Raleigh
co-pilots were whispering
to their colleagues
it was something not normal
and we had co-pilots that
were afraid to fly with him
and keep a close eye
on what he was doing
really
if pilots are afraid
to fly with this guy
which is essentially what
the base manager told us
that's very revealing
about the accident
thanks a lot
hate to say it but this is
a really questionable pilot
we got a picture of a
pilot who could fly okay
but when he was faced
with something unexpected
his performance
would start deteriorating
how this guy end
up at American Eagle?
where are their final?
application should be on file
we try to get as much
information as we can
for complete pilots history
his previous job was with Comair
captain hillis applied to work
for American eagle in Oct 1919
while he was flying
for another airline
finer if did a background
check this guy
when investigators ask American eagle
about background checks on Michael Hillis
they shocked by what they learned
they did not go back and
check with previous employers
the NTSB does what
American eagle never did
they requisition Michael
Hillis' file from Comair
when we compared his records of
comair with his records at American eagle
they were consistent
moody
unpredictable
gets distracted
concerns about tunnel vision
in an emergency situation
and he was potentially
a dangerous pilot
tunnel vision in
emergency situation
comair considered
this guy wanted him fired
it just keeps getting worse
I've never encountered
before since
a pilot who was
recommended to be terminated
because he was
potentially unsafe
comair recommended for dismissal
did they fired him?
he resigns from comair
before they can fire
that captain should not
have been flying passengers
under any circumstances
did the American eagle know
about this guy performance history?
it didn't look like they asked
no record of comair
providing to American eagle
but the picture is crystal clear
Michael Hillis' flying career was
blemished by failed certification test
bad evaluations from trainers
and complains from colleges that
will never passed on to American eagle
one would have to ask
themselves if you really knew
the background of this pilot
would you put your wife
or your child in that aircraft?
and the answer would be no
but there were two pilots
in the cockpit of flight 3379
in this case
the ability of first officer to recognize
that the captain skills were deficient
it took a long time
did the first officer know
who he is flying with?
here
investigators wonder
if first officer sailor knew he
was team with an unreliable pilot?
no
First Officer Matthew Sailor
25 years old
work for American eagle
for a year before the crash
the NTSB looks into the work
schedules of first officer sailor
and captain hillis
have they flown with us before?
no
not once
they discover the first officer
was knew to this particular route
so was he based at Raleigh?
no
he work out of Miami
I think it was critical
to this accident
that the first officer was from a
different base than the captain
first officer in Raleigh–Durham
need to keep a close eye on him but
he's out of Miami
this guy had no idea
who he was flying with
let's go ahead and go speed type
when first officer sailor joins captain
hillis in the cockpit on Dec 13 1994
he has no idea what
type of pilot he's team with
this pilot should've never been
a pilot and command that aircraft
as flight 3379 is on final
approach for Raleigh–Durham
captain hillis is
caught by surprise
he missed interpret's the
illumination of an ignition light
why is that ignition light on?
did we just have a flame out?
not sure what's going on with it
we had a flame out
captain hillis doesn't realize that by
increasing the propeller speed too quickly
he has created a momentary
negative torque condition
he missed diagnoses
engine failure
and responded improperly
I am gonna continue
instead of landing hillis
decides to do a go around
let's go
missed approach
starting with the
captain's misdiagnosis
of an engine failure
and his decision to go around
pretty much was
self-induced engine failure
the pilots now face
a severe emergency
the gear was down
it was trying to climb
set max power
it was impossible
in that configuration
they basically about
to go off the edge of cliff
it falls to the first officer
to rectify captain's mistakes
here
I think he could have
saved the airplane
but by the time
he recognize that
it was too late
15 people are killed
because of hillis' errors
made every mistake in the book
in the last two minutes of the flight
I had anger
sure at that time for
the pilot and the co-pilot
for the errors that they made
ultimately there was more
pointing fingers to the airline
if American eagle access documents
about hillis' past before they hire him
he might not have been in
that cockpit on Dec 13 1994
the final takeaway
from 3379 is that
we've gotta identify
those airman
that don't display
airmanship qualities
the crash of flight
3379 reveals deep flaws
in the standard hiring
practices of US airlines
background information on pilots
is almost never shared amongst airlines
if I was to apply
for a job somewhere
they would check my references
this is a pilot
isn't it important that we find out if
this person is competent enough?
that's for 88
tragically the case of flight
3379 is not unprecedented
again 93
in three previous accidents
the NTSB recommended that
records from previous employers
be made available to a
pilot's current employer
four times job
now for the forth time
the NTSB recommends
that US airlines conduct
better background checks
on perspective pilots
but still no changes are
made to federal regulations
I felt like I had
to do something
I had to speak for these
15 people that couldn't speak
and I went spoke
in front of congress
in 1996 two years
after the crash
US congress passes the
pilots record information act
to ensure airlines have access to
previous companies pilot records
the chances of a pilot falling
through the cracks as this pilot did
have been reduced
because of the legislation
it's unfortunate for
that to happen but
but that's what it took