no no no
security footage of
flight Dubai flight 981
captures its final moments
oh it's diving hard
the level of violence to
the impact was catastrophic
62 people are
killed in the fatal dive
investigators soon discovered
the pilots had aborted two landings
Rostov tower
we're going around
a go around is done just
when conditions are not perfect
did they say why they were
going around the second time?
they just said
going around
check your speed
the next thing I knew the plane
was diving towards the runway
investigators needed to find out
how the two go-arounds were different
one turns to disaster
why?
fly Dubai flight 981 closes in on
Rostov-on-don international airport
in south west Russia
Rostov tower
sky Dubai 981
we're at 2600 feet
2300 feet is our
next target altitude
11 miles out
captain Aristos Sokratous
and first officer
Alejandro Álava Cruz
prepare the Boeing
737800 for touch down
both pilots had a pretty good amount
of flying hours in 737 specifically
these were experienced pilots
flight 981
Rostov-tower
winds 240 degrees
gust 30 knots
you're clear to
land on runway 22
the controller reports the
weather conditions at the airport
thick clouds cover Rostov-on-don
high winds are
battering the runways
the weather in Rostov
at that time was
pretty low cloud
with wind gusts
it was typical for that
time of year for Rostov
if you look at the
geography with the
sea and the hills around it
then yes
you can expect some challenges
fly Dubai flight 981 departed
Dubai international airport at 10:PM
it's 4 hour flight north
west to Rostov-on-Don
it's bumpy ride for the
55 passengers on board
the flight is expected
to land in minutes
150 knots
8 miles out
the pilots reduce speed
as they begin the final descent
on approach
pilots know exactly
what the airplane is doing
the know the conditions
that they're flying in
flaps 30
they're going to drop
the flaps bit by bit
when they dropped
their landing gear
it's very gradual process
it should be a bit bumpy
and later should be calm
the pilots expect
turbulence on approach
but anticipate a smooth landing
the runway is just 4 miles away
but there is thread ahead
go around
wind-shear ahead
the on-board radar has
detected dangerous winds
wind-shear ahead
wind-shear is a rapid change
in direction and speed of wind
if a pilot experiences a strong head-wind
that suddenly changes to a tail-wind
the aircraft might not have
enough lift to remain airborne
especially at low altitude
the wind-shear alert is build into
the aircraft's avionics to tell you
going in the wind currents
that could be problematic
wind-shear ahead
wind-shear
go-around
just one thousand
feet above the ground
landing at Rostov-on-don
becomes too risky
Rostov tower
this is 981
we're conducting a go-around
due to the wind-shear
the pilots abort their approach
every pilot is prepared to make
a go-around on every approach
it's something that pilots do
off the top of their heads
there's no manual involved
they have a limit the amount
of approaches that can try
as long as they
have enough fuels
so why not go-around
and let's try it again
flight 981
copy
flight 981 is one of four incoming
flights controllers are managing
as high winds delay landings
Aeroflot 1166
be advised
sky Dubai 981 reports
wind-shear on landing
the air traffic
controller's work-flow
was definitely increased
in this environment
and they have to start
juggling all those cards in the air
as flight 981 climbs
Aeroflot 1166
you're clear to
land on runway 22
an Aeroflot flight
prepares to land
captain Sokratous pays close
attention to its communications
I wanna see what
this guy will do
the crew at this point is hoping
that the crews of other's flights
are able to give them some
information that they might be able to use
to make some decision
about what to do next
that flight can't land
at Rostov-on-don either
Aeroflot 1166
we're going-around
due to wind-shear
the Aeroflot pilots also encounter
wind-shear on final approach
they're forced to abort
that kind of seals the deal
fly Dubai is gonna
have to either wait
or they're gonna have to
go to an alternative airport
high over Rostov-on-don
passengers on
flight 981 are restless
the pilots are
holding at 15000 feet
circling near the airport
waiting for a chance to land
the pilot sit on a holding pattern since
that had enough fuel to be able to do so
to wait for weather
conditions to improve
3 other planes are
also in a holding pattern
the storm pounding
Rostov-on-don isn't passing
Aeroflot 1166
we're diverting
sky Dubai 981
for your information
previous flight went
to alternative airport
all the other flights decide to
divert to alternate airport instead
the problem with diverting is that
it's expensive and it's inconvenient
the passengers don't
end up with the destination
they have to be put up in hotels
and
with low-cost airline
it's the last thing it wants
captain Sokratous continues
monitoring the weather radar
finally he spots a clearing
I think I can give it a try
I agree
let's try
it's not unusual for crews to take
advantage if there happens to be
breaking the weather pattern that provides
safe conditions to land the aircraft
sky Dubai 981
request descent
for another approach
50000 feet over Rostov-on-don
the pilots again prepare to land
sky Dubai 981
Rostov tower
you're clear to
land on runway 22
good evening
your first officer here
we'll be landing shortly
once again we
apologize for the delay
13 miles from runway 22
the pilots lined up
for a second approach
be advised
low altitude had wind 53 knots
even though winds are strong
controllers aren't reporting
wind-shear at the runway
flaps 30
but as they approach
they soon realize
something's not right
check your speed
okay
go around
the pilots execute
another go-around
keep it at 50 degrees
goes up
just 2000 feet in the air
captain Sokratous is
wrestling with the Boeing 737
seconds later
flight 981 is diving
straight at the runway
oh my god
fire and emergency crews
rushed to the end of runway 22
aircraft punched a crater in the
runway about a meter and half deep
with
wreckage
wreckage through everywhere
fire-fighters battle the
flames through the night
but there's no one to be rescued
all 62 on-board flight
981 are killed in the crash
grieving families and the
world demand answers
hours after flight Dubai flight 981
crashes on the runway at Rostov-on-don
investigators from the IAC
The Interstate Aviation Committee
arrived on the scene
the IAC is the lead air
accident investigation agency
not just for Russia but for
several of the former soviet states
the IAC must find the
cause for the horrific tragedy
okay
that's great
that belongs over here
wreckage from flight 981 is
laid out in a nearby hanger
for closer inspection
a team from the united Arab
emirate assist in the investigation
so how fast did the
plane hit the ground?
the size of the debris would tell
weather it's a high speed impact
or it's low speed impact
there are clues in
pieces of wreckage
it's how much left of it
it was all small pieces
it describes a very high speed
and violent impact with the ground
it makes us question
what really happened
let's see it
investigators wonder how the plane
could have gathered so much speed
during an attempted landing
oh it's diving hard
security footage gives them a
look at the last moments of flight 981
flight 981 angle of descent
leads investigators to wonder
if the pilots were having
problems controlling their plane
maybe it's their
flight controls
you know I have seen it before
Boeing 737 flight control
have a problematic history
March the Th 1991
united airlines flight 585
banks hard right and crashes
while attempting to land
killing all on-board
3 years later it happens again
USA flight 427 roles left
and crashes near Pittsburgh
investigators with tearing
their out trying to figured it out
2 years passed without incident
then while on approach to land
the pilots of east-wind
airlines flight 517 lose control
this time the pilots regain
control of their plane
and land safely in
Richmond Virginia
the plane is intact
investigators get
their best lead yet
after 5 year of investigation
the national transportation
safety board concluded
that
a power unit in the rudder
that'd been responsible for
auto corner rudder hard over
the rudder head
moved to one side
and that caused the
aircraft to roll over
and then dive into the ground
movements of rudder
and other control surfaces
occur when pilots pushed
their rudder pedal or pull the yoke
power control units turns those
commands into actual movements
of the control surfaces
it's similar to the
power steering on a car
hey there
did you recover the PCUs?
investigators want to know if any
of flight 981's control units failed
yep
they're here
great
we need to test them
much of the Boeing
737 was destroyed
during high speed impact
but two of the power
control unit have survived
they could provide
crucial information
PCUs of the heart and soul of
the flight controls of the airplane
and one of the first
question is if you have
an airplane that came
a screaming out of sky
50 degree angle is
that we have a PCU
problem in the flight controls
investigators carefully
examine the PCUs of flight 981
they look for signs
of a malfunction
nothing wrong with the PCUs
they were extensively
examine and found
they have had absolutely no connection to
what brought this airplane out of the sky
with flight control
issues ruled out
the team turn to the
controller for insight
take me through what you saw
they were on final approach
flight 981
Rostov tower
you're clear to
land on runway 22
then they aborted
their first attempt to land
they reported wind-shear
Rostov tower
this is 981
we're conducting a go
around due to wind-shear
sky Dubai 981
make holding pattern
that you're convenience
they climbed and began holding
how long with the holding?
for a long time
investigators learned that the
pilots held for almost 2 hours
waiting for the
weather to improve
sky Dubai 981
request descent
for another approach
then they asked to land
but something went wrong when
the pilots made their second approach
Rostov tower
sky Dubai 981
we're going around
did they say why they were
going around the second time?
no
they just said going around
that's all
the next thing I knew the plane
was diving towards the runway
did they report any
problems with the plane?
no
nothing
IAC investigators
still can't explain
why flight 981 suddenly banked
and then dive into runway 22
something had gone wrong
on the second go around
but investigators
didn't know what
was there a problem
with the airplane?
did the pilots make a mistake?
there's no knowing yet
okay
two go arounds
one turns to disaster
why?
let's take a look
at the first one
investigators turn to FDR data
to better understand
why fly Dubai flight 981
performed one
successful go around
but crashed during the second
investigators
need to figure out
how the two go arounds
were different from each other
zoom a little bit
look
they confirmed the pilots
reacted to a wind shear alarm
during the first approach
how did they respond?
thrust jumps up to 102
so he applied max power
what about the flaps?
flaps are 30
and gear
remain down
textbook wind shear go around
pilot encounters a wind shear
he'll typically perform a what's
call a wind shear scape maneuver
and that involves increasing
the engine power to maximum
you leave a flaps down
you leave the gear down
wind shear ahead
wind shear go around
the first go around
was pretty routine
they responded appropriately
they did exactly what
they should have done
this
is the second go around
investigators analyze the
second attempt at landing
focusing in on the last
moments before the crash
now did they get another wind
shear warning at the second time?
no
nothing
look
there's leap in air speed
from 153 to 176 in seconds
10 seconds before the pilots abort
a sudden increase in the
plane's airspeed was recorded
investigators saw the airspeed
fluctuated for
more than 20 knots
within a few seconds
it's pretty strong gust of wind
they can see that on
the flight not a recorder
investigators determine that a
strong gust of winds struck the plane
you can feel the wind increase
on the nose of the airplane
it's probably also moving
the airplane a little bit left or right
it's not a pleasant
position to be in
how did the pilots
responds this time?
let me see
they added max power
okay
go around
and what about the
flaps and landing gear?
flaps are retracted
gear retracted
the data reveals that
on the second go around
the pilots performed
a different procedure
they didn't fly the wind shear scape
maneuver during the second go around
well looks like they were
doing a standard go around
on a standard go around
the flaps and landing
gear are retracted
except they did it at max power
given how streamline
the aircraft is
with the landing gear up
and the flaps largely retracted
using max power is
very much overkill
investigators conclude
that on the second attempt
the crew flew a
hybrid of two procedures
they used the power of a
wind shear escape maneuver
with the gear and flaps
settings of a traditional go around
so
what would that
do to the plane?
we need to take a look
at all the factors of plane
they're holding on
for nearly two hours
that's
4 tons of fuel they burnt
the weight of the Boeing 737 is a
critical factor in the plane's performance
adding the weight of the plane
total weight
that's 54 tons
it's light plane
yeah
at least weight
you know the crew would feel
a faster acceleration
max power
no drag
from flaps or landing gear
low weight
this plane could have been
accelerating dangerously fast
this is really an
accelerated situation
this is a very powerful
airplane doing something
that feels like you just
went into an after-burner
how much quicker did
this plane pickup speed
on the second go around
we need to do modeling on this
it was really incompetent
upon investigators to look further
and the question of acceleration
investigators turn to computer
modeling to answer a crucial question
here is all the data for the
first and second go around
how did the rate of acceleration
differ at the start of the two attempts?
first go around
speed increased by 17 knots
and the second
second go around
25 knot increase
lots of difference of 8 knots
between the two go arounds
yeah
it was a key part of the
findings when they realized that
over 40% difference existent
between the acceleration
from the first go around
to the second go around
could the increase in acceleration
have affected the pilots themselves?
they calculate the impact
of the second go around
wow
look at the backward force
experienced by the pilot
that faster acceleration
on the second go around
would have pushed
him back into the seat
the team also examines the
impact of vertical acceleration
g-force would have
lifted the pilots upwards
the pilot would have
felt a slight unweighted
he would come up out of seat
so
sudden acceleration like this
both horizontal and vertical
that tricks on your mind
were captain Sokratous's
senses his worse enemy?
maybe he experiences
Somatogravic Illusion
check your speed
okay
go around
a Somatogravic illusion
is a dangerous form
of special disorientation
when a plane accelerates quickly
with no visual reference of the horizon
the gravitational forces
cause a pitch up illusion
in the inner ear
the little hairs in the
inner ear bend backwards
tricking the brain into
thinking the head is tilting up
we might be going level
but if you cannot see outside
that sensation
on your vestibular system
is overwhelming and you know
you would really feel
that you're climbing up
the Somatogravic illusion is one
of the most lethal traps in aviation
keep the nose up
15 degrees
it's extremely
convincing illusion
what was the actual
pitch of the plane
after it accelerated during
the second go around
almost 20 seconds
after the actual pitch
was
8.8 degrees nose up
investigators look for evidence
that the pilots of flight 981
became severely
disoriented in the dark
if you imagine that
this glass of water
represents the fluid in your ear
if you accelerated this
along a smooth surface
the water would be pushed
up against the back of the glass
very much
like this
in other words
it's the same effect
as if you simply
tilted the glass
if you take visual
information of why
what tends to
happen is that the pilot
forgets about the acceleration
and assumes that
everything he's feeling
is due to the pitch
and what was the
pilots perceived pitch?
combining the horizontal and vertical
acceleration experienced by the pilot
we can calculate the pitch
that is perceived by the pilot
this is called the
illusionary pitch
pilot's perceived pitch was
21.6 degrees
they compare the plane's actual
pitch to the pilot's illusionary pitch
during the second go around
10 seconds later
the plane's pitch up 3.9 degrees
and
the pilot perceived it to be
26.7 degrees nose up
wow
that's huge difference
this puts the captain
into a situation
that he potentially will be
experiencing Somatogravic illusion
the captain is feeling one thing
but the aircraft is
doing something else
look at this
nearly end of the flight
the actual pitch is 7.6 degrees
and the perceived pitch
becomes well over 40
investigators
discover 3 instances
where there was a
dramatic difference
between the plane's actual
and the pilot's perceived pitch
keep at 15 degrees
nose up
it's evidence that the pilots may have
experienced the Somatogravic illusion
during the second go around
could the feeling of
the rapid acceleration
have effected how the
pilots flew the plane?
they dig deeper
into the flight data
well the captain push
forward on the yoke
he was trying to pitch
the plane downward
that's what his senses
were telling him to do
the captain responding
more to his feelings
than the what he was seeing on
any instrumentation in front of it
he decides that he needs
to push the airplane forward
and counteract this
massive pitch-up
he's trying to save
them by pitching down
wow
check this out
he pushed the
stabilizer trim down
from the data
investigators see the captain
didn't just push the yoke
be careful
captain applies the stabilizer trim
because
he's trying to push the
nose of the aircraft down
wait
for how long?
he held the trim
switch for 12 seconds
holding the switch for
12 seconds is unheard of
that shouldn't
never be held for
that about of time
the team discovers that
instead of pitching up to climb
the captain is pitching
the plane towards the ground
no no no
eventually putting the
plane into a fatal dive
the sudden change
in direction is jarring
at that time you would feel
like you're in a roller coaster
you know when you're
coming up to the pick as
you were diving at speed
is similar to that sensation
the pitch down has another
disorienting effect on the pilot's senses
pitching down of the aircraft
would have caused by the captain
and the first officer
to experience a dramatic
change in the g-forces
oh my god
that would increase the
confusion in the cockpit
as to what's going on
investigators conclude that the
various g-forces on captain Sokratous
caused his complete
spacial disorientation
the captain push in
and pull in on the yoke
stumping on the rudder
into dive you know
that shows confusion
he's probably disoriented
you know he's trying desperately to
get out of the sensation that he's feeling
but there's one question
that steel troubles investigators
was the first officer
feeling the illusion as well?
even though the accelerations
experienced by both pilots was the same
the perception of what
is happening can differ
and that can be due
to many different factors
expectations
what did they looking at?
their age
their experience
start at the second
go around please
the cockpit voice recorder
could tell investigators
if the first officer was also under the
influence of the Somatogravic illusion
okay
go around
careful
no no no
don't do that
he sees something wrong
no
pull it
he's telling to
pull back the yoke
pull it
if he's feeling the same
illusion as the captain
it sure doesn't seem
like he was affected by
the first officer knew almost
trouble the aircraft was in
knew the captain wasn't
responding the way he should
oh my god
investigators are left wondering
why the first officer didn't intervene
you look at this first officer
trying his best and wonder
why didn't you just take control
and say I've got the airplane
he's been the flying
737800 for nearly two years
he's fully certified
investigators looking to
the first officer's background
to understand why he
didn't take control of flight 981
when he saw that the captain
was making grave mistakes
look
his trainer wrote notes
on his assessment
and this one is telling
they find notes left by
one of his flight instructors
that alarmed them
one thing that could have
possibly saved that aircraft was
discovered in a note that was
left behind by the flight instructor
he needs to be a bit more assertive
in what is needed from the captain
and he continues
tell him what you want done and do
not wait for the captain inquire with you
or direct you in this regard
he's not the type
to take control
no
pull it
pull it pull it pull it
the first officer could see that
the captain was experiencing
enormous problems trying
to control the go around
he really should have taken
some decisive action and intervene
my god
I still don't
understand something
why did they try to land
the plane in the first place?
the big mystery was why was this crew
so determine to land on Rostov-on-done
when every other flight
had already diverted
storm was pummeling
Rostov-on-done airport
as flight 981 circled above
why didn't the pilots
divert to another airport?
investigators look for answers
in the cockpit voice recording
sky Dubai 981
for your information
previous flight went
to alternative airports
say other flights diverted
there's no need
I'm gonna keep flying
investigators just
couldn't understand
why they wanted
to fly and circles for
almost two hours
I'm gonna try this approach
and if I can't make it
we'll have a go around
and I will head to
Mineralnye Vody
okay
okay captain
understood
who's talking to?
the dispatcher on Dubai
investigators finally get an
indication of the captain's rational
for attempting another landing
as the captain decides
whether to divert
he contacts flight
Dubai flight dispatcher
in the united Arab emirates
we would like to recommend
you hold max as possible
dispatchers manage
the entire fleets operation
for specific airline
the dispatcher and the captain
are coequally responsible
for the safety of the flight
there is a very delicate dance
that goes on between and among
the dispatchers and the captains
the captain follows with the
dispatcher's recommendation
minuter turns to hours as the
pilot wait for a chance to land
I don't know man if we divert
we're gonna exceed our flying hours
what are you looking at?
Max Duty Hours
he's calculating his duty hours
regulations limit how
many hours pilots can fly
during a duty period
near the five and
a half hours now
the team learns that the pilots were
concern they might exceed their duty hours
stop
roll the map
they've been flying
for at least 5 hours
it'll take another hour to
reach their alternative airport
wait out the storm
then they start to get back to
Rostov-on-Don before returning to Dubai
diverting would put them
over their duty hours for the day
right
I think it can be clear by the
time we do this approach now
and even if we start now
I think we'll be good
we'll be good
okay
is he landing because it's clear
or
because he wants
to get on the ground
the conversation on the flight deck
before the second approach
clearly showed that
they weren't really thinking so
much about the safety of the landing
just the fact that
they wanted to land
I think I can give it a try
I agree
let's try
stop the recording
so they decide to
circle for two hours
after a four hour flight
in the middle of the night
did the long flight affect the pilot's
ability to land the plane safely?
two hours of hold
six hours total time
aren't we see decline in the decision
making capability because of fatigue?
tired?
no
as investigators break
down flight 981's journey
from Dubai to Rostov-on-don
they identify a glaring problem
they were actually in
here for more than 6 hours
it's almost 5:00AM their
time when they're landing
the Circadian Rhythm is
body's natural alignment
with the day and night cycle
the quad period is
roughly for four hour period
between 2 in the morning
and 6 in the morning
that's the point of which your mental
ability is pretty much at is lowest
I think I can give it a try
I agree
let's try
investigators determine the crew
was suffering from operational fatigue
as they launch their
second approach
good evening
your first officer here
we'll be landing shortly
once again we
apologize for the delay
the decision to make a second
attempt to land at Rostov-on-don
triggers a chain of events
that ends catastrophe
check your speed
as the aircraft is
hit by some wind
the crew is forced into
executing another go around
okay
go around
and this time
it was all gonna go wrong
captain Sokratous executes
a wind shear go around
pushing the throttle
to max power
the first officer performs
a standard go around
retracting the flaps and
raising the landing gear
both pilots were essentially flying
two different airplanes from there
this blunder factors heavily
into the catastrophe that followed
flight 981 climbs from
Rostov-on-don at high speed
when you light on fuel
and you put the max thrust
you will accelerate
it's what happened in the last
few seconds that doomed flight 981
keep it at 50 degrees
goes up
at this moment captain
Sokratous fights an inner battle
acceleration the aircraft
makes captain feels as though
the aircraft is pitching up
a lot more than actually is
spacial orientation
deteriorates rapidly
your vestibular senses
your middle ear
are all telling you
the wrong thing
the captain counters the pitch up
feeling of a Somatogravic Illusion
by pushing the yoke forward
the captain has lost touch with the reality
of what is happening to the airplane
then the final blow
the captain holds that stabilizer trim
button down for about 12 seconds
with the sudden forcing
of the aircraft nose down
and stabilizer trim
the aircraft transitions
from the climb
very suddenly
into a dive
the aircraft is now in a
very dangerous situation
which the captain is
unable to overcome
my god
they're accelerating rapidly
and first officer finally gets
on the yoke and tries to pull
but the controls on the left
side govern where the airplane is
and even to a certain point
and there's no recovery
nose diving at full
throttle towards the runway
captain Sokratous is
completely disoriented
when he adds rudder
at the last moment
he's lost all awareness
of how the plane is flying
pilots in this case were
conducting the flight very well
right up until those
last few moments
and then
it already just fell apart
the IAC investigation
into the crash of flight 981
is a landmark case of
how spacial disorientation
can end in disaster
this accident is wake-up call for the
industry as one of the accident
that pay for the
way into increase
training in spatial
disorientation
in the final report
investigators blame the
captain's string of errors
on his diminished
psychological state
the IAC recommends that fly
Dubai provide better training
on the manual
operation of stabilizer trim
so the pilots don't make
the same mistake again
researching to human factors
including situations like this
where disorientation likely occurred
is at the forefront of
aviation safety research
we are training our
pilots on simulators
to experience these illusions
before they experience in this
so they can recognize
those situations
I think the flight Dubai
accident shows how quickly
your senses can overtake you
and one of the key lesson is
the pilots to
trust in their instruments
to take a step back from what
may they think they're experiencing
to actually understand
what the airplane is doing
you've gotta keep
the airplane flying