one of the world's most sophisticated war
planes speeds down the runway at Guam
rotate
their mission that day
was to return home
but the take off
ends in disaster
a two billion dollar stealth
bomber goes up in flames
we wanna know what
the heck just happened
the entire fleet is grounded
this could be the end of
the B-2 bomber program
plane goes full nose up
investigators analyze
the flight second by second
what about this?
and discover a hidden vulnerability
in the B-2's electronic armor
there is no way a pilot would
understand the system well enough
to realize what could happen
what is going on?
you good to go sir
thank you
Major Ryan Link and
Captain Justin Grieve
are ending a four month
deployment in Guam
better
yeah
looks good
okay
let's head home then
copy that
Andersen air force base is both a
training facility and the launching point
for US military operations
in the western pacific
generator one is on
engine's ground idle
27 percent confirmed
back to Missouri Missouri
their mission that day
was to return home
our time was up in Guam
and
they were beginning a
16 hour continuous flight
back to Knob Noster Missouri
Whiteman Air Force Base
which was our home base
they're one of two crews
returning home today
in a unique war plane
the B-2 bomber
it was flying wing design
and really a marvel
of engineering
the air force ended up spending
44 billion dollars to
develop and then field
the fleet of B-2 bombers
developed in the 1980
during the cold war
the stealth bomber was
designed to evade soviet radar
there are only 21
of them in existence
it can sneak in, with much
less chance of being detected
either by enemy surface
to air missile defenses or
enemy fighters
tower
that's 5
start-up is complete
you can activate our flight plan
refueling number one will
be at ARCP charlie at 07350
expecting to unload
51,000 pounds
control point charlie
copy
today the 7000 mile journey
home from Guam
will require the crew to
refuel near the Hawaii islands
and then over California
before reaching Whiteman
Air Force Base in Missouri
Major Link is a qualified
instructor on the B-2
Captain Grieve is
an experienced pilot
with more than 2500 hours
of military flying experience
they are among only 300
pilots qualified to fly the B-2
the aviators in the B-2 at that
time are absolute best of the best
they were hand-picked
they were vetted extensively
they were truly in
elite group of aviators
Grieve and Link are
second in line to take off
the plane they're flying
is named spirit of Kansas
every B-2 bomber is named
after an individual state
except for two
there is spirit of America
and spirit of Kitty Hawk
that's 6+1
clear for take off
maintain 5000
pitot heat is on
clear right
go to line up
the pilots must carefully maneuver
the massive 168 ton bomber
to the foot of the runway
to ensure they don't put
any dents in the B-2's shell
try to taxi slowly
because you're low
observable platform
so
obviously
if you scrape the airplane
you degrade the capability
of the war fighting machine
that's 5
go channel 5
that's 5 copy
channel 5
that's 5
our lead is airborne
we're going 60
on this flight captain Grieve
is the mission commander
what's different is
the captain
like you would think the aircraft
commander is actually on the right seat
we call them a mission commander
and the pilot is
in the left seat
first MCT
the very first time I flew
the B-2 I felt like I was a bird
it was so smooth
you just slightly touch
the flight controls
and she does what you want
what was that?
FCS caution
stop or go?
go
warning rescinding
in the B-2, there's two
different kind of caution lines
the red one and yellow one
in this case it was yellow
which is just precautionary
a red caution light you
probably abort the take off
rotate
spirit of Kansas lifts
off the runway at Guam
almost immediately the massive
bomber pitches up dramatically
next thing they know
they're going straight up
the momentum of that maneuver up
cause the pilots to
experience about 1.6 G
their aircraft don't want to do
what is was supposed to be doing
full power
the B-2 isn't gaining altitude
it's still only 80
feet off the ground
and losing speed
make believe you're in
your automobile right now
you turn left but
that car turns right
what is going on?
that's not the way
he supposed to work
that's the scenario
these pilots were in
the pilots now feel their
airplane shaking violently
and realize it's on
the verge of stalling
from my 50 years flying the B-2
the only time I felt the B-2
shake is in the simulator
that's the only scenario
when you would feel that shake
you never feel it otherwise
the plane's left wing drops
Grieve knows the plane
is heading for the ground
there is only one thing he can
do to save his and major link's life
they are trained to have that God
feel of when to pull the ejection handle
and don't forget the air force wants
these pilots to eject and save themselves
there's no shame in ejecting ever
even from a billion dollar bomber
Grieve doesn't have time
to think about his decision
the B-2's left wing is
now scraping the ground
we're gonna get out
explosive tear a hole in the
fuselage above the cockpit
and rockets eject the
pilots from the aircraft
the stealth bomber hits the
ground and burst into flames
alert one
runway 6 romeo
I'm stunned
the B-2 is gone through 19
years and 3 wars without a crash
this is unheard of
one of the world's most advanced
warplanes has been incinerated
during a routine take off
the whole world is left
wondering what went wrong
for two straight days
fire fighters at Anderson air-force base
in Guam battle the flaming wreckage
of B-2 bomber spirit of Kansas
with the price tag
of 2 billion dollars
this is the most expensive
aviation accident of all time
crash at Guam did
shake us to the core in the
we wanna know what
the heck just happen?
operations of the entire
B-2 fleet are suspended
even before an
investigation is launched
it's bad
to have to stand down
the B-2 flying operations
on the other hand
they have no choice
they have no idea what's
going wrong inside that B-2
and they have to find out
before they risk any
more B-2s in flight
US air force appoints the well
respected general floyd carpenter
to lead the investigation
because of the high
profile nature of this accident
I think they expect a
lot of media interest
and so as a senior
greater general
I was picked I think to get the airplanes
back operational and clear to fly again
you never gonna believe this
investigators watch the
accident unfold on security video
great to have the video
and we were able to glean
a lot of information from it
video of the take off shows
that as the plane lifted off
it pitched nose high
your first reaction when you
see that airplane pitched up
is like
what are they doing?
the plane then drifts left
before the left wing
scrapes the ground
left wing falls off
and hits the ground
and through that whole
thing you were thinking
where is the crew?
first time you see it
you quite don't realize
the crew actually ejects
can you take it
back for me please?
stop
that's the pilots
one and two
the video shows the pilots ejecting
just as the plane hits the ground
both pilots had been taken
to hospital for evaluation
Justin Grieve has suffered
a serious back injure
from the forces of ejection
it was a waiting process for us and
gathering all the other information
while we waited to talk to them and
hear their side of what really happened
investigator study the mechanical
and computer systems that control the jet
perfect
what about the actuator?
we had so much of the
aircraft already available
actuators, engines
all those things
what you're really looking
for in this type of accident
they quickly determine that all of
the plane's flight control surfaces
were functioning on take off
pretty quickly we were
able to rule out the fact
that the engines
were not a problem
the hydraulics were not problem
the flight controls were not problem
I pulled these from the video
up
it's a beautiful sunny morning
why does a bomber
pitches nose up and
crashed in a fireball
on the runway at Guam?
is this a weighting
balance issue?
many deployment like that is
not uncommon to load aircraft
with spare parts
or other equipment that
you might wanna get home
and not wait to ship home
some classified material
going back to white man
personal belongings
gear
so center gravity
became a big issue for us
could it have been that?
not enough to disrupt
their balance there
the B-2 is capable of carrying
40,000 pounds of weaponry
but spirit of Kansas
wasn't carrying any bombs
or other heavy cargo that
could have shift if on take off
we found up that there
really wasn't a lot of equipment
there were no
ammunitions being carried
so everything was in
balance as it should have been
and so center gravity
was ruled out pretty quick
investigators look more closely
at the take off rolls of both B-2s
on the day of the accident
for clues as to why spirit of
Kansas couldn't get airborne
like the plane just ahead of it
spirit of south Carolina
okay
pause it
right there
okay
so south Carolina lifts off
just passed that taxi way
right above here
because we didn't have video
we had to look at
take off roll of
this lead aircraft
compare to the second aircraft
and
stop
okay, our guys
lift off just passed
that
runway light which is this guy
right here
look at that
we found out that spirit of Kansas took off
1500 feet shorter than its lead aircraft
what is going on?
again video helped us understand
that take off roll was shorter
but didn't understand why?
the investigators turn to data from
the bomber's flight recorder for answers
the plane is still on the
ground 546 feet above see level
not 682
so the altitude is off by 136 feet
now sir there is no way
he got up to 145 knots
using only this much runway
agreed
something happened and
causes airplane to pitch up
but so far we've ruled
out all the easy stuff
and so now we start looking into
other situations that could have cause
aircraft to do what it did
no here sir
the noses lifting off the ground
but the plane registers a
pitch down of -8 degrees
now obviously
this plane is not pitching down
but the computer thinks it is
that's why it tried to lift the
nose higher and higher and higher
until it stalled
once we got performance
parameters of the aircraft
we were able to determine that
the airplane thought that it was
-8 degrees angle of attack
then you start going back
to say why did it think that
the heart of the B-2 bomber is
its sophisticated on board computer
known as its flight
control system
or FCS
without it
it would be impossible the pilots to
make all the calculation necessary
to keep the unusual
aircraft flying
you don't have a tail
think about that
you don't have any kind
of vertical empennage
it's just a big flying wing
accurate data is crucial
on a B-2 pilots tell the computer
what they want the plane to do
and the computer determines
how to accomplish that
the flight computers move
the surfaces of this airplane
in a way that's not intuitive to
any pilot of any other aircraft
simply but it'd be nearly
impossible to fly this airplane safely
without flight computers
so
air speed, climb angle,
and altitude are all off
how does that
happen on this plane?
investigators need to determine why
the stealth bomber was getting faulty data
let's see what the
pilots can tell us
we weren't looking to blame them
or you know point a finger at them
but there were tough
questions to ask
three weeks after the accident
the pilots of spirit of Kansas agreed
to be interviewed by investigators
okay captain
how about we
take it from the top?
started up at 9:15
a few minutes later major Links called
the calibration message during start up
the pilots tell investigators that they
received an unusual computer message
shortly after start up
never seen that
me neither
hey chief we're seeing
air data cal message
can you send someone
up here to clear that up?
air data cal stands
for air data calibration
in a simplest term
the air data calibration gives the
aircraft its orientation to the universe
there are 24 sensors flush
mounted near the nose of the B-2
that constantly
measure air pressure
the planes computer uses
those readings to calculate
altitude, air speed
and angle of attack
all 24 system have
memory in them
and they're measuring
themselves against all the others
and so if they get
out of the balance
if one is reading
too low or two high
it calls for an air
data calibration
and the pilots see that
when that occurs
they call out maintenance
okay
let's see what we can
do to clear this for you
can you put it in
maintenance mode for me?
that's good
you good to go sir
thank you
so they have these 24 sensors, they
make sure they communicating correctly
and if they do
they let it go forward
pitot heat is on
less than an hour later
clear right
go to line up
the pilots maneuver the massive
bomber to the start of the runway
okay
go on
everything was 100 percent
routine until we get a 100 knots
that's when we got
the FCS master caution
you got a master caution
while you're still on the ground
yes sir
just a flicker
100 knots
before I even push the
button it rescind itself
what was that?
FCS caution
after a 100 knots to our
decision road take speed
we will abort for
safety of flight items
we define safety of flight as
we're unable to control this airplane
or there is something on the
road where you're gonna hit
stop or go?
go
warning rescinded
in that scenario, if I was the
pilot in command, I will continue
why
it's not safety of flight
145 rotate
when we hit 145
I call for major Link to rotate
then it all very
quickly went to hell
they lift off
the flight control computer's
sensors are problem, so it pitches up
pilots try to go nose down
full power
they go max power but
the airplane is trying to stall
major link is trying to push it
back down, but it wasn't working
it doesn't have any
effect in the plane
we were basically
just belong for the ride
and then the left
wing just drops
and I know we're done
we gotta get out
then I pulled the handles
if the airplane did not
performed as advertise
there was time
for them to get out
and get the airplane
back to the tax payers
thank you
for your time today captain
thank you sir
they were extremely force
coming in their testimony
they survived it
but they had no understanding
of what happened either
investigators need to know more
about the calibration that
grieve reported in his testimony
it's not part of the plane's
regular start up procedure
if a sensor provides a reading
that differ significantly from others
a recalibration is done
that tells the wayward
sensors how much they're off
in order to bring them back
into agreement with the others
these three were
just off by little
they are way off
and they need a very big adjustment
to get them align with the rest
and were not sure why sir
100 knots
a master caution alarm
that flickered on for a few
seconds just before take off
becomes a key
piece of the puzzle
at that point we
really didn't know
how they related but
we figured they might be
there was too much coincidence starting
to happen that pointed to these things
what was that?
FCS caution
3 calibrated sensors started
providing faulty data again
six seconds later
stop or go?
go
the flight computer resolve the discrepancy
between the sensors and cancel the warning
what is going on with
this plane sensors?
they have a mystery
flaw in the B-2
puts the 59th and the
air force under a lot of pressure
they have to find out exactly what
went wrong with the flight controls
in order to return that
fleet to safe operations
and the world will
be watching them
okay
so
let's start at the top
why they need to
recalibrate in the first place?
it was a procedure that a
lot of pilots had never seen
and maintainers
didn't do very often
investigators look for any
abnormalities in the mission
that might have had an
effect on the B-2 sensors
hah
so
they got delayed by a day
what it happened was?
Whiteman Air Force Base in
Missouri had severe snow storm
it was snowing quite heavily
visibility was near zero
so what we did is we delayed
the mission to come home
24 hours
spirit of Kansas was
left on the tarmac
while the pilots waited
to resume the mission
okay
so the jet was left outside for
24 hours because of the delay
so what
check the weather
second the last page
holy smokes
that is one hell a lot of rain
weather record showed that a tropical
rain storm settled over the airbase
the night before the accident
tell me
rain storm didn't take down
a two billion dollar airplane
decisions were made and
these B-2s were left outside
in this particularly
heavy rain storm
okay
let's flood these two
investigators run
tests on B-2's sensors
to determine the effect
rain may have had on them
and stop
gotta be kidding me
tests confirmed that the sensors
exposed to the heaviest rain fall
got saturated and
needed recalibrating
even prior to that
when it was in
test in development
we've never experienced
that much rain on the system
so no one really knew how
that would adversely effect
the operations of the B-2
the reason no one realize
how heavy rain effect the B-2
is the it's almost always
parked inside a hanger
at white man air
force base over night
even if it's flying a mission
over Afghanistan or Libyan
it returns to Missouri
the B-2's occasional deployment to
Guam presented different weather conditions
could heavy rain be the simple
explanation for this accident?
this would not have happened
in a the desert environment
this would not have
happened at whiteman
but Guam is very unique
they left the B-2 parked
out all night in the rain
the moisture got in there
see something
just doesn't add up
they did the recalibration
you good to go sir
but they still ended
up with faulty data
that nearly kill them
yeah
full power
state of the art military
jet put itself into a stall
because it was getting faulty
data about its climb angle
investigators still don't know why
the B-2 is always operated under
so much pressure and scrutiny
if they can’t figure out what
went wrong that day in Guam
honestly
this could be the end of
the B-2 bomber program
okay
so
they recalibrate at
09:34
nearly an hour later
the master caution lights up
because of an air data issue
so
what happens in
those 56 minutes?
investigators review what the
pilots told them about the flight
routine taxi
they hit the pitot heat
wait for the timer
and they're off
so
what about this?
they are small heaters connected
to each of the plane's sensors
just before take off
the pilots activate the heaters
so the sensors don't freeze up
when the plane reaches cooler
temperature at higher altitudes
we can't take off advanced the
power and go down the runway
until we put the pitot heat on
pitot heat is on
it's essential that those
sensors are getting heated
investigators wonder
if the pitot heat
could have effected
the recalibrated sensors
clear right
go to line up
we didn't know enough
to really put them together
and so we had to go get better
understanding of the system
and we did that
through engineers that
actually build the system
he saw the frequency of our calibration
he was surprised and concerned
and then
they turn on pitot heat
when they get to the runway
and then he was really
concerned when he saw
and understood
like he only could
that with moisture in the system
and the data we put into it to fix it
could cause such a problem
on the day of the accident
turning on the pitot heat had a
consequence that no one anticipated
recalibrating the sensors brought
the 3 wet ones in line with the others
but turning on the pitot heat
boiled away the moisture
bringing the sensors
back out of alignment
first MCT
so the data that was put in on
the calibration now, is invalid again
and the flight computers now try to
resolve the issue with these sensors
but the discovery doesn't explain
another key event, during short flight
what was that?
FCS caution
why did the faulty air data warning
disappears 6 seconds after it came on?
stop or go?
go
warning rescinded
it's seconds from take off
US air force investigators looking to
the logic guiding the B-2's flight computer
so it has to make choice
the flight data computer
needs a solution
and what we mean by that is
it can't spend even a
second or a milliseconds
wondering where it is?
and what needs to be done?
the B-2's flight computer is constantly
receiving four separate data stream
from all 24 sensors
if there is a discrepancy in
the values of those channels
the computer is programmed to
select any two of the channels to proceed
it just chose wrong
yeah, we should fix that
it's not voting is to
throw out bad data
what they think is bad data
keep the good data
and it resolves the issue
the light goes away
the flight computers
are now good to go
and so the pilots are now, okay
well that must just have been a glitch
let's keep going
stop or go?
go
warning rescinded
the flight computers chose the two channels
that included the faulty sensor data
rotate
12 seconds later
the plane pitched up abnormally
because of the faulty
air data readings
once they rotated the aircraft
on speed as they thought
and left the ground
they along for the
ride at that point
but if we calibrating the plane's
sensors before turning on the pitot heat
can be catastrophic
why was that the
official procedure?
so hardly any of all that
investigators learn that
recalibration are rarely done
while the B-2 is at its
home base in Missouri
but during a deployment
in Guam in 2006
maintenance personnel were
performing frequent recalibration
copy that
I'm on my way
they knew there was a challenge
bu they didn't what it was
and they did speculate that
because of the weather in Guam
raining a lot more than at home
that it might be an
issue of moisture
technicians in Guam spoke
to an engineer in the US
who suggested a procedure to
remedy the frequent air data calibrations
yeah, then we have to do
an on-board recalibration
they were able to talk
to an engineer that said
well before you do
a data calibration
try turning on the pitot heat
and burning that
water out of the system
and see if that
will take care of it
I haven't tried that
good idea though
the technician passed
on the suggestion
to the B-2 pilots in Guam
try turning on your pitot
heat before your second step
copy
apparently I should do it
yep, but
our guys didn't do that
can you think of a reason why?
investigators learned from
technicians at Whiteman Air Force Base
that the procedure
for activating pitot heat
in response to an air-data
calibration message
was not officially adopted
really
why the heck not?
some crews knew about it
some did not
pilots back in whiteman
who were not there
never heard of it and
maintainers had never heard of it
there is nothing
there is nothing anywhere about using pitot
heat when a calibration message appears
you good to go sir
neither Ryan Link
Justin Grieve
nor the maintainer
assigned to their plane
was ever told about
the moisture issue
or the informal
procedure for rectifying it
better
yeah looks good
the maintainers that morning
were following the tech orders
which tell them
exactly what to do
in the preflight
but for some reason
this new work around to
compensate for the moisture
just hadn't made
it into the manual
and that's a
little bit of tragedy
so
these three are wrong
what if they used pitot
heat instead of recalibrating?
they would have burned
off the excess moisture
that solved the problem
no faulty air data
no accident
if information had been shared
from previous deployment 2006
to 2008
this accident could
have been prevented
hey chief for seeing
an air data cal message
can you send someone
up here to clear that up?
the maintenance personnel that
came out to the aircraft that day
of the accident
did everything exactly right
they were just doing the
procedure they were taught
it doesn't seem like
anybody understood
what this recalibration could do
the investigation has
uncovered the catastrophic gap
in the B-2 crews
understanding of the link
between calibrating sensors
and flight controls
rotate
there is no way a pilot or a maintainer
would understand the system well enough
to realize what
could have happened
and they did that
data calibration
that lack of understanding
left the crew of spirit of Kansas
vulnerable to the
effects of the faulty data
investigators now wonder
if there was something that pilots
could have done to save their plane
18 seconds
to get this plane
under control
was it even possible?
investigators reexamine
the crash sequence
to see if the pilots of the
B-2 bomber spirit of Kansas
could have prevented their
aircraft from crashing at Guam?
rotate
certainly
no B-2 pilot wanted to be
the first to eject from a B-2
plane goes full nose up
he pushes full forward
and goes full power
plane starts rolling left
he applies right stick
he's fighting
investigators determine that
major link took the correct action
to save the B-2 bomber
but because of its low
altitude and slow speed
disaster was unavoidable
ultimately this was a no
win situation with the crew
as we determine
with hundreds and hundreds
of simulations afterwards
no one could have flown
this aircraft out of that situation
the data also shows just how close
the pilots came to losing their lives
they are seconds
away from impact
and
they still hadn't
pulled the handle
if they had delayed even
a fraction of second later
to eject
they both likely would
not have survived
the video of the accident
shows that the plane's left wing
was already scraping the
ground when the pilots ejected
we've gotta get out
they're heroes in the sense that
there guys waited to the
very last possible second
I don't know if many other
people that can say that they waited
till the wing tip hit the
ground before ejecting
can you imagine that?
all pilots in the
air force are good
or maybe great
but these guys were
truly outstanding
and they were very very close
despite everything
to actually saving that aircraft
one of the most sophisticated
warplanes on earth
was brought down by a
combination of poor whether
who would have guessed
that a little bit of moisture
would have led to all theses
and poor communications
which left Grieve and Link
without understanding
recalibrating their sensors
could lead to a serious
flight control issue
100 knots
this accident didn't
happened because of bad data
not because of bad software
not because of bad weather
not because of
bad decision making
it happened because
of bad communication
in the end safety is everything
it doesn't matter
if it's an airliner
a fighter jet
a space plane or stealth bomber
full power
safety is critical and safety
depends on communication
the air force investigation
underscores the need for pilots
to be kept informed about their
technology controlling their airplanes
do really really
wanted to leave the defense of your
families your children your grand children
to a computer
or do you want to leave it to
the brightest asset that we have
and that is the human brain
in spite of being involved in the most
expensive aviation disaster in history
Major Ryan Link and
Captain Justin Grieve
went on to have
successful military careers
the B-2 was back in the air
two month after the crash
the flight computer
was redesigned
to prevent faulty air data
the procedure for using pitot heat
instead of recalibrating the sensors
is documented in air force
manuals and technical documents
there hasn't been an issue
with faulty air data since
Northrop produced
an amazing aircraft
then I commend them
and the maintainers
and the aviators that
continue to make the B-2
the envy to the world